Let Not the Sun

It began delightfully: “Where are you going for your holiday, Bill?” his sister asked casually one day at tea, someone having mentioned a trip to Italy; “climbing, I suppose, as usual?” And he had answered just as casually, “Climbing, yes, as usual.”

They were both workers, she a rich woman’s secretary, and he keeping a stool warm in an office. She was to have a month, he a bare three weeks, and this summer it so happened, the times overlapped. To each the holiday was of immense importance, looked forward to eagerly through eleven months of labour, and looked back upon afterwards through another long eleven months. Frances went either to Scotland or some little pension in Switzerland, painting the whole time, and taking a friend of similar tastes with her. He went invariably to the Alps. They had never gone together as yet, because—well, because she painted and he climbed. But this year a vague idea had come to each that they might combine, choosing some place where both tastes might be satisfied. Since last summer there had been deaths in the family; they realised loneliness, felt drawn together like survivors of a wreck. He often went to tea with her in her little flat, and she accompanied him sometimes to dinner in his Soho restaurants. Fundamentally, however, they were not together, for their tastes did not assimilate well, and their temperaments lacked that sympathy which fuses emotion and thought in a harmonious blend. Affection was real and deep, but strongest when they were apart.

Now, as he walked home to his lodgings on the other side of London, he felt it would be nice if they could combine their holidays for once. Her casual question was a feeler in the same direction. A few days later she repeated it in a postscript to a letter: “Why not go together this year,” she wrote, “choosing some place where you can climb and Sybil and I can paint? I leave on the 1st; you follow on the 15th. We could have two weeks in the same hotel. It would be awfully jolly. Let me know what you feel, and mind you are quite frank about it.”

They exchanged letters, discussed places, differed mildly, and agreed to meet for full debate. The stage of suggestion was past; it was a plan now. They must decide, or go separately. One of them, that is to say, must take the responsibility of saying No. Frances leaned to the Engadine—Maloja—whereas her brother thought it “not a bad place, but no good as a climbing centre. Still, Pontresina is within reach, and there are several peaks I’ve never done round Pontresina. We’ll talk it over.” The exchange of letters became wearisome and involved, because each wrote from a different point of view and feeling, and each gave in weakly to the other, yet left a hint of sacrifice behind. “It’s a very lovely part,” she wrote of his proposal for the Dolomites, “only it’s a long way off and expensive to get at, and the scenery is a bit monotonous for painting. You understand. Still, for two weeks—” while he criticised her alternative selections in the Rhone Valley as “rather touristy and overcrowded, don’t you think?—the sort of thing that everybody paints.” Both were busy, and wrote sometimes briefly, not making themselves quite plain, each praising the other’s choice, then qualifying it destructively at the end of apparently unselfish sentences with a formidable and prohibitive “but.” The time was getting short meanwhile. “We ought to take our rooms pretty soon,” wrote Frances. “Immediately, in fact, if we want to get in anywhere,” he answered on a letter-card. “Come and dine to-night at the Gourmet, and we’ll settle everything.”

They met. And at first they talked of everything else in the world but the one thing in their minds. They talked a trifle boisterously; but the boisterousness was due to excitement, and the excitement to an unnatural effort to feign absolute sympathy which did not exist fundamentally. The bustle of humanity about them, food, and a glass of red wine, gradually smoothed the edges of possible friction, however.

“You look tired, Bill.”

“I am rather,” he laughed. “We both need a holiday, don’t we?”

The ice was broken.

“Now, let’s talk of the Alps,” she said briskly.

“It’s been so difficult to explain in writing, hasn’t it?”

“Impossible,” he laughed, and pulled out of his pocket a sheet of notepaper on which he had made some notes. Frances took a Baedeker from her velvet bag on the hook above her head. “Capital,” he laughed; “we’ll settle everything in ten minutes.”

“It will be so awfully jolly to go together for once,” she said, and they felt so happy and sympathetic, so sure of agreement, so ready each to give in to the other, that they began with a degree of boldness that seemed hardly wise. “Say exactly what you think—quite honestly,” each said to the other. “We must be candid, you know. It’s too important to pretend. It would be silly, wouldn’t it?” But neither realised that this meant, “I’ll persuade you that my place is best and the only place where I could really enjoy my holiday.” Bill cleared a space before him on the table, lit a cigarette, and felt the joy of making plans in his heart. Francis turned the pages to her particular map, equally full of delight. What fun it was!

“All I want, Bill dear, is a place where I can paint—forests, streams, and those lovely fields of flowers. Almost anywhere would do for me. You understand, don’t you?”

“Rather,” he laughed, making a little more room for his own piece of paper, “and you shall have it, too, old girl. All I want is some good peaks within reach, and good guides on the spot. We’ll have our evenings together, and when I’m not climbing, we’ll go for picnics while you paint, and—and be awfully jolly all together. Sybil’s a nice girl. We shall be a capital trio.” He put her Baedeker at the far corner of the table for a moment.

“Oh, please don’t lose my place in it,” she said, pulling the marker across the page and leaving the tip out.

“I’m sorry,” he replied, and they laughed—less boisterously.

“You tell me your ideas first,” she decided, “and then I’ll tell you mine. If we can’t agree then, we’re not fit to have a holiday at all!”

It worked up with deadly slowness to the rupture that was inevitable from the beginning. Both were tired after, not a day’s, but a year’s work; both felt selfish and secretly ashamed; both realised also that an unsuccessful holiday was too grave a risk to run—it involved eleven months’ disappointment and regret. Yet, if this plan failed, any future holiday together would be impossible.

“After all,” sighed Frances peevishly at length, “perhaps we had better go separately.”

It was so tiring, this endless effort to find the right place; their reserve of vitality was not equal to the obstacles that cropped up everywhere. Full, high spirits are necessary to see things whole. They exaggerated details. “It’s funny,” he thought; “she might realise that climbing is what I need. One can paint everywhere!” But in her own mind the reflection was the same, turned the opposite way: “Bill doesn’t understand that one can’t paint anything. Yet, for climbing, one peak is just as good as another.” He thought her obstinate and faddy; she felt him stubborn and rather stupid.

“Now, old girl,” he said at length, pushing his papers aside with a weary gesture of resignation, having failed to convince her how admirable his choice had been, “let’s look at your place.” He laughed patiently, but the cushions provided by food and wine and excitement had worn thin. Friction increased; words pricked; the tide of sympathy ebbed—it had been forced really all along, pumped up; their tastes and temperaments did not amalgamate. Frances opened her Baedeker and explained mechanically. She now saw clearly the insuperable difficulties in the way, but for sentimental and affectionate reasons declined to be the first to admit the truth. She was braver, bigger than he was, but her heart prevented the outspoken honesty that would have saved the situation. He, though unselfish as men go, could not conceal his knowledge that he was so. Each vied with the other in the luxury of giving up with apparent sweetness, only the luxury was really beyond the means of either. With the Baedeker before them on the table, the ritual was again gone through—from her point of view, while in sheer weariness he agreed to conditions his strength could never fulfil when the time came. They met half-way upon Champéry in the Valais Alps above the Rhone. It satisfied neither of them. But speech was exhausted; energy flagged; the restaurant, moreover, was emptying and lights being turned out.

They put away Baedeker and paper, paid the bill, and rose to go, each keenly disappointed, each feeling conscious of having made a big sacrifice. On the steps he turned to help her put her coat on, and their eyes met. They felt miles apart. “So much for my holiday,” he thought, “after waiting eleven months!” and there was a flash of resentful anger in his heart. He turned it unconsciously against his sister.

“Don’t write for rooms till the end of the week,” he suggested. “I may think of a better place after all.”

It was the tone that stung her nerves, perhaps. She really hated Champéry—a crowded, touristy, “organised” place. Her sacrifice had gone for nothing. “Even now he’s not satisfied!” she realised with bitterness.

“Oh, if you don’t feel it’ll do, Bill, dear,” she answered coolly, “I really think we’d better give it up going together, I mean.” Her force was exhausted.

He felt sore, offended, injured. He looked sharply at her, almost glared. A universe lay between them now. Before there was time to reflect or choose his words, even to soften his tone, he had answered coldly:

“Just as you like, Frances. I don’t want to spoil your holiday. You’re right. We’d better go separately then.”

Nothing more was said. He saw her to the station of the Tube, but the moment the train had gone he realised that the final wave of her little hand betrayed somehow that tears were very close. She had not shown her face again. He felt sad, ashamed, and bitter. Deeper than the resentment, however, was a great ache in his heart that was pain. Remorse surged over him. He thought of her year of toil, her tired little face, her disappointment. Her brief holiday, so feverishly yearned for, would now be tinged with sadness and regret, wherever she went. Memory flashed back to their childhood together, when life smiled upon them in that Kentish garden. They were the only two survivors. Yet they could not manage even a holiday together. …

Though so little had been said at the end, it was a rupture … He went home to bed, planing a splendid reconstruction. Before they went to their respective workplaces in the morning he would run over and see her, put everything straight and sweet again, explaining his selfishness, perhaps, on the plea that he was overtired. He wondered, as he lay ashamed and sad upon his sleepless bed, what she was thinking and feeling now … and fell asleep at last with his plan of reconstruction all completed. His last conscious thought was—“I wish I had not let her go like that … without a nice goodbye!”

In the morning, however, he had not time to go; he postponed it to the evening, sending her a telegram instead: “Come dinner to-night same place and time. Have worked out perfect plan.” And all day long he looked forward eagerly to their meeting. Those childhood thoughts haunted him strangely—he remembered the enormous plans all had made together years ago in that old Kentish garden where the hopfields peered above the privet hedge and frightened them. There were five of them then; now there were only two.

But plans, large or small, are not so easily made. Fate does not often give two chances in succession. And Fate that day was very busy in and out among the London traffic. Frances, hopeful and delighted, kept the appointment—and waited a whole hour before she went anxiously to his flat to find out what was wrong. In the awful room she knew that Fate had made a different plan, and had carried it out. She was too late for him to recognise her, even. In the pocket of the coat he had been wearing she found a sheet of paper giving the names of hotels at Maloja, pension terms, and railway connections from London. She also found the letter he had written engaging the rooms. The envelope was addressed and stamped, but left open for her final approval. She keeps it still.

What she also keeps, however, more than the recollection of real, big quarrels that had come into their lives at other times, is the memory of the way they had left one another at that Tube station, and the horrid fact that she had gone home with resentment and unforgiveness in her heart. It was such a little thing at the moment. But the big, formidable quarrels had been adjusted, made up, forgotten, whereas this other regret would burn her till she died. “We were so cross and tired. But it might so easily have been different. If only … I had not left him … just like that … !”

Lost in the Alps

There was something unusual in the village street that morning as I made my way to the chalet post-office to send a telegram, but the mind was only vaguely aware of it. A familiar detail seemed lacking: a difference had crept in. One noticed it — no more than that. Sunshine flooded the valley, the forests hung in purple shadow to the west, far overhead the snow shone dazzling against the turquoise blue, and the air was filled with the roar of falling water. Girls in yellow jumpers were going down to the tennis courts, tourists starting on their expeditions, mules clattering on the cobbles, and the Priest went by, his face, as always, grave.

All seemed as usual: the difference did not disclose itself. My mind, perhaps, was too preoccupied composing a complicated telegram in the fewest possible words to think about it. It was on my way back that I suddenly realized what was wrong: the familiar groups of guides, waiting for employ ment, were omitted from the picture. Something had happened.

A high Alpine climbing village is a sensitive organism, whose collective life responds swiftly to the least change a new arrival, a departure, a summit conquered, but above all an accident. The news runs through it like a wind. On the way back to my friend's chalet the Priest passed me again. ' Yes, a man is lost,' he said, his face graver than before. ' He's been out all night. The search parties have left.'

He gave a few details, then hurried on, but in the twinkling of an eye the note of that brilliant, even gorgeous, morning had changed completely. The shadow of disaster dimmed the sun shine, the pleasant roar of falling water became ominous, the great peaks wore a forbidding air. Somewhere among their awful loneliness a man was lost. The thing all dread had happened.

It was strange, at this early hour, how the undercurrent of news flashed so swiftly along the sunny street, touch ing some and missing others. To those who merely played tennis, danced, and went for walks, it meant less; to those who climbed and knew the wild places where the victim might be lying, it was poignant. One resented these careless, happy tourists picking flowers, chasing butterflies, playing tennis, in light hearted safety. Through the mind flashed vivid pictures of the cold, dreadful heights, of icy slopes, of dizzy ledges, of perilous corners above an abyss of emptiness. One turned, rather, to the peasants who stood about in groups, some with telescopes, all with grave faces and sympathetic questions. A man was lost. He had been out alone all night. There had been a cold wind but a clear sky. He was still clinging, perhaps, to some ledge, unable to get up or down, shouting to the emptiness, perhaps lying injured on some desolate pitch of rock, perhaps motionless.

My host, an old resident of the village, experienced climber as well, had all the available facts at his finger - tips when I got back. He was ready to start too. We chose a route the other parties had not taken, and on the way up he gave me details of what was known. We took with us Zeiss glasses, food, brandy, extra ropes. It was a gloomy, mournful expedition. We went fast, much too fast for climbers; the feeling of hurry made it impossible to take it easy.

An odd thing was that, although the man had broken all the rules, no one had used a word of blame. He was not a climber, but one of those vigorous Englishmen of middle age who enjoy ' a scramble.' He wore nailed boots and carried an iron-shod alpenstock. He was married, his wife and children at Como, where he was to join them in a few days. He was a botanist. He took with him a knapsack with food and a thermos of tea. He had left his hotel at two o'clock on the previous afternoon, but he had not told anyone exactly where he was going. His direction was only vaguely known. He had not re turned for dinner. He had been out twenty hours. Search parties had started at midnight; others had left at dawn. Three shots - echo carries the sound for miles were to be the signal that he had been found.

We used the 'botany' as our guide taking a precipitous trail to a region of desolate rocks where rare saxifrages grew. Every inch of the ground was known to both of us. We climbed in silence, the pace leaving no breath for words, but the glasses were used constantly, and occasionally there was a pause to discuss direction. Such a man, it was certain, would not choose obviously dangerous places, although his enthusiasm for some rare plant must remain an incalculable factor always. The probability seemed that his search had led him to some point whence descent became suddenly impossible. A common occurrence this, for to get up is often easier than to get down again. He had clung on through the dark ness, beneath the stars, till his strength failed and exhaustion loosened his grip. Or, perhaps, on some steep pitch where ordinary care meant safety, he had slipped. There were ugly drops to the south in plenty, but it was not the obviously dangerous places we need examine.

The few peasants we met all knew of the possible disaster gave little help; some had seen a solitary figure, others had not; descriptions varied; there was nothing reliable to guide us. We hurried as the day wore on. Up by the torrent, through deep forest, past waterfalls, across bright green upper pastures where a million flowers shone, scanning every couloir, examining every ledge where a man might venture, and especially the slope of shale at its foot. It was a familiar trail to both of us. The music of the cow bells filled the air. The gentians blazed. The snowfields sparkled far overhead, and the gay tourist village, except as the place where he had started twenty four hours ago now, was quite forgotten.

It was toward afternoon that I first noticed we began to speak of it instead of he. We were well up above the world by now, in the heart of the great heights, not far from the snow, the huge mountains coming more and more into their own. What we called ' the saxifrage rocks ' lay an hour below us. The sky wore a darker blue; the wind, creeping down from the glacier, had a nip in it; the flowers changed; and the immense desolation was emptied of any moving figures but our own. An occasional marmot whistled before diving into its hole, a bird flitted to another boulder, a white butterfly danced past, a stray fly buzzed and vanished. But that was all.

Already the Oberland giants were peering at us from behind the ridges we had topped. The silence of the big mountains, their grandeur, their mighty loneliness, their awe, stole over us. The change one had noticed in the sunny village street was increasingly manifest.

It was this change, though we did not speak of it at the time, that impressed us both, proving how the mood, the attitude of mind, determine selection. The familiar beauty retreated, letting terror in. The scenes we knew so well, had so often enjoyed with happy won der, now wore another guise. The majesty turned awful, the splendor cruel, the indifference to human life stood out. This new significance in 'scenery ' we had admired countless times at dawn, in the moonlight, in the fierce midday sunshine- became ever more apparent. The whole mean ing of the high mountains altered, light and shade falling in unaccustomed places. Imaginatively, one became aware of the conspiracy that exists among these great inanimate peaks and precipices, first to entice, then to en force the penalty for the least mistake. Every detail of crag and summit, every shoulder, col, and dangerous slope, became invested with a dim sense of personality that clothed another type of life. And this life, as the shadows lengthened and darkness grew upon the eastern side, became for us, not merely indifferent, but definitely hostile.

A hint of the monstrous crept into the lonely grandeur. These stupendous Powers, having claimed their victim, now tried to hide him. Other Consciousnesses now watched our puny efforts at discovery, peering down into our minds that still hoped to save. The sense of being watched was present. The weight of wonder, of admiration, of sympathetic tenderness certainly, was shifted from the mountains to the man. Awe was too strong for beauty any more. The eye searched, not for the marvel of form and color upon these terrible heights, not for the mystery of their inaccessible and dreadful loneliness, but strained ever for a small, significant outline, lying broken among huge, misshapen boulders the outline of a man, possibly of little importance beyond an immediate family circle, playing no big rôle in life that mattered, but a human be ing, a soul who, adventuring carelessly against too heavy odds, had lost.

Never again, for us, could these peaks and precipices, these flowers, snowfields, streams, seem quite the same. Into their collective being we called ' scenery ' a new ingredient had entered permanently, so that their wonder must ever hereafter hold too much of respect for our former loving admiration. We should pass the slope of shale in silence, glance upward at the treacherous ledge with a sigh, a shudder. Even on the brightest day, spring flowers carpeting our approach, this must be so. Nor would this emo tion bear much relation to the wooden cross the peasants erect with reverence. The spot would be haunted by the shadow of an adventure against awful odds.

Half on the shale, half on a patch of turf where gentians actually brushed one cheek, we found him - motionless. Just before the darkness came the glasses picked out the significant out line. The unnatural shape betrayed it among the grim boulders. My friend merely pointed in silence, his face a little paler beneath the sunburn, as he held out the binoculars. The drop was perhaps one hundred feet, but death must have been instantaneous, for the neck was broken. The stick lay fifty yards away. In one hand a little saxifrage was still clutched tightly.

Malahide and Forden

I

Our three-months’ tour was drawing to its close—the Company playing in a midland town at the moment and Forden was chatting with me in the wings during the second act, when Malahide’s great voice boomed in my ears as he hurried to his entrance. It startled me; the audience must surely hear it too. Forden gave me his quick smile, an understanding wink added to it.

“Hubert, old man!” cried the voice. “There’s a place called Barton I want to see—Barton-in-Fabis. Let’s go tomorrow. There’s a train at 10:15. Forden, you come too!” His eyes blazed at us with an odd glare through the greasepaint, his great shoulders swept round the canvas, and he was gone on to the stage, where at once his voice became audible in the lines that ten-weeks had made rather too familiar.

I experienced a twinge of surprise. Walking was little to Malahide’s taste. He usually spent his spare time playing golf, and in the afternoon he invariably slept for a couple of hours, so as to be rested for the evening performance. That he should propose a whole day’s walk, therefore, was unexpected.

My companion and I were left staring at each other.

“Does he mean it—d’you think!” I asked in a low voice. “It sounds such an odd name. You think it’s real?” I laughed a little.

“A lovely name, though,” came the whispered answer. “It’s real enough. Yes—I’ve heard of it—”

“Oh, you’ve heard of it?” I interrupted, looking up at him.

He nodded. Always absentminded rather, he was also always truthful. An expression on his face now puzzled me. He looked perturbed. I repeated my remark, anxious to press him for some reason.

“People make pilgrimages there—sometimes—I believe. There’s an old church—” Then his cue sounded, and he moved quickly away, but flinging over his shoulder, again with his quick smile, a final whisper: “Oh, it’s real, yes, quite real. We’ll go.”

So it was the church and the odd name that had caught Malahide’s romantic fancy. Yet such a flat and empty name, I thought, without the adjunct, which alone gave it atmosphere. “In fabis,” I gathered from one of the local supers, meant “among the beans,” and Barton was a village “with a lot of historic interest,” he informed me proudly. The name and the historic interest, evidently, had taken Malahide’s vagrant fancy. He was an incalculable fellow; but he was not a man to ply with questions. His temper was insecure as a wayward child’s. I, therefore, asked no questions. Forden, too, was an elusive creature, where questions were concerned. There are people who instinctively detest having to give definite information in reply to definite questions. All the more, then, was I surprised to hear Forden ask one of Malahide—about the expedition. We passed the latter’s dressing room as we left the theatre to walk home together, and the door was open.

“Ten-fifteen, remember, Central Station,” boomed Malahide, catching sight of us. “Single tickets to Stanton. We walk from Stanton.” It again surprised me; he had actually thought out details.

It was then that Forden asked his question:

“I—I suppose,” he ventured, faltering a trifle, “there’s a train back all right?”

The evening performance of course, involved an early meal, and the question seemed so natural that I thought nothing, but Malahide looked up from pulling on his big boots as though it startled him. He seemed taken by surprise. His eyes held the same blaze, the touch almost of glare, I had noticed before, but the startled air was added.

“We’ll work round. What can it matter anyhow—provided we get there?” was all he vouchsafed, and in a tone that did not invite cross-examination.

So it was to be 10:15, with single tickets to Stanton, a walk thence to Barton among its Beans, with its old church and historic interest, and we were to “work round” to another station, and so home. Malahide had planned it all in advance. He wanted to go. Forden also wanted to go. It all seemed natural enough, ordinary, no exceptional feature anywhere about it beyond the trivial detail that Malahide did not care for walking as a rule. It is strange, therefore, that somewhere in my being lurked a firm conviction that the whole business was exceptional. For one thing, I felt sure that both Malahide and Forden did not really want to go. That they had to go, and meant to go, was the impression left upon my mind, not that either of them actually “wished” it.

During our supper of cold tongue, salad and beer, for instance, we made no further allusion to the expedition. Rather than actually avoided, it was just tacitly assumed, Forden, I partly gathered, realised that I still did not quite believe in the Barton walk, but was too delicately loyal to discuss our friend’s delightful irresponsibilities. In his own mind, too, I fancied, lay the thought that Malahide would not turn up, and that he would lose his morning’s sleep for nothing, but that he meant to keep the rendezvous none the less. My fancy may have been quite wrong, yet this, anyhow, was Forden all over. He was of finest material, something transparent and a trifle exquisite in him; and even when poorly cast—as in the present play—this quality shone beautifully through his acting.

We went soon to bed, but Malahide kept late hours, and Forden and myself were asleep long before he turned in. In the morning, however, he was waiting at the station when we got there. He had left the hotel before us. “I’ve been to look at the churches,” was his unexpected explanation. “One of ’em was open, and I went in and sat a bit. A wonderful atmosphere of peace and stillness. By Jove, it makes one think,” and he gabbled on about the charm and atmosphere of an empty, ancient church. It was surprising, of course, and it left us without comment. Yet I had known him before in this odd mood—when he was frightened about something, frightened usually, of death. Malahide, I understood, was frightened now, and his thoughts, for some reason, ran on death. In his eyes, moreover, I noticed, though veiled a little, a trifle deeper down, the same blaze I had seen the night before. And all the way to Stanton he gazed out of the window, humming to himself, the heap of morning papers beside him all untouched. The criticisms of his own performance, as, equally, mention of the Company, though of importance to the week’s business, had, for once, no interest for him. His mind lay, evidently, upon other matters. He looked extraordinarily happy—happier, I thought, than I had ever seen him before; there was a careless indifference, a lightness, something, too, of a new refinement—to use a queer word his vehement personality did not ever suggest—thought were new, yet all this lit, as from below, by the gleam of hidden fear I most certainly detected in him. And it was these contradictions, I think, these incompatibilities almost, that affected me so powerfully. Impressions began to pour and pour upon me. Emotions stirred. Things going on at a great speed in Malahide were things that I could not fathom.

To me, this short train journey to Stanton, en route for Barton among its Beans, already had the spice of something just a little unusual, of something a trifle forced. Unexpected touches played about it, as though a faint unknown light shone from the cloudless sky of that perfect April morning, but from beyond it. Forden, behind the transparent mask of his rather beautiful face, betrayed more than his customary absentmindedness, sometimes to a point I could have thought bewilderment. Each time I spoke to him—to Malahide I did not once address a word—he started a little. In him there was no attempt at adjustment, no analysis, no effort to explain or query. He asked himself, I am sure, no single question. Whatever life brought him he accepted always. He was receptive merely; a recipient, but an extremely sensitive recipient, leaving all problems, all causes, to his God. Though without a formal creed, Forden was a deeply religious nature. And Forden now seemed to me—let me put it quite plainly as I felt it at the time—preparing, making himself ready, getting himself in hand, to meet something. Yes, to meet something—that is the phrase. And it was the search for this phrase, its discovery rather, that made me aware of an incomprehensible stress of subconscious excitement similarly in myself.

We were a queer enough trio, it may be, even in our normal moments. In myself, at any rate, being of different build to both Malahide and Forden, numerous little wheels were already whirring, gathering speed with every minute. This whirring one usually calls excitement. My own personal reactions to what followed are all, of course, that I can report. Though caught up, more or less, with the other two, I remained always the observer, thus sharing only a small portion probably of what my companions experienced. Another man, of different calibre, placed as I was, t have noticed nothing. I cannot say. My problem is to report faithfully what I observed; and whether another man would have observed the same thing, or nothing at all, is beside the mark. … Already before the train stopped at Stanton I felt—well, as if my feet did not quite touch the ground, and by the ground I mean the ordinary. It may, or may not, be an exaggeration to say that I felt both feet slightly off the earth. That my centre of gravity was shifting is, perhaps, the most truthful expression I can find.

By the time we reached Stanton, at any rate, the whirring wheels had generated considerable heat, and with this heat playing all through my system I had already begun to see and feel in a way that was not quite the ordinary way. I perceived differently: I experienced, as it were, with a heightened consciousness. Perception seemed intensified a trifle; but more than that, and chiefly, it seemed different.

Different is the right adjective, I think. Malahide and Forden were “different” to the Malahide and Forden I knew comfortably from long acquaintance. Very, very slightly different, however, not radically so. I saw them from another angle. There was nothing I could seize or label. The instant my mind fastened on any detail, it was gone. The “difference” escaped me, leaving behind it a wonder of enquiry, a glow of curiosity I could not possibly define.

One sentence, perhaps, can explain my meaning, both in reference to the men and to the inanimate things they moved among: I saw more of everything …

The fields, through the carriage windows, were of freshest green, yellow with a million buttercups, sparkling still from a shower that had followed sunrise, and the surface of the earth lay positively radiant in its spring loveliness. It laughed, it danced, it wept, it smiled. Yet it was not with this my mind was occupied during the half-hour’s run to Stanton, but rather with the being of my two companions. I made no effort to direct my thoughts. They flowed of their own accord, with poignant, affectionate emotions I could not explain, towards Malahide and Forden. …

II

Played about them, over them, these thoughts did, lovingly rather, and directed by a flair, so to say, of understanding that was new in me. …

Neither would ever see forty again, yet to me they seemed young, their careers still in front of them; and each, though without much energy, groping a way honestly toward some ultimate meaning in life that neither, I fancied, was ever likely to discover. If not dilettanti, both shrank from the big sacrifices. They were married, and each, in this fundamental relationship, unsatisfied, though each, outwardly at least, had mastered that dissatisfaction. Accepting, that is, a responsibility undertaken, they played the game. There was fine stuff in them. And both sought elsewhere, though without much energy as I have said, an outlet marriage had accordingly failed to provide. Not immorality, of course; but a mental, maybe a spiritual, outlet. They sought it, I now abruptly judged, without success. Their stream of yearning, whatever its power, went lost among the stars and unremunerative dreams. The point, however, remains: this yearning did exist in each. Its power, I conceive, was cumulative.

Similarly, in their daily work as actors, and uncommonly good actors, one with a streak of fine inspiration, the other, Malahide, with a touch of fiery genius, both accepted an art that both held, mournfully, and secretly rather, was not creative. They were merely interpreters of other men’s creations. And, here again, lay deep dissatisfaction. Here, indeed, lay the root and essence of a searching pain both shared—since, God knows, they were gifted, honest beings—that a creative outlet, namely, was denied to creative powers.

This fundamental problem—the second one—lay unsolved in both; hence both were open to attack and ready for adventure. But the lesser adventures, refuge of commonplace fellows, they resolutely declined. Were they, perhaps, worthy then of the greater adventure that circumstances, at length, with inexplicable suddenness, and out of the least likely material, offered to them. … ?

Somewhat thus, at any rate, I saw my companions, as the train jolted us that sparkling April morning, many years ago, towards Stanton, Malahide humming his mood idly through the open window, Forden lying at full length, reading the papers with listless eye. But I saw another thing as well, saw it with a limpid clearness my description may not hold: something ahead—an event—lay in waiting for them, something they knew about, both not desiring, yet desiring it, something inevitable as sunrise.

We move towards and past events successively, calling this motion time. But the event itself does not move at all. It is always there. We three, now sitting in the jolting carriage, were approaching an event about which they knew, but about which I did not know. I received, that is, an imperfect impression of something they saw perfectly. And in some way the accumulated power of their combined yearnings, wasted as I had thought, made what happened possible.

It was an extraordinary idea to come to me with such conviction, and with this atmosphere of prophecy. I glanced at the two men, each like myself the victim, I remembered, of a strange, unhappy weakness. These weaknesses, too, I realised, contributed as well: unbalance, instability, were evidently necessary to the event. To steady, heroic types it never could have happened.

The train was stopping, and Malahide already had the door half-open. Forden, in his turn, sprang up.

“Stanton!” cried the former, as though he spoke a line of tense drama on the stage. “Here we are. Come on, you fellows!” And he was on the platform before the train drew to a standstill. His vehemence was absurd. He used it, I knew, to help him make the start, the fear I have mentioned prompting it. And Forden, like a flash, was on his heels. I followed, pausing a moment to collect the papers in case Malahide should ask for them, and then, thank heaven, as we stood on that ugly platform and asked the porter the way to Barton, my own strange feelings, heightened perception with them, dropped back with a jerk into the normal again. The uncomfortable insight was suddenly withdrawn. It had seemed an intrusion into their privacies; I was relieved to see them again as two friends merely, two actors, out for a country walk with me to a village called Barton-in-Fabis on a brilliant April morning.

One last flash only there was, as I followed them out, one final hint of what I have called “seeing more” of everything, seeing “differently,” rather. The three of us left the carriage as described, in sequence; yet to me it flashed with definite though illogical assurance that only one got out. Not that one was gone and two were left, but that the three of us got out as one, simultaneously. One being left that carriage. The fingers of a hand, thus, may move and point in several directions at once, while the hand, of which they form parts, moves forward in one direction only, as a whole. The simile occurred to me. … I perceived it, moreover, through what I can only call a veil of smoke.

III

“Oh, about three to four mile, maybe,” the porter was telling Malahide, “an’ you can pick up the Midland at Attenborough to get back. … Yes, it’s a nice day for a walk, I dessay. …”

The name made us laugh, but the instructions as to paths, stiles, signposts, turnings, I, personally, did not listen to. I assumed, as most do, an air of intelligent comprehension. Forden, I saw, wore a similar expression, from which I knew that he, too, was not listening properly, but was leaving it to Malahide, wondering, like myself, how the latter could carry in his great slumbering mind so many intricate details whereas, actually, he was doing nothing of the sort. Malahide was merely acting, intent upon some other matter that was certainly not here and now.

We started off, therefore, with but a few details of our journey secure:—“a mile and a half down the road, and bearin’ to the right, you’ll see a signpost to Barton across the fields, and if you foller that a little way, bearin’ to the left a bit now, you’ll see a gate on the right just past some trees, but you don’t go through that gate, you go straight on, bearin’ to the right always, till you come to a farm, and then, through another gate …”

There was a definite relation between the length of description and a tip in the porter’s mind, upon which Forden commented wittily, as we swung down the road, each relying upon the other two, and then exclaiming confidently, but with blurred minds, as we reached a signpost: “Ah! Here we are!” while we scrambled over a stile into enticing fields of gold.

We spoke little at first. “We must bear to the left, remember,” mentioned Malahide once, to which Forden and I nodded agreement, adding however: “till we reach the gate,” with Malahide’s firm reminder: “which we do not go through,” followed by my own contribution: “past some trees, yes, to another gate,”—and then Malahide’s conclusive summing up: “always bearing to the right, of course …”

We jogged on happily, while the larks sang overhead, the cuckoos called and the brilliant sunshine flooded a countryside growing more and more remote from signs of men and houses. Not even a thatched cottage or a farmhouse broke the loneliness from human kind. …

We spoke little, I have said; but my companions, presently, fell into a desultory conversation about their own profession, about present and future conditions on the stage, individual talent, rents of theatres, and so forth, to all of which, being an interloper merely, I listened with slight interest. It was the odd smell of burning, I think, that held my curious attention during this preliminary period, for I saw no cause for it, no smoke of rubbish being consumed, no heath-fire certainly. Malahide, I remember, coughed a little once or twice, and Forden sniffed like an animal that scents an untoward element in the atmosphere, though very faintly. They made no comment, I offered none. It was, obviously, of no importance. The beauty of the day in its fresh spring brilliance absorbed me wholly, so that my thoughts ran on of their own accord, floating on a stream of happy emotion, careless as the pleasant wind. The sentences I caught from time to time did little more than punctuate, as it were, this stream of loveliness that poured through me from the April morning. Yet at intervals I caught their words, a phrase or a sentence would arrest me for a second; and each time this happened, I noticed what I can only call a certain curious change, a change—in distance. Their talk, I mean, passed gradually beyond me.

There was incoherence, due partly, of course, to the gaps I missed; and once or twice, it seemed to me, they were talking at cross-purposes, although tone and demeanour betrayed nothing of the sort. I remember that this puzzled me, that I registered the fact vaguely, at any rate; also, that an occasional comment of my own won no rejoinder from either Malahide or Forden—almost as though, momentarily, they had forgotten my existence and seemed unaware that I was with them.

Deeper and deeper into my own sensuous enjoyment of the day I sank accordingly, glad that I might take the beauty in my own little way. One thing only pierced my personal mood from time to time: the picture of Malahide’s great head thrust forward a little when I glanced at him, the eyes turned upwards, carrying in them still that odd soft blaze, the glare, as I called it, now wholly gone; and that upon Forden’s delicate face was a gentle expression, curiously rapt, yet with a faint brush as of bewilderment somewhere among the peering features. This impression, however, came back to me later, rather than held my attention much at the actual moment. We moved on deeper and deeper into the lonely countryside. With the exception of a man some fields ahead of us, I saw no living soul.

IV

Our path, meanwhile, crossed a lane, and a little later a road, though not a highroad since no telegraph poles marred it, and then Malahide remarked casually: “But, I say! It’s about time, isn’t it?” He stood abruptly, staring round him. “It’s about time—eh?”

“For what?” enquired Forden gently, not looking at him, a touch of resignation in his voice.

“That signpost, I mean. We should have come to it by now.”

“Oh, that signpost,” echoed the other, without interest.

Neither of them included me in this exchange, which had broken in upon a longish conversation, and I found myself resenting it. They had not so much as glanced in my direction.

“Signpost!” I exclaimed bluntly, looking straight at Malahide. “Why, we passed it long ago.” And as I said it, my eye again took in the figure of the man three fields away, the only living being yet seen. Out of the corner of my eye I saw him merely, and a breath of sharper air, or something like it, passed quickly over my skin. “It said ‘To Barton,’” I added, a flavour of challenge in my tone. I purposely kept my gaze hard on Malahide.

He turned slowly, with a look as though, casually, he picked me up again; our eyes met; that sharper air seemed in my mind now.

“We passed a signpost,” he corrected me; “but it merely said ‘Footpath.’ And it pointed over there—behind us. The way we’ve come.”

Forden, to my amazement, nodded in consent. “Over there, yes,” he agreed, and pointed with his stick, but at right angles to the direction Malahide had meant. “And it said: ‘From Barton.’”

This confusion, produced purposely and in a spirit of play though of course it was, annoyed me. I disliked it, as though somewhere it reached a sad, uneasy region in my mind.

It was Malahide’s turn to nod in consent. “Then we’re all right,” he affirmed with unnecessary vehemence in his deep voice. And that vehemence, again, I did not like. “Besides,” he added sharply, pointing ahead, “there he is!”

A wave of vague emotion troubled me; for an instant I felt again that sharper air—and this time in the heart.

“Who?” I asked quickly.

He replied carelessly: “The man.”

“What man?”

Malahide turned his eyes full upon my own, so that their soft blaze came over me like sunshine, almost with a sense of warmth in them. On his great face lay a singular expression. I heard Forden, who stood just behind me, laughing gently. There seemed a drift of smoke about them both. I knew a touch of gooseflesh.

“What man do you mean?” I asked with louder emphasis, and this time, I admit, with a note of exasperation that would not be denied, for the nonsense, I thought, had gone far enough, and there was a flavour in it that set my nerves on edge.

Malahide’s reply came easily and naturally: “The man who plants them,” he said without a smile. “He sticks them into the ground, that fellow. He’s going about with an assortment of signposts ‘To and From Barton,’ and every now and again he plants one for us.”

“We’re standing under one now,” Forden breathed behind me in his purring way, and looking up I saw that this was true. I read in black lettering upon a white background: “To Barton.” It indicated the direction we were taking.

It occurred to me suddenly now that we had already walked at least four miles, yet had seen no farm, no trees, no garden. I had been sunk too deep in my own mood to notice things perhaps. This signpost I certainly had not noticed until Forden drew my attention to it. Malahide was tapping the wooden arm with the point of his stick, reading the lettering aloud as he did so:

“Footpath From Barton,” I heard him boom. And instantly my eyes fixed tightly on it with all the concentration that was in me. Yes, Malahide had read correctly. Only, the arm now swung the other way. It pointed behind us! And I burst out laughing. Sight and memory had, indeed, fumbled badly. I felt myself for a moment “all turned round,” as the saying is. Malahide laughed too; we all laughed together. It was, boisterous, not quite spontaneous laughter, but at any rate it relieved a sense of intolerable tension that in myself had reached a climax. This fooling had been overdone, I felt.

“So, you see, we are all right,” Malahide exclaimed, and swung forward over the meadow, already plunged again in the conversation with Forden which he himself had interrupted. They had enjoyed their little game about the signposts, Malahide, in particular, his touch of fancy about “the man who planted them.” It all belonged to the careless, happy mood of a holiday expedition, as it were—the nonsense of high spirits. This, at least, was the ready explanation my mind produced so glibly, knowing full well it would not pass the censor of another kind of understanding, a deeper kind, that sought hurriedly, even passionately, for the true explanation. It was not nonsense; nor was it acceptable. It alarmed me.

I repeat: this confusion about directions, the two men agreeing that opposite directions were one and the same, was not the nonsense that it sounds; and I affirm this in view of that heightened perception, already first experienced in the train, which now came back upon me in a sudden flood. It brought with it an atmosphere of prophecy, almost of prevision, and certainly of premonition, an atmosphere that accompanied me, more or less, with haunting persistence to the end.

And its first effect was singular: all that a man says, I now became aware, has three meanings, and not merely one. The revelation arrived as clearly as though it were whispered to me through the shining air. There is the literal meaning of the actual words; there is the meaning of the sentence itself; and there is the meaning, above and beyond both these, in which the whole of the utterer is concerned, a meaning, that is, which the unconscious secret part in—the greater part—tries and hopes to say. This last, the most significant of all three, since it includes cause as well as result, makes of every common sentence a legend and a parable. Gesture, tone of voice betray its trend; what is omitted, or between the lines, betrays still more. Its full meaning, being in relation to unknown categories, is usually hidden both from utterer and hearers. It deals simultaneously with the past, the present and—the future. I now became aware of this Third Meaning in the most commonplace remarks of my companions.

It was an astounding order of perception to occur to me, and the difficulty of reporting it must be obvious from this confused description. Yet it seemed to me at the time so simple, so convincing, that I did not even question its accuracy and truth. Malahide and Forden, fooling together about the contradictory signposts, had betrayed this third meaning in all they said and did. Indeed, that it appeared impossible, absurd, was a proof, perhaps the only possible proof, of its reality. Momentarily, as it were, they had become free of unknown categories.

V

My own attitude contained at first both criticism and resistance; it was only gradually that I found myself caught in the full tide that, apparently, swept my companions along so easily. A first eddy of it had touched me in the train, when my feet felt a little “off the earth”; now I was already in the bigger current; before long I had become entirely submerged with them. … Fields and lanes, meanwhile, slipped rapidly behind us, but no farm, no trees, no gate, as the porter described, had been seen. We were lost, it seemed, in the heart of the sparkling April day; dew, light and gentle airs our only guides. The day contained us.

I made efforts to disentangle myself.

“Barton’s not getting any nearer,” I expostulated once.

“Barton-in-Fabis,” mentioned Malahide with complete assurance, that no longer held a trace of vehemence, “is there—where it always is,” while Forden’s breath of delicate laughter followed the flat statement, as though the larks overhead had sung close beside my ear.

“D’you think we’re going right?” I ventured another time. “Our direction, I mean?”

Again, with that ghostly laughter, Forden met me: “It’s the way we have to go,” he replied half under his breath. “It’s always a mistake to trouble too much about direction—actual direction, that is.” And Malahide was singing to himself as though nothing mattered in the world, details as to direction least of all. … It was just after this, I remember, as our lane came to a stile and we leaned over it comfortably, all three, that the odour of burning touched my mind again, only with it, at the same time, a sight so moving, that I paused in thought, catching my breath a little. For the field before us sloped down into the distance, ancient furrows showing just beneath the surface like the flowing folds of a shaken carpet. They ran, it seemed, like streams. Their curve downhill lent this impression of movement. They were of gold. Every inch of the surface was smothered with the shimmering cream of a million yellow buttercups.

“Rivers of Gold!” I exclaimed involuntarily, and at the same moment Forden was over the stile in a single leap and running across the brilliant grass.

“Look out!” he cried, a bewitched expression on his face, “it’s fire!”—and he was gone.

It was as though he swam to the neck in gleaming gold. He peered back at me a second through the shining flood—and it was in this instant, just as I caught his turning face, that Malahide was after him. He passed me like a wave, still singing; there was a rush of power in his speed. I followed at once, unable to resist. The three of us ran like one man over and through that flood of golden buttercups, passing, as we did so, every sign the railway porter had told us to look out for: the farm, the trees, the gate, the second gate—everything. Only, we passed them more than once. It was as though we swung in a rapid circle round and round the promised signs, always passing them, always coming up to them, always leaving them behind, then always seeing them in front of us again, yet the entire sequence right, natural and—possible.

Now, I noticed this. I was aware of this. Yet it caused me no surprise. That it should be so seemed quite ordinary—at the time. …

We brought up presently, not even breathless, some halfway down that golden field.

“Nothing to what I expected,” exclaimed Malahide, interrupting his singing for the first time.

“There was no pain,” mentioned Forden, his voice soft and comforting, as though he spoke to a little child.

There was an instant of most poignant emotion in me as they said certainty flashed through me that I could not seize; a sudden wave, as it were, of tears, of joy, of sorrow, of despair, swept past me and was gone again before I had the faintest chance to snatch at any explanation. Like the memory of some tremendous, rather awful dream, it vanished, and Malahide’s quick remark, the next second, capped its complete oblivion:

“And there he goes again!” I heard. “He’s stuck another one in!”

He was pointing to a hedge at the bottom of the field where, behind the veil of its creamy hawthorn, I just made out the figure of a man ambling slowly along, till the hedge, growing thicker, finally concealed him. But the signpost, when we reached it a few minutes later, showed an arm rotten with age, and only the faded legend on it, hardly legible: “Footpath.” It pointed downwards—into the ground.

VI

We swung forward again, without a moment’s delay, it seemed, my companions talking busily together as before, their meaning, also as before, far, far beyond me. They were talking, too, on several subjects at once. The odd language they had just used, the way we swung forward instantly, without comment or explanation, touched no sense of queerness in me—then. No comment or explanation were necessary; it was natural we should go straight on. Their talking on “several subjects simultaneously,” however, did occur to me—yes, as marvellous.

Foolish, even impossible, as it must sound, it yet did happen; they talked on more than one subject at the same time. They carried on at least a couple of conversations at once without the slightest difficulty, without the smallest effort or confusion. My own admission into the secret was partial, I think; hence my trouble and perplexity. To them it was easy and natural. With me, even the strain of listening made the head swim. The effort to follow them was certainly a physical one, for I was aware of a definite physical reaction more than once, almost indeed of a kind of dizziness akin to nausea.

To report it is beyond my power. For one thing, I cannot remember, for another, the concentration necessary left me a little stupefied. I can give an instance only, and that a poor one. They used “third meanings,” too.

Malahide, thus, while voluble enough in his normal state, was at the same time usually inarticulate. His verbosity, that is, conveyed little. The tiny vital meaning in him fumbled and stammered through countless wrappings, as it were. These wrappings smothered it. Now, on the contrary, he talked fluently and clearly. It was I who was puzzled—at first—to find the subject he discussed so glibly. And Forden, usually timid and hesitating in his speech, though never inarticulate, now also used a flow of fearless words in answer. Yet not precisely “in answer,” for both men talked at once. They uttered simultaneously—on two subjects, if not on three:

“We all deserve, maybe,” Malahide’s deep voice thundered, “a divine attention few of us receive—God’s pity. We are not, alas, wholehearted. Few of us, similarly, deserve another compliment. Due to splendour—the Devil’s admiration.”

His voice, for once, was entirely natural, unselfconscious. There was the stress of real feeling and belief in what he said.

“I for one,” he went on, “I take my hat off to the wholehearted, whether in so-called good or evil. For of such stuff are eventual angels wrought …”

Angels! The word caught me on the raw. Its “third meaning” caught me on the raw, that is, and with a sense of power and beauty so startling that I missed the rest. The word poured through me like a flame. Of what he spoke, to what context the strange statement was related, I had no inkling; yet, while he actually spoke the words, I heard Forden speaking to Malahide, who heard and understood and answered—but speaking, and simultaneously, on another matter altogether. And this other matter, it so chanced, I grasped. Remote enough from what Malahide was saying, and trivial by comparison, it referred to an Alpine sojourn with his wife a couple of summers before. Malahide, too, had been with them:

“Often, after the hotel dinner,” Forden said contemptuously, “I heard them mouthing all sorts of lovely poetic phrases; yet not one of them would make the slight sacrifice of personal comfort necessary to experience that loveliness, that poetry, in themselves …”

To which Malahide, though still developing “God’s pity” and the “Devil’s admiration” in phrases packed with real feeling, contrived somehow to answer, but always simultaneously, his friend’s remark:

“They bring their own lower world,” he boomed, “even into the beauty of the mountains, then wonder that the beauty of the mountains tells them nothing. They would find Balham on great Betelgeuse”—a tremendous laugh rang out—“and Clapham Junction on fiery Vega!”

“Her pity,” came Forden’s words, talking of another matter altogether, yet uttered simultaneously with his friend’s laughing rhetoric, “is self-pity merely. She does these out-of-the-way things, you see, without sufficient apparent reason. It is not a desire for notoriety—that would shock her—but it is a desire to be conspicuous. Life, which means people, did not make a fuss about her in her youth. But the law of compensation works inevitably. Late in life, you see, she means to have that fuss.”

It is the phraseology, perhaps, that enables me to remember this singular exchange. My head, of course, was spinning. For Malahide made a reply to this, while still discussing the poseurs in the Alpine hotel. And while they talked thus on two subjects simultaneously, Forden managed to chat easily too with me—upon a third. … It was as though a second dimension in time had opened for them. Between myself and Forden, again, there was plainly some kind of telepathic communication. He had my thought, at any rate, before I uttered it aloud.

Of this I can give two instances, both trivial, yet showing that simultaneously with his Malahide-conversations he was paying attention to my own remarks, and—simultaneously again—was answering them. It was absolutely staggering.

Here are the instances memory retained:

Some scraps of white paper, remnants of an untidy picnic party, lay fluttering in the thick grass some distance in front of us, and at the first glance I thought they were not paper, but—chickens. Only on coming nearer was the mistake clear. Whether I meant to comment aloud on the little deception, or not, I cannot remember; but in any case, before I actually did so, Forden, glancing down at me with his gentle smile, observed: “I, too, thought at first they were chickens.” He hit them idly with his stick as we passed.

The second instance, equally trivial, equally striking at the same time, was the gamekeeper’s cottage on the fringe of a wood. It suggested to my mind, for some reason, a charcoal-burner’s hut in a book of German fairytales, and I said so. This time I spoke my thought. “But, you know, I’ve just said that,” came Forden’s comment, his eyes twinkling brightly as before. And it was true; he had said it a fraction of a second before I did. During this brief exchange between us, moreover, he was still talking fluently with Malahide—on at least two subjects—and simultaneously. … Now, from the fact that I noticed this, that my mind made a note of it, that is, I draw the conclusion that my attention was definitely arrested, surprise accompanying it. The extraordinariness of the matter struck me, whereas to my companions it was ordinary and natural. I was, therefore, not wholly included in their marvellous experience. I was still the observer merely.

Immediately following the telepathic instances with Forden, then, came a flash of sudden understanding, as though I were abruptly carried a stage deeper into their own condition:

I discerned one of the subjects they discussed so earnestly together.

This came hard upon a momentary doubt—the doubt that they were playing, half-fooling me, as it were. Then came the swift flash that negatived the doubt. I can only compare it to the amazing review of a man’s whole life that is said to flash out in a moment of extreme danger. This quality, as of juggling with Time, belonged to it.

Malahide and Forden, then, I realised, were talking together of Woman, of women, rather, but of individual women. Ah! The flash grew brighter: of their own wives. Yet that Malahide spoke of Forden’s wife and that: Forden discussed Mrs. Malahide. Each had the free entrée into the other’s mind, and what each was too loyal to say about his own wife, the other easily said for him. This swiftest telepathic communication, as with myself and Forden, they enjoyed between themselves. With supreme ease it was accomplished.

It was an astounding performance. This discussion of their wives was actually, of course, a discussion of—well, not of Mary Forden and Jane Malahide individually, but, through them, of the deep unsolved problem of mate and sex which each man had faced in his own life—unsuccessfully. The fragments I caught seemed meaningless, because the full context was lacking for me. I got a glimmer of their Third Meanings, however, and realised one thing, at any rate, clearly: they were giving one another help. Forden’s honeymoon, I remembered, had been spent in the Alps, whereas Malahide’s wife had the lack of proportion which made her conspicuous by a pose of startling originality. This gave me a clue. Time, however, as a sequence of minutes, days and years, did not trouble either speaker. The entire matter, regardless of past and present, seemed spread out like a contour-map beneath the eyes of their inner understanding. There was no picking out one characteristic, dealing with it, then passing on to consider another. To me it came, seriatim, in that fashion, but they saw the matter whole and all at once; so rapidly, so comprehensively, too, that the sentences flew upon each other’s heels as though uttered simultaneously by each speaker.

They were it seemed, poised above the landscape of their daily lives, and in such a way that they were able to realise present, past and future simultaneously. It was no longer exactly “today,” it was no longer necessarily “today.” Temporarily they had escaped from the iron tyranny of being fastened to a particular hour on a particular day. They—and partially myself with them—were no longer chained by the cramping discipline of a precise moment in time, any more than a prisoner, his chains filed off, is fixed to a precise spot in his dungeon. Where we were in time, God knows. It might have been yesterday, it might have been tomorrow—any yesterday, any tomorrow—which we now realised simultaneously with the so-called present. It happened to be—so I felt—a particular tomorrow we realised, and it was something in the three of us (due, I mean, to the combination of our three personalities) that determined which particular tomorrow it was. The prisoner in space, his chains filed off, moves instinctively to the window of escape; and they, prisoners in time, moved now similarly to a window—of escape. …

A flash of this escape from ordinary categories, of this “different” experience, had come to me as we left the railway carriage. It now grew brighter, more steady, more continuous. I seemed travelling in time, as one travels ordinarily in space. To the wingless creature crawling over fields the hedge behind it is past, the hedge beyond it future. It cannot conceive both hedges existing simultaneously. Then some miracle gives it wings. Hanging in the air, it sees both past and future existing simultaneously. Losing its wings once more, it crawls across the fields again. That air-experience now seems absurd, impossible, contradicting all established law. The same signpost points now as it always pointed—in one direction.

This analogy, though imperfect, occurred to me, while we brought up, but not even breathlessly, halfway down the field as already mentioned, and all I have attempted to describe took place in that brief interval of running.

Before entering that field with its rivers of gold, we had been leaning on a stile; we were leaning on that stile still. Or, it may be put otherwise: we were leaning on that stile again.

Similarly, the whole business of running, of passing the signs mentioned by the porter, the conversations, the emotions, everything in fact, were just about to happen all over again. More truly expressed, they were all happening still. Like Barton, in Malahide’s previous phrase, it was all there. The hedge behind, the hedge in front, were both beneath us, existing simultaneously. … At a particular spot in the hedge—a particular “tomorrow”—we paused. …

VII

… At my side, touching my shoulders, Malahide and Forden were quietly discussing the way to Barton-in-Fabis, and, as I listened, there came over me again that touch of nausea. For, while flatly contradicting one another, they were yet in complete agreement.

It was at this instant the shock fell upon me with its glory and its terror.

My companions stood back to back. I was a yard or so to one side. They both now turned suddenly—but how phrase the incredible thing?—they both came at me, while at the same time they went away from me. A hand, endowed with consciousness, a hand being turned inside out like a glove, might feel what I felt.

I saw their two faces. A little more, a little less, and there must have been a bristling horror in the experience. As it was, I felt only that a sheet of wonder caught us up all three. The odour of burning that came with it did not terrify; that drift of yellow smoke, now deepening, did not wound. I accepted, I understood, there was even something in me had rejoiced.

In the twinkling of an eye, both men were marvellously changed: they stood before me, splendid and divine. I was aware of the complete being in each, the full, whole Self, I mean, instead of the minute fraction I had known hitherto. All that lay in them, either of strength or weakness, was magnificently fused. … The word “glory” flashed, followed immediately by a better word, and one that Malahide had already used. Its inadequacy was painful. Its third meaning, however, in that instant blazed. “Angels” in spite of everything, remains.

And I, too, moved—moved with them both, but in a way, and in a direction, I had never known before. The glove, the hand, being turned inside out, is what my pen writes down, but accurate description is not possible. I moved, at any rate, on—on with my two companions towards Barton.

“It’s all one to me,” I said, perfectly aware that I suddenly used the third meaning of the phrase, and that Malahide and Forden understood.

“I’ve just said that myself,” the latter mentioned—and this again was true. The smile, the happiness, on his face carried the very spirit of that radiant April morning, the essence of spring, with its birds, its flowers, its dew, its careless wisdom.

“Such things,” cried Malahide, “are painless after all. It comes on me like sleep upon a child. Ha, ha!” he laughed, in his wild, vehement way. “It’s all one to me now too. Escape, by God!”

The stab of fierce emotion his language caused me passed and vanished; the afflicting memory of the burning odour was forgotten too. Everything, indeed, was one. Both men, I realised, gazed at me, smiling, wonderful, superb, and in their eyes a light, whose reflection apparently lay also in my own; an immense and awful pity that our everyday, unhappy, partial selves should ever have dared to masquerade as though they were complete and real. …

“God’s pity,” sang Malahide like a trumpet. “We shall have deserved it … !”

“And the Devil’s admiration,” followed Forden’s sweeter tones, as of a vox humana, both. Distant, yet like a lark against my ears. He was laughing with sheer music. “There was no terror. I knew it must be so. … Oh, the delicious liberty … at last!”

Both uttered simultaneously. In the same breath, anguish and happiness working together, my own voice cried aloud:

“We are, for once, wholehearted!”

VIII

At the moment of actual experience a new category would not seem foolish or impossible. These qualities would declare themselves only when it passed away. This was what happened—gradually—to me now, and, alas, to my companions too. A searing pain accompanied the transition, but no shock of violence.

At the pinnacle there was a state of consciousness too strange, too “different,” to be set down. The content of life, its liberty, its splendour, its characteristics of grandeur, even of divinity, were more than ordinary memory could retain. My own cry: “We are wholehearted” must betray how pitiful description is. … Thus, the lovely moment, for instance, when I first saw rivers of gold, kept repeating itself—because it gave me happiness, because it moved me. That field of golden buttercups was always—there. I lingered with it, came back to it, enjoyed it over and over again, yet with no sense of repetition. It was new and fresh each time. Now, Malahide and Forden, selecting other moments, chose these instead, and these, again, were moments easy to be remembered. Their finer instances baffle memory, although I knew and shared them at the time. Forden, for some peculiar choice to himself, was in the mountains which he loved; his honeymoon presumably. Malahide, on the other hand, preferred his stars, though details of this have left me beyond recovery … Yet, while we lingered, respectively, among rivers of gold and stars and snowy peaks, we were solidly side by side in the actual present, crossing the country fields towards Barton-in-Fabis on this April morning.

The gradual passing of this state remains fairly clear in me.

There came signs, I remember, of distress and effort in our relationships. This, at least, was the first touch of sorrow that I noticed. I was coming back to the surface, as it were. The change was more in myself than in the others. There was argument about footpath, signposts, and the way to Barton generally.

“The fellow has planted his last post,” I heard Malahide complaining, “Now he’ll begin pulling them all up again. He both wants us to get to Barton, yet doesn’t want it.” He paused. His usual laugh did not follow. “You know,” he went on, his whisper choking a little oddly in his throat, “he rather—puts the wind up me.” A spasm ran over his big body. Then suddenly, he added, half to himself, with an effort painfully like a gasp, “I can’t get my breath—quite.”

Forden spoke very quickly in his delicate way, resignation rather sweetly mingled in it: “Well, at any rate, we’re all right so far, for I see the porter’s farm and gate at last.” He started and pointed. “Over there, you see.” Only, instead of pointing across the fields, he—to my sharp dismay—looked and pointed straight into the sky above him.

It was the fear in Malahide that chiefly afflicted me. And the pain of this, I remember, caused me to make an effort—which was an unwise thing to do. I drew attention to the ordinary things about us:

“Look, there’s a hill,” I cried.

“God!” exclaimed Forden, with quiet admiration, “what amazing things you say!” While Malahide began to sing again with happiness.

His reaction to my sentence forced me to realise the increasing change in myself. As I uttered the words I knew their third meaning; in the plain sentences was something that equalled in value: “See! the Heavens are open. There is God!” My companions still heard this third meaning, for I saw the look of majesty in Malahide’s great eyes, the love and beauty upon Forden’s shining face. But, for myself, having spoken, there remained—suddenly—nothing more than a commonplace low hill upon the near horizon. The gate and farm I saw as well. A feeling of tears rose in me, for the straining effort for recovery was without result, anguished and bitter beyond words.

I stole a glance at my companions. And that strange word Malahide had used came back to me, but with a deep, an awful sense of intolerable regret, as though its third meaning were gone beyond recall, and only two rather empty and foolish syllables remained. …

It was passing, yes, for all three of us now; the gates of ivory were closing; there was confusion, and a rather crude foolishness. Oddly enough, it was Forden—seeing that he was altogether a slighter fellow than Malahide—it was Forden who rose most slowly to the surface. Very gradually indeed he left the deeps we had all known together. To all that he now said and did Malahide responded with an aggravating giggle. He said such foolish things, confused, uncomfortable to listen to. His nerves showed signs of being frayed. He became a trifle sullen, a little frightened as well, and in his gait and gesture lay a disconcerting hurry and uncertainty, as though, hesitating to make a decision of some vital sort, he was flurried, almost in a frenzy sometimes, trying vainly to escape. This stupid confusion in him afflicted me, but the effort to escape seemed to paralyse something in my mind. It was petrifying . … And thus the sequence of what followed, proved extraordinarily difficult to remember afterwards. An atmosphere of sadness, of foreboding, of premonition came over me; there was desolation in my heart; there were stabs of horrible presentiment. All these, moreover, were ever vaguely related to one thing—that inexplicable faint odour of burning. …

What memory recalls can be told very briefly. It lies in my mind thus, condensed and swift:

The storm was natural enough, but, here again, the smell of burning alarmed and wrung me. It was faint, it was fugitive. Our mistake about the river had no importance, for the depression in the landscape might easily after all have held flowing water. The roofs, too, were not the roofs of Barton, but of a hamlet nestling among orchards, Clifden by name, and it was here, Forden informed us, he had first met his wife and had proposed to her; this also of no importance, except that he went on talking about it, and that it surprised him. He suddenly recognised the place, I mean. It increased his bewilderment, and is mentioned for that reason.

The storm, then, came abruptly. We had not seen it coming. Following a low line of hills, it overtook us from behind, bringing its own wind with it. The rustling of the leaves was the first thing I noticed. The trees about us began to shake and bend. The sparkling brilliance, I saw, had left the day; the sun shone dully; the fields were no longer radiant; the flowers, too, were gone, for we were crossing a ploughed field at the moment.

The discussion between us may be omitted; its confusion is really beyond me to describe. The storm, however, is easily described, for everyone has seen that curious thickening of the air on a day in high summer, when the clouds are not really clouds, but come as a shapeless, murky gloom, threatening a portentous downpour, while yet no single raindrop falls. In childhood we called it “blight,” believing it to be composed of myriads of tiny insects. Lurid effects of lighting accompanied it, trees and roofs, against its dark background, looking as if stage flares illumined them. The whole picture, indeed, was theatrical in the extreme, artificial almost; but the aspect that I, personally, found so unwelcome, was that it laid over the sky an appearance of volumes of dense, heavy smoke. The idea of burning may, or may not, have been in my own mind only, for my companions made no comment on it. I cannot say. That it made my heart sink I remember clearly.

It was a sham storm, it had no meaning, nothing happened. Having accomplished its spectacular effect, it passed along the hills and dissipated, and the sun shone out with all its former brilliance. Yet, before it passed, certain things occurred; they came and went, it seemed to me afterwards, with the simultaneity of dream happenings. Forden, noticing the wall of gloom advancing, catching the noise of the trees as well, stopped dead in his tracks, and stared. He sniffed the air, but made no comment. An expression of utter bewilderment draped his face. He seemed once more bewitched. It was here the smell of burning came to me most strongly.

“Look out!” he cried, and started to run. He ran in front of us, we did not attempt to follow. But he ran in a circle, like a terrified animal. His figure went shifting quickly, silhouetted, like the trees and roofs, against the murky background of the low-hanging storm. A moment later he was beside us again, his face white, his eyes shining, his breath half-gone.

“Come on, old Fordy,” said Malahide affectionately, taking him by the arm. He, for some reason, was not affected. “It’s not going to rain, you know, and anyhow there’s no good running. Let’s sit down and eat our lunch.” And he led the way across a few furrows to the hedge.

We ate our sandwiches and cake and apples. The sun shone hotly again. None of us smoked, I remember. For myself, the smell of burning had left something so miserable in me that I dared not smell even a lighted match. But no word was said by anybody in this, or in any other, sense. I kept my own counsel. … And it was while we lay resting idly, hardly speaking at all, that a sound reached me from the other side of the hedge: a footstep in the flowered grass. My companions exchanged quick glances, I noticed, but I did not even turn my head. I did not dare.

“He’s putting it in,” whispered Malahide, a touch of the old vehemence in his eyes. “The last one!” Forden smiled, nodded his head, and was about to add some comment of his own, when the other interrupted brusquely:

“Is that the way to Barton?” he enquired suddenly in a louder voice, something challenging, almost truculent, in the tone. He jerked his head towards the gate we had recently come through. “Through that gate and past that farm, I mean?”

The answering voice startled me. It was the owner of the footsteps, of course, behind the hedge.

“No. That’s a dead end,” came in gruff but not unpleasant country tones.

There was no more than that. It was all natural enough. Yet a lump came up in my throat as I heard. I still dared not look round over my shoulder. I looked instead into Forden’s face, so close beside me. “We’re all right,” he was saying, as he glanced up a “Don’t struggle so. It’s the way we’ve got to go …” and was about to say more, when a fit of coughing caught him, as though for a moment he were about to suffocate. I hid my eyes quickly; a feeling of horror and despair swept through me; for there was terror in the sound he made; but the next second, when I looked again, the coughing had passed, and I saw in his face an expression of radiant happiness; the eyes shone wonderfully, there was a delicate, almost unearthly, beauty on his features. I found myself trembling, utterly unnerved.

“We’d better be getting on,” mentioned Malahide, in his abrupt, inconsequent fashion. “We mustn’t miss that train back.” And it was this unexpected change of key that enabled me at last to turn my head. I looked hurriedly behind the hedge. I was just in time to see a man, a farmer apparently, in the act of planting a post into the ground. He was pressing it down, at any rate, and much in the fashion of Malahide’s former play about a “fellow who planted signposts.” But he was planting—two. Side by side they already stood in the earth. One arm pointed right, the other left. They formed, thus, a cross.

The very same second, with a quiver in the air, as when two cinema pictures flash on each other’s heels with extreme rapidity, I experienced an optical delusion. I must call it such, at any rate. The focus of my sight changed instantaneously. The man was already in the distance, diminished in outline, moving away across the bright fields of golden buttercups. I saw him as I had seen him once or twice before, earlier in the day, a moving figure in the grass; and when my eyes shifted back to examine the posts, there was but a single post—a signpost whose one arm bore in faded lettering the words: “From Barton.” It pointed in the direction whence we had come. …

I followed my companions in a dream that is better left untouched by words. Led by Malahide, we passed through Clifden; we came to the Trent and were ferried across; and a little later we reached, as the porter had described, a Midland station called Attenborough. A train soon took us back to the town where we were playing. Malahide, without a word, vanished from our side the moment we left the carriage. I did not see him again until, dressed in his lordly costume, he stood in the wings that night, waiting impatiently for his entrance. I had walked home with Forden, flung myself on the bed, and dropped off into a deep two-hours’ sleep.

IX

A performance behind the scenes that night was more dramatic me, at least—than anything the enthusiastic audience witnessed from the front. The three of us met in the wings for the first time since Malahide had given us the slip at the station. High tea at six I had alone, Forden for some reason going to a shop for his meal. Malahide, for another reason, ate nothing. We met, anyhow, at our respective posts in the wings. Neither Forden nor I were on till late in the second act, and as we came down the rickety stairs from separate dressing-rooms, at the same moment it so chanced, I realised at once that he was as little inclined to talk as I was. My own mind was still too packed with the whirling wonder of the whole affair for utterance. We nodded, then dropped back towards the door through which he would presently make his entrance.

It was just then, while someone was whispering “He’s giving a marvellous performance tonight,” that Malahide swept by me from his exit and ran to his dressing-room for a hurried change.

“Hullo, Hubert!” he cried in his tempestuous way. “I say …” as though it surprised him to see me there. “By the by,” he rattled on, stopping dead for a breathless second in the rush to his room, “there’s a place called Barton I want to see—Barton-in-Fabis. Let’s go tomorrow. There’s a train at 10:15. Forden can come too!” And he was gone. Gone too, I realised with a dreadful sinking of the heart, a trembling of the nerves as well—utterly gone as though it had never happened, was all memory of the day’s adventure. The mind in Malahide was blank as a clean-washed slate.

And Forden—standing close behind him within easy earshot—my eye fell upon Forden, who had heard every single word. I saw him stare and bite his lips. He passed a hand aimlessly across his forehead. His eyelids flickered. There was a quiver of the lips. In his old man’s wig and makeup, he looked neither himself nor the part he was just about to play. Waiting there for his cue, now imminent, he stared fixedly at Malahide’s vanishing figure, then at me, then blankly into space. He was like a man about to fall. He looked bewitched again. A moment’s intense strain shot across the delicate features. He made in that instant, I am convinced, a tremendous, a violent, effort to recapture something that evaded him, an effort that failed completely. The next second, too swift to be measurable, that amazing expression, the angel’s, shone out amazingly. It flashed and vanished. … His cue sounded. He, too, was gone.

How I made my own entrance, I hardly know. Five minutes later we met on the stage. He was normal. He was acting beautifully. His mind, like Malahide’s, was a clean-washed slate.

X

My one object was to avoid speech with either Malahide or Forden. The former was on the stage until the end of the play, but the latter made no appearance in the last act. I slipped out the moment I was free to go. Malahide’s door was ajar, but he did not see me. Foregoing supper, I was safely in bed when I heard Forden come upstairs soon after midnight. I fell into an uneasy sleep that must have been deeper, however, than it seemed, for I did not hear Malahide come in, but I was wide awake on the instant, dread clutching me with gripping force, when I heard Forden’s voice outside my door.

“It’s half-past nine!” he warned me. “We mustn’t miss the train, remember!”

After gulping down some coffee, I went with him to the station, and he was normal and collected as you please. We chatted in our usual fashion. Clearly, his mind held no new, strange thing of any sort. Malahide was there before us. …

The day, for me, was a nightmare of appalling order. A kind of mystical horror held me in a vice. Half-memories of bewildering and incredible things haunted me. The odour of burning, faint but unmistakable, was never absent. …

We took single tickets to Stanton, Malahide reading a pile of papers and commenting volubly on the criticisms of the play. A porter at the station gave us confused directions. We followed faulty signposts, ancient and illegible, losing ourselves rather stupidly … and I noticed a man—a farmer with a spud—wandering about the fields and making thrusts from time to time at thistles. A sham storm followed a low line of hills, but no rain fell, and the brilliance of the April day was otherwise unspoilt. Barton itself we never reached, but we crossed the Trent on our way to a station called Attenborough, first passing a hamlet, Clifden, where, Forden informed us, he had met the girl he later made his wife.

It was a dull and uninspired expedition, Malahide voluble without being articulate, Forden rather silent on the whole … and at the home station Malahide gave us the slip without a word … but during the entire outing neither one nor other betrayed the slightest hint of familiarity with anything they had known before. In myself the memory lay mercilessly sharp and clear. I noted each startling contrast between the one and other. At the end I was worn out, bone-tired, every nerve seemed naked … and, again, I left the theatre alone, ran home, and went supperless to bed.

My determination was to keep awake at all costs, but sleep caught me too easily, as I believed it was meant to catch me. No such little thing as a warning was allowed to override what had to be, what had already been. … In the early hours of the morning, about two o’clock, to be exact, I woke from a nightmare of overwhelming vividness. Wide awake I was, the instant I opened my eyes. The nightmare was one of suffocation. I was being suffocated, and I carried over into waking consciousness the smell of burning and the atmosphere of smoke. The room, I saw at once, was full of smoke, the burning was not a dream. I was being suffocated. But in my case the suffocation was not complete, whereas Malahide and Forden died, according to the doctors, in their sleep. They did not even wake. They knew no pain.

May Day Eve

I

It was in the spring when I at last found time from the hospital work to visit my friend, the old folk-lorist, in his country isolation, and I rather chuckled to myself, because in my bag I was taking down a book that utterly refuted all his tiresome pet theories of magic and the powers of the soul.

These theories were many and various, and had often troubled me. In the first place, I scorned them for professional reasons, and, in the second, because I had never been able to argue quite well enough to convince or to shake his faith, in even the smallest details, and any scientific knowledge I brought to bear only fed him with confirmatory data. To find such a book, therefore, and to know that it was safely in my bag, wrapped up in brown paper and addressed to him, was a deep and satisfactory joy, and I speculated a good deal during the journey how he would deal with the overwhelming arguments it contained against the existence of any important region outside the world of sensory perceptions.

Speculative, too, I was whether his visionary habits and absorbing experiments would permit him to remember my arrival at all, and I was accordingly relieved to hear from the solitary porter that the “professor” had sent a “veeckle” to meet me, and that I was thus free to send my bag and walk the four miles to the house across the hills.

It was a calm, windless evening, just after sunset, the air warm and scented, and delightfully still. The train, already sinking into distance, carried away with it the noise of crowds and cities and the last suggestions of the stressful life behind me, and from the little station on the moorland I stepped at once into the world of silent, growing things, tinkling sheep-bells, shepherds, and wild, desolate spaces.

My path lay diagonally across the turfy hills. It slanted a mile or so to the summit, wandered vaguely another two miles among gorse-bushes along the crest, passed Tom Bassett’s cottage by the pines, and then dropped sharply down on the other side through rather thin woods to the ancient house where the old folk-lorist lived and dreamed himself into his impossible world of theory and fantasy. I fell to thinking busily about him during the first part of the ascent, and convinced myself, as usual, that, but for his generosity to the poor, and his benign aspect, the peasantry must undoubtedly have regarded him as a wizard who speculated in souls and had dark dealings with the world of faery.

The path I knew tolerably well. I had already walked it once before—a winter’s day some years ago—and from the cottage onward felt sure of my way; but for the first mile or so there were so many cross cattle-tracks, and the light had become so dim that I felt it wise to inquire more particularly. And this I was fortunately able to do of a man who with astonishing suddenness rose from the grass where he had been lying behind a clump of bushes, and passed a few yards in front of me at a high pace downhill toward the darkening valley.

He was in such a state of hurry that I called out loudly to him, fearing to be too late, but on hearing my voice he turned sharply, and seemed to arrive almost at once beside me. In a single instant he was standing there, quite close, looking, with a smile and a certain expression of curiosity, I thought, into my face. I remember thinking that his features, pale and wholly untanned, were rather wonderful for a countryman, and that the eyes were those of a foreigner; his great swiftness, too, gave me a distinct sensation—something almost of a start—though I knew my vision was at fault at the best of times, and of course especially so in the deceptive twilight of the open hillside.

Moreover—as the way often is with such instructions—the words did not stay in my mind very clearly after he had uttered them, and the rapid, panther-like movements of the man as he quickly vanished down the hill again left me with little more than a sweeping gesture indicating the line I was to follow. No doubt his sudden rising from behind the gorse-bush, his curious swiftness, and the way he peered into my face, and even touched me on the shoulder, all combined to distract my attention somewhat from the actual words he used; and the fact that I was travelling at a wrong angle, and should have come out a mile too far to the right, helped to complete my feeling that his gesture, pointing the way, was sufficient.

On the crest of the ridge, panting a little with the unwonted exertion, I lay down to rest a moment on the grass beside a flaming yellow gorse-bush. There was still a good hour before I should be looked for at the house; the grass was very soft, the peace and silence soothing. I lingered, and lit a cigarette. And it was just then, I think, that my subconscious memory gave back the words, the actual words, the man had spoken, and the heavy significance of the personal pronoun, as he had emphasised it in his odd foreign voice, touched me with a sense of vague amusement: “The safest way for you now,” he had said, as though I was so obviously a townsman and might be in danger on the lonely hills after dark. And the quick way he had reached my side, and then slipped off again like a shadow down the steep slope, completed a definite little picture in my mind. Then other thoughts and memories rose up and formed a series of pictures, following each other in rapid succession, and forming a chain of reflections undirected by the will and without purpose or meaning. I fell, that is, into a pleasant reverie.

Below me, and infinitely far away, it seemed, the valley lay silent under a veil of blue evening haze, the lower end losing itself among darkening hills whose peaks rose here and there like giant plumes that would surely nod their great heads and call to one another once the final shadows were down. The village lay, a misty patch, in which lights already twinkled. A sound of rooks faintly cawing, of seagulls crying far up in the sky, and of dogs barking at a great distance rose up out of the general murmur of evening voices. Odours of farm and field and open spaces stole to my nostrils, and everything contributed to the feeling that I lay on the top of the world, nothing between me and the stars, and that all the huge, free things of the earth—hills, valleys, woods, and sloping fields—lay breathing deeply about me.

A few seagulls—in daytime hereabouts they fill the air—still circled and wheeled within range of sight, uttering from time to time sharp, petulant cries; and far in the distance there was just visible a shadowy line that showed where the sea lay.

Then, as I lay gazing dreamily into this still pool of shadows at my feet, something rose up, something sheetlike, vast, imponderable, off the whole surface of the mapped-out country, moved with incredible swiftness down the valley, and in a single instant climbed the hill where I lay and swept by me, yet without hurry, and in a sense without speed. Veils in this way rose one after another, filling the cups between the hills, shrouding alike fields, village, and hillside as they passed, and settled down somewhere into the gloom behind me over the ridge, or slipped off like vapour into the sky.

Whether it was actually mist rising from the surface of the fast-cooling ground, or merely the earth giving up her heat to the night, I could not determine. The coming of the darkness is ever a series of mysteries. I only know that this indescribable vast stirring of the landscape seemed to me as though the earth were unfolding immense sable wings from her sides, and lifting them for silent, gigantic strokes so that she might fly more swiftly from the sun into the night. The darkness, at any rate, did drop down over everything very soon afterward, and I rose up hastily to follow my pathway, realising with a degree of wonder strangely new to me the magic of twilight, the blue open depths into the valley below, and the pale yellow heights of the watery sky above.

I walked rapidly, a sense of chilliness about me, and soon lost sight of the valley altogether as I got upon the ridge proper of these lonely and desolate hills.

It could not have been more than fifteen minutes that I lay there in reverie, yet the weather, I at once noticed, had changed very abruptly, for mist was seething here and there about me, rising somewhere from smaller valleys in the hills beyond, and obscuring the path, while overhead there was plainly a sound of wind tearing past, far up, with a sound of high shouting. A moment before it had been the stillness of a warm spring night, yet now everything had changed; wet mist coated me, raindrops smartly stung my face, and a gusty wind, descending out of cool heights, began to strike and buffet me, so that I buttoned my coat and pressed my hat more firmly upon my head.

The change was really this—and it came to me for the first time in my life with the power of a real conviction—that everything about me seemed to have become suddenly alive.

It came oddly upon me—prosaic, matter-of-fact, materialistic doctor that I was—this realisation that the world about me had somehow stirred into life; oddly, I say, because Nature to me had always been merely a more or less definite arrangement of measurement, weight, and colour, and this new presentation of it was utterly foreign to my temperament. A valley to me was always a valley; a hill, merely a hill; a field, so many acres of flat surface, grass or ploughed, drained well or drained ill; whereas now, with startling vividness, came the strange, haunting idea that after all they could be something more than valley, hill, and field; that what I had hitherto perceived by these names were only the veils of something that lay concealed within, something alive. In a word, that the poetic sense I had always rather sneered at, in others, or explained away with some shallow physiological label, had apparently suddenly opened up in myself without any obvious cause.

And, the more I puzzled over it, the more I began to realise that its genesis dated from those few minutes of reverie lying under the gorse-bush (reverie, a thing I had never before in all my life indulged in!), or, now that I came to reflect more accurately, from my brief interview with that wild-eyed, swift-moving, shadowy man of whom I had first inquired the way.

I recalled my singular fancy that veils were lifting off the surface of the hills and fields, and a tremor of excitement accompanied the memory. Such a thing had never before been possible to my practical intelligence, and it made me feel suspicious—suspicious about myself. I stood still a moment—I looked about me into the gathering mist, above me to the vanishing stars, below me to the hidden valley, and then sent an urgent summons to my individuality, as I had always known it, to arrest and chase these undesirable fancies.

But I called in vain. No answer came. Anxiously, hurriedly, confusedly, too, I searched for my normal self, but could not find it; and this failure to respond induced in me a sense of uneasiness that touched very nearly upon the borders of alarm.

I pushed on faster and faster along the turfy track among the gorse-bushes with a dread that I might lose the way altogether, and a sudden desire to reach home as soon as might be. Then, without warning, I emerged unexpectedly into clear air again, and the vapour swept past me in a rushing wall and rose into the sky. Anew I saw the lights of the village behind me in the depths, here and there a line of smoke rising against the pale yellow sky, and stars overhead peering down through thin wispy clouds that stretched their wind-signs across the night.

After all, it had been nothing but a stray bit of sea-fog driving up from the coast, for the other side of the hills, I remembered, dipped their chalk cliffs straight into the sea, and strange lost winds must often come a-wandering this way with the sharp changes of temperature about sunset. Nonetheless, it was disconcerting to know that mist and storm lay hiding within possible reach, and I walked on smartly for a sight of Tom Bassett’s cottage and the lights of the Manor House in the valley a short mile beyond.

The clearing of the air, however, lasted but a very brief while, and vapour was soon rising about me as before, hiding the path and making bushes and stone walls look like running shadows. It came, driven apparently, by little independent winds up the many side gullies, and it was very cold, touching my skin like a wet sheet. Curious great shapes, too, it assumed as the wind worked to and fro through it: forms of men and animals; grotesque, giant outlines; ever shifting and running along the ground with silent feet, or leaping into the air with sharp cries as the gusts twisted them inwardly and lent them voice. More and more I pushed my pace, and more and more darkness and vapour obliterated the landscape. The going was not otherwise difficult, and here and there cowslips glimmered in patches of dancing yellow, while the springy turf made it easy to keep up speed; yet in the gloom I frequently tripped and plunged into prickly gorse near the ground, so that from shin to knee was soon a-tingle with sharp pain. Odd puffs and spits of rain stung my face, and the periods of utter stillness were always followed by little shouting gusts of wind, each time from a new direction. Troubled is perhaps too strong a word, but flustered I certainly was; and though I recognised that it was due to my being in an environment so remote from the town life I was accustomed to, I found it impossible to stifle altogether the feeling of malaise that had crept into my heart, and I looked about with increasing eagerness for the lighted windows of Bassett’s cottage.

More and more, little pinpricks of distress and confusion accumulated, adding to my realisation of being away from streets and shopwindows, and things I could classify and deal with. The mist, too, distorted as well as concealed, played tricks with sounds as well as with sights. And, once or twice, when I stumbled upon some crouching sheep, they got up without the customary alarm and hurry of sheep, and moved off slowly into the darkness, but in such a singular way that I could almost have sworn they were not sheep at all, but human beings crawling on all-fours, looking back and grimacing at me over their shoulders as they went. On these occasions—for there were more than one—I never could get close enough to feel their woolly wet backs, as I should have liked to do; and the sound of their tinkling bells came faintly through the mist, sometimes from one direction, sometimes from another, sometimes all round me as though a whole flock surrounded me; and I found it impossible to analyse or explain the idea I received that they were not sheep-bells at all, but something quite different.

But mist and darkness, and a certain confusion of the senses caused by the excitement of an utterly strange environment, can account for a great deal. I pushed on quickly. The conviction that I had strayed from the route grew, nevertheless, for occasionally there was a great commotion of seagulls about me, as though I had disturbed them in their sleeping-places. The air filled with their plaintive cries, and I heard the rushing of multitudinous wings, sometimes very close to my head, but always invisible owing to the mist. And once, above the swishing of the wet wind through the gorse-bushes, I was sure I caught the faint thunder of the sea and the distant crashing of waves rolling up some steep-throated gully in the cliffs. I went cautiously after this, and altered my course a little away from the direction of the sound.

Yet, increasingly all the time, it came to me how the cries of the seabirds sounded like laughter, and how the everlasting wind blew and drove about me with a purpose, and how the low bushes persistently took the shape of stooping people, moving stealthily past me, and how the mist more and more resembled huge protean figures escorting me across the desolate hills, silently, with immense footsteps. For the inanimate world now touched my awakened poetic sense in a manner hitherto unguided, and became fraught with the pregnant messages of a dimly concealed life. I readily understood, for the first time, how easily a superstitious peasantry might people their world, and how even an educated mind might favour an atmosphere of legend. I stumbled along, looking anxiously for the lights of the cottage.

Suddenly, as a shape of writhing mist whirled past, I received so direct a stroke of wind that it was palpably a blow in the face. Something swept by with a shrill cry into the darkness. It was impossible to prevent jumping to one side and raising an arm by way of protection, and I was only just quick enough to catch a glimpse of the seagull as it raced past, with suddenly altered flight, beating its powerful wings over my head. Its white body looked enormous as the mist swallowed it. At the same moment a gust tore my hat from my head and flung the flap of my coat across my eyes. But I was well-trained by this time, and made a quick dash after the retreating black object, only to find on overtaking it that I held a prickly branch of gorse. The wind combed my hair viciously. Then, out of a corner of my eye, I saw my hat still rolling, and grabbed swiftly at it; but just as I closed on it, the real hat passed in front of me, turning over in the wind like a ball, and I instantly released my first capture to chase it. Before it was within reach, another one shot between my feet so that I stepped on it. The grass seemed covered with moving hats, yet each one, when I seized it, turned into a piece of wood, or a tiny gorse-bush, or a black rabbit hole, till my hands were scored with prickles and running blood. In the darkness, I reflected, all objects looked alike, as though by general conspiracy.

I straightened up and took a long breath, mopping the blood with my handkerchief. Then something tapped at my feet, and on looking down, there was the hat within easy reach, and I stooped down and put it on my head again. Of course, there were a dozen ways of explaining my confusion and stupidity, and I walked along wondering which to select. My eyesight, for one thing—and under such conditions why seek further? It was nothing, after all, and the dizziness was a momentary effect caused by the effort and stooping.

But for all that, I shouted aloud, on the chance that a wandering shepherd might hear me; and of course no answer came, for it was like calling in a padded room, and the mist suffocated my voice and killed its resonance.

It was really very discouraging: I was cold and wet and hungry; my legs and clothes torn by the gorse, my hands scratched and bleeding; the wind brought water to my eyes by its constant buffeting, and my skin was numb from contact with the chill mist. Fortunately I had matches, and after some difficulty, by crouching under a wall, I caught a swift glimpse of my watch, and saw that it was but little after eight o’clock. Supper I knew was at nine, and I was surely over halfway by this time. But here again was another instance of the way everything seemed in a conspiracy against me to appear otherwise than ordinary, for in the gleam of the match my watch-glass showed as the face of a little old gray man, uncommonly like the folk-lorist himself, peering up at me with an expression of whimsical laughter. My own reflection it could not possibly have been, for I am clean-shaven, and this face looked up at me through a running tangle of gray hair. Yet a second and third match revealed only the white surface with the thin black hands moving across it.

II

And it was at this point, I well remember, that I reached what was for me the true heart of the adventure, the little fragment of real experience I learned from it and took back with me to my doctor’s life in London, and that has remained with me ever since, and helped me to a new sympathetic insight into the intricacies of certain curious mental cases I had never before really understood.

For it was sufficiently obvious by now that a curious change had been going forward in me for some time, dating, so far as I could focus my thoughts sufficiently to analyse, from the moment of my speech with that hurrying man of shadow on the hillside. And the first deliberate manifestation of the change, now that I looked back, was surely the awakening in my prosaic being of the “poetic thrill”; my sudden amazing appreciation of the world around me as something alive. From that moment the change in me had worked ahead subtly, swiftly. Yet, so natural had been the beginning of it, that although it was a radically new departure for my temperament, I was hardly aware at first of what had actually come about; and it was only now, after so many encounters, that I was forced at length to acknowledge it.

It came the more forcibly too, because my very commonplace ideas of beauty had hitherto always been associated with sunshine and crude effects; yet here this new revelation leaped to me out of wind and mist and desolation on a lonely hillside, out of night, darkness, and discomfort. New values rushed upon me from all sides. Everything had changed, and the very simplicity with which the new values presented themselves proved to me how profound the change, the readjustment, had been. In such trivial things the evidence had come that I was not aware of it until repetition forced my attention: the veils rising from valley and hill; the mountain tops as personalities that shout or murmur in the darkness; the crying of the sea birds and of the living, purposeful wind; above all, the feeling that Nature about me was instinct with a life differing from my own in degree rather than in kind; everything, from the conspiracy of the gorse-bushes to the disappearing hat, showed that a fundamental attitude of mind in me had changed—and changed, too, without my knowledge or consent.

Moreover, at the same time the deep sadness of beauty had entered my heart like a stroke; for all this mystery and loveliness, I realized poignantly was utterly independent and careless of me, as me; and that while I must pass, decay, grow old, these manifestations would remain forever young and unalterably potent. And thus gradually had I become permeated with the recognition of a region hitherto unknown to me, and that I had always depreciated in others and especially, it now occurred to me, in my friend the old folk-lorist.

Here surely, I thought, was the beginning of conditions which, carried a little further, must become pathogenic. That the change was real and pregnant I had no doubt whatever. My consciousness was expanding and I had caught it in the very act. I had of course read much concerning the changes of personality, swift, kaleidoscopic—had come across something of it in my practice—and had listened to the folk-lorist holding forth like a man inspired upon ways and means of reaching concealed regions of the human consciousness, and opening it to the knowledge of things called magical, so that one became free of a larger universe. But it was only now for the first time, on these bare hills, in touch with the wind and the rain, that I realized in how simple a fashion the frontiers of consciousness could shift this way and that, or with what touch of genuine awe the certainty might come that one stood on the borderland of new, untried, perhaps dangerous, experiences.

At any rate, it did now come to me that my consciousness had shifted its frontiers very considerably, and that whatever might happen must seem not abnormal, but quite simple and inevitable, and of course utterly true. This very simplicity, however, doing no violence to my being, brought with it nonetheless a sense of dread and discomfort; and my dim awareness that unknown possibilities were about me in the night puzzled and distressed me perhaps more than I cared to admit.

III

All this that takes so long to describe became apparent to me in a few seconds. What I had always despised ascended the throne.

But with the finding of Bassett’s cottage, as a signpost close to home, my former sangfroid, my stupidity, would doubtless return, and my relief was therefore considerable when at length a faint gleam of light appeared through the mist, against which the square dark shadow of the chimney-line pointed upwards. After all, I had not strayed so very far out of the way. Now I could definitely ascertain where I was wrong.

Quickening my pace, I scrambled over a broken stone wall, and almost ran across the open bit of grass to the door. One moment the black outline of the cottage was there in front of me, and the next, when I stood actually against it—there was nothing! I laughed to think how utterly I had been deceived. Yet not utterly, for as I groped back again over the wall, the cottage loomed up a little to the left, with its windows lighted and friendly, and I had only been mistaken in my angle of approach after all. Yet again, as I hurried to the door, the mist drove past and thickened a second time—and the cottage was not where I had seen it!

My confusion increased a lot after that. I scrambled about in all directions, rather foolishly hurried, and over countless stone walls it seemed, and completely dazed as to the true points of the compass. Then suddenly, just when a kind of despair came over me, the cottage stood there solidly before my eyes, and I found myself not two feet from the door. Was ever mist before so deceptive? And there, just behind it, I made out the row of pines like a dark wave breaking through the night. I sniffed the wet resinous odour with joy, and a genuine thrill ran through me as I saw the unmistakable yellow light of the windows. At last I was near home and my troubles would soon be over.

A cloud of birds rose with shrill cries off the roof and whirled into the darkness when I knocked with my stick on the door, and human voices, I was almost certain, mingled somewhere with them, though it was impossible to tell whether they were within the cottage or outside. It all sounded confusedly with a rush of air like a little whirlwind, and I stood there rather alarmed at the clamour of my knocking. By way, too, of further proof that my imagination had awakened, the significance of that knocking at the door set something vibrating within me that most surely had never vibrated before, so that I suddenly realized with what atmosphere of mystical suggestion is the mere act of knocking surrounded—knocking at a door—both for him who knocks, wondering what shall be revealed on opening, and for him who stands within, waiting for the summons of the knocker. I only know that I hesitated a lot before making up my mind to knock a second time.

And, anyhow, what happened subsequently came in a sort of haze. Words and memory both failed me when I try to record it truthfully, so that even the faces are difficult to visualise again, the words almost impossible to hear.

Before I knew it the door was open and before I could frame the words of my first brief question, I was within the threshold, and the door was shut behind me.

I had expected the little dark and narrow hallway of a cottage, oppressive of air and odour, but instead I came straight into a room that was full of light and full of—people. And the air tasted like the air about a mountain-top.

To the end I never saw what produced the light, nor understood how so many men and women found space to move comfortably to and fro, and pass each other as they did, within the confines of those four walls. An uncomfortable sense of having intruded upon some private gathering was, I think, my first emotion; though how the poverty-stricken countryside could have produced such an assemblage puzzled me beyond belief. And my second emotion—if there was any division at all in the wave of wonder that fairly drenched me—was feeling a sort of glory in the presence of such an atmosphere of splendid and vital youth. Everything vibrated, quivered, shook about me, and I almost felt myself as an aged and decrepit man by comparison.

I know my heart gave a great fiery leap as I saw them, for the faces that met me were fine, vigourous, and comely, while burning everywhere through their ripe maturity shone the ardours of youth and a kind of deathless enthusiasm. Old, yet eternally young they were, as rivers and mountains count their years by thousands, yet remain ever youthful; and the first effect of all those pairs of eyes lifted to meet my own was to send a whirlwind of unknown thrills about my heart and make me catch my breath with mingled terror and delight. A fear of death, and at the same time a sensation of touching something vast and eternal that could never die, surged through me.

A deep hush followed my entrance as all turned to look at me. They stood, men and women, grouped about a table, and something about them—not their size alone—conveyed the impression of being gigantic, giving me strangely novel realisations of freedom, power, and immense existence more or less than human.

I can only record my thoughts and impressions as they came to me and as I dimly now remember them. I had expected to see old Tom Bassett crouching half asleep over a peat fire, a dim lamp on the table beside him, and instead this assembly of tall and splendid men and women stood there to greet me, and stood in silence. It was little wonder that at first the ready question died upon my lips, and I almost forgot the words of my own language.

“I thought this was Tom Bassett’s cottage!” I managed to ask at length, and looked straight at the man nearest me across the table. He had wild hair falling about his shoulders and a face of clear beauty. His eyes, too, like all the rest, seemed shrouded by something veil-like that reminded me of the shadowy man of whom I had first inquired the way. They were shaded—and for some reason I was glad they were.

At the sound of my voice, unreal and thin, there was a general movement throughout the room, as though everyone changed places, passing each other like those shapes of fluid sort I had seen outside in the mist. But no answer came. It seemed to me that the mist even penetrated into the room about me and spread inwardly over my thoughts.

“Is this the way to the Manor House?” I asked again, louder, fighting my inward confusion and weakness. “Can no one tell me?”

Then apparently everyone began to answer at once, or rather, not to answer directly, but to speak to each other in such a way that I could easily overhear. The voices of the men were deep, and of the women wonderfully musical, with a slow rhythm like that of the sea, or of the wind through the pine-trees outside. But the unsatisfactory nature of what they said only helped to increase my sense of confusion and dismay.

“Yes,” said one; “Tom Bassett was here for a while with the sheep, but his home was not here.”

“He asks the way to a house when he does not even know the way to his own mind!” another voice said, sounding overhead it seemed.

“And could he recognise the signs if we told him?” came in the singing tones of a woman’s voice close behind me.

And then, with a noise more like running water, or wind in the wings of birds, than anything else I could liken it to, came several voices together:

“And what sort of way does he seek? The splendid way, or merely the easy?”

“Or the short way of fools!”

“But he must have some credentials, or he never could have got as far as this,” came from another.

A laugh ran round the room at this, though what there was to laugh at I could not imagine. It sounded like wind rushing about the hills. I got the impression too that the roof was somehow open to the sky, for their laughter had such a spacious quality in it, and the air was so cool and fresh, and moving about in currents and waves.

“It was I who showed him the way,” cried a voice belonging to someone who was looking straight into my face over the table. “It was the safest way for him once he had got so far—”

I looked up and met his eye, and the sentence remained unfinished. It was the hurrying, shadowy man of the hillside. He had the same shifting outline as the others now, and the same veiled and shaded eyes, and as I looked the sense of terror stirred and grew in me. I had come in to ask for help, but now I was only anxious to be free of them all and out again in the rain and darkness on the moor. Thoughts of escape filled my brain, and I searched quickly for the door through which I had entered. But nowhere could I discover it again. The walls were bare; not even the windows were visible. And the room seemed to fill and empty of these figures as the waves of the sea fill and empty a cavern, crowding one upon another, yet never occupying more space, or less. So the coming and going of these men and women always evaded me.

And my terror became simply a terror that the veils of their eyes might lift, and that they would look at me with their clear, naked sight. I became horribly aware of their eyes. It was not that I felt them evil, but that I feared the new depths in me their merciless and terrible insight would stir into life. My consciousness had expanded quite enough for one night! I must escape at all costs and claim my own self again, however limited. I must have sanity, even if with limitations, but sanity at any price.

But meanwhile, though I tried hard to find my voice again, there came nothing but a thin piping sound that was like reeds whistling where winds meet about a corner. My throat was contracted, and I could only produce the smallest and most ridiculous of noises. The power of movement, too, was far less than when I first came in, and every moment it became more difficult to use my muscles, so that I stood there, stiff and awkward, face to face with this assemblage of shifting, wonderful people.

“And now,” continued the voice of the man who had last spoken, “and now the safest way for him will be through the other door, where he shall see that which he may more easily understand.”

With a great effort I regained the power of movement, while at the same time a burst of anger and a determination to be done with it all and to overcome my dreadful confusion drove me forward.

He saw me coming, of course, and the others indeed opened up and made a way for me, shifting to one side or the other whenever I came too near them, and never allowing me to touch them. But at last, when I was close in front of the man, ready both to speak and act, he was no longer there. I never saw the actual change—but instead of a man it was a woman! And when I turned with amazement, I saw that the other occupants walking like figures in some ancient ceremony, were moving slowly toward the far end of the room. One by one, as they filed past, they raised their calm, passionless faces to mine, immensely vital, proud, austere, and then, without further word or gesture, they opened the door I had lost and disappeared through it one by one into the darkness of the night beyond. And as they went it seemed that the mist swallowed them up and a gust of wind caught them away, and the light also went with them, leaving me alone with the figure who had last spoken.

Moreover it was just here that a most disquieting thought flashed through my brain with unreasoning conviction, shaking my personality, as it were, to the foundations: viz., that I had hitherto been spending my life in the pursuit of false knowledge, in the mere classifying and labelling of effects, the analysis of results, scientific so called; whereas it was the folk-lorist, and suchlike, who with their dreams and prayers were all the time on the path of real knowledge, the trail of causes; that the one was merely adding to the mechanical comfort and safety of the body, ultimately degrading the highest part of man, and never advancing the type, while the other—but then I had never yet believed in a soul—and now was no time to begin, terror or no terror. Clearly, my thoughts were wandering.

IV

It was at this moment the sound of the purring first reached me—deep, guttural purring—that made me think at once of some large concealed animal. It was precisely what I had heard many a time at the Zoological Gardens, and I had visions of cows chewing the cud, or horses munching hay in a stall outside the cottage. It was certainly an animal sound, and one of pleasure and contentment.

Semidarkness filled the room. Only a very faint moonlight, struggling through the mist, came through the window, and I moved back instinctively toward the support of the wall against my back. Somewhere, through openings, came the sound of the night driving over the roof, and far above I had visions of those everlasting winds streaming by with clouds as large as continents on their wings. Something in me wanted to sing and shout, but something else in me at the same time was in a very vivid state of unreasoning terror. I felt immense, yet tiny, confident, yet timid; a part of huge, universal forces, yet an utterly small, personal, and very limited being.

In the corner of the room on my right stood the woman. Her face was hid by a mass of tumbling hair, that made me think of living grasses on a field in June. Thus her head was partially turned from me, and the moonlight, catching her outline, just revealed it against the wall like an impressionist picture. Strange hidden memories stirred in the depths of me, and for a moment I felt that I knew all about her. I stared about me quickly, nervously, trying to take in everything at once. Then the purring sound grew much louder and closer, and I forgot my notion that this woman was no stranger to me and that I knew her as well as I knew myself. That purring thing was in the room close beside me. Between us two, indeed, it was, for I now saw that her arm nearest to me was raised, and that she was pointing to the wall in front of us.

Following the direction of her hand, I saw that the wall was transparent, and that I could see through a portion of it into a small square space beyond, as though I was looking through gauze instead of bricks. This small inner space was lighted, and on stooping down I saw that it was a sort of cupboard or cell-like cage let into the wall. The thing that purred was there in the centre of it.

I looked closer. It was a being, apparently a human being, crouched down in its narrow cage, feeding. I saw the body stooping over a quantity of coarse-looking, piled-up substance that was evidently food. It was like a man huddled up. There it squatted, happy and contented, with the minimum of air, light, and space, dully satisfied with its prisoned cage behind the bars, utterly unconscious of the vast world about it, grunting with pleasure, purring like a great cat, scornfully ignorant of what might lie beyond. The cell, moreover, I saw was a perfect masterpiece of mechanical contrivance and inventive ingenuity—the very last word in comfort, safety and scientific skill. I was in the act of trying to fit in my memory some of the details of its construction and arrangement, when I made a chance noise, and at once became too agitated to note carefully what I saw. For at the noise the creature turned, and I saw that it was a human being—a man. I was aware of a face close against my own as it pressed forward, but a face with embryonic features impossible to describe and utterly loathsome, with eyes, ears, nose and skin, only just sufficiently alive and developed to transfer the minimum of gross sensation to the brain. The mouth, however, was large and thick-lipped, and the jaws were still moving in the act of slow mastication.

I shrank back, shuddering with mingled pity and disgust, and at the same moment the woman beside me called me softly by my own name. She had moved forward a little so that she stood quite close to me, full in the thin stream of moonlight that fell across the floor, and I was conscious of a swift transition from hell to heaven as my gaze passed from that embryonic visage to a countenance so refined, so majestic, so divinely sensitive in its strength, that it was like turning from the face of a devil to look upon the features of a goddess.

At the same instant I was aware that both beings—the creature and the woman—were moving rapidly toward me.

A pain like a sharp sword dived deep down into me and twisted horribly through my heart, for as I saw them coming I realized in one swift moment of terrible intuition that they had their life in me, that they were born of my own being, and were indeed projections of myself. They were portions of my consciousness projected outwardly into objectivity, and their degree of reality was just as great as that of any other part of me.

With a dreadful swiftness they rushed toward me, and in a single second had merged themselves into my own being; and I understood in some marvellous manner beyond the possibility of doubt that they were symbolic of my own soul: the dull animal part of me that had hitherto acknowledged nothing beyond its cage of minute sensations, and the higher part, almost out of reach, and in touch with the stars, that for the first time had feebly awakened into life during my journey over the hill.

V

I forget altogether how it was that I escaped, whether by the window or the door. I only know I found myself a moment later making great speed over the moor, followed by screaming birds and shouting winds, straight on the track downhill toward the Manor House. Something must have guided me, for I went with the instinct of an animal, having no uncertainties as to turnings, and saw the welcome lights of windows before I had covered another mile. And all the way I felt as though a great sluice gate had been opened to let a flood of new perceptions rush like a sea over my inner being, so that I was half ashamed and half delighted, partly angry, yet partly happy.

Servants met me at the door, several of them, and I was aware at once of an atmosphere of commotion in the house. I arrived breathless and hatless, wet to the skin, my hands scratched and my boots caked with mud.

“We made sure you were lost, sir,” I heard the old butler say, and I heard my own reply, faintly, like the voice of someone else:

“I thought so too.”

A minute later I found myself in the study, with the old folk-lorist standing opposite. In his hands he held the book I had brought down for him in my bag, ready addressed. There was a curious smile on his face.

“It never occurred to me that you would dare to walk—tonight of all nights,” he was saying.

I stared without a word. I was bursting with the desire to tell him something of what had happened and try to be patient with his explanations, but when I sought for words and sentences my story seemed suddenly flat and pointless, and the details of my adventure began to evaporate and melt away, and seemed hard to remember.

“I had an exciting walk,” I stammered, still a little breathless from running. “The weather was all right when I started from the station.”

“The weather is all right still,” he said, “though you may have found some evening mist on the top of the hills. But it’s not that I meant.”

“What then?”

“I meant,” he said, still laughing quizzically, “that you were a very brave man to walk tonight over the enchanted hills, because this is May Day eve, and on May Day eve, you know, They have power over the minds of men, and can put glamour upon the imagination—”

“Who—‘they?’ What do you mean?”

He put my book down on the table beside him and looked quietly for a moment into my eyes, and as he did so the memory of my adventure began to revive in detail, and I thought quickly of the shadowy man who had shown me the way first. What could it have been in the face of the old folk-lorist that made me think of this man? A dozen things ran like flashes through my excited mind, and while I attempted to seize them I heard the old man’s voice continue. He seemed to be talking to himself as much as to me.

“The elemental beings you have always scoffed at, of course; they who operate ceaselessly behind the screen of appearances, and who fashion and mould the moods of the mind. And an extremist like you—for extremes are always dangerously weak—is their legitimate prey.”

“Pshaw!” I interrupted him, knowing that my manner betrayed me hopelessly, and that he had guessed much. “Any man may have subjective experiences, I suppose—”

Then I broke off suddenly. The change in his face made me start; it had taken on for the moment so exactly the look of the man on the hillside. The eyes gazing so steadily into mine had shadows in them, I thought.

“Glamour!” he was saying, “all glamour! One of them must have come very close to you, or perhaps touched you.” Then he asked sharply, “Did you meet anyone? Did you speak with anyone?”

“I came by Tom Bassett’s cottage,” I said. “I didn’t feel quite sure of my way and I went in and asked.”

“All glamour,” he repeated to himself, and then aloud to me, “and as for Bassett’s cottage, it was burnt down three years ago, and nothing stands there now but broken, roofless walls—”

He stopped because I had seized him by the arm. In the shadows of the lamp-lit room behind him I thought I caught sight of dim forms moving past the bookshelves. But when my eye tried to focus them they faded and slipped away again into ceiling and walls. The details of the hilltop cottage, however, started into life again at the sight, and I seized my friend’s arm to tell him. But instantly, when I tried, it all faded away again as though it had been a dream, and I could recall nothing intelligible to repeat to him.

He looked at me and laughed.

“They always obliterate the memory afterwards,” he said gently, “so that little remains beyond a mood, or an emotion, to show how profoundly deep their touch has been. Though sometimes part of the change remains and becomes permanent—as I hope in your case it may.”

Then, before I had time to answer, to swear, or to remonstrate, he stepped briskly past me and closed the door into the hall, and then drew me aside farther into the room. The change that I could not understand was still working in his face and eyes.

“If you have courage enough left to come with me,” he said, speaking very seriously, “we will go out again and see more. Up till midnight, you know, there is still the opportunity, and with me perhaps you won’t feel so—so—”

It was impossible somehow to refuse; everything combined to make me go. We had a little food and then went out into the hall, and he clapped a wide-awake on his gray hairs. I took a cloak and seized a walking-stick from the stand. I really hardly knew what I was doing. The new world I had awakened to seemed still a-quiver about me.

As we passed out on to the gravel drive the light from the hall windows fell upon his face, and I saw that the change I had been so long observing was nearing its completeness, for there breathed about him that keen, wonderful atmosphere of eternal youth I had felt upon the inmates of the cottage. He seemed to have gone back forty years; a veil was gathering over his eyes; and I could have sworn that somehow his stature had increased, and that he moved beside me with a vigour and power I had never seen in him before.

And as we began to climb the hill together in silence I saw that the stars were clear overhead and there was no mist, that the trees stood motionless without wind, and that beyond us on the summit of the hills there were lights dancing to and fro, appearing and disappearing like the inflection of stars in water.

Memories of the Black Forest

The intricate windings of a railroad that follow charmingly the foldings of pine-clad valleys will nowadays conduct the traveller well into the more frequented portions of the Black Forest. One minute he will look down from the car window into the yawning depths of rocky gorges, with a wild torrent brawling over the stones at the bottom; while the next will show him a smiling green valley, with the same wild torrent transformed into the smoothest of clear streams. He will pass in and out of the wooded mountain slopes, as the train follows the curves and twists of the ingenious Schwarzwald railway, and after reaching a height of nearly 3,000 feet, will descend again into the plain of the Rhine.

In this way the hurried tourist may undoubtedly see a good deal of the Black Forest country.

If, however, he wishes to get away from the civilization which the prosaic railroad invariably brings with it, he must leave the cars at one of the little stations and strike northwards into the interior. With a light knapsack and a stout staff he can then follow at his leisure the lovely little paths that wind in and out amid the great trees, leading from village to village, or across the hills to the more open valleys. With no other companions than the squirrels playing among the boughs and the great buzzards circling far overhead, he may in this manner traverse wide tracts of solitary forest. He may quietly drop in upon the quaint and legend-haunted hamlets, surprising the good burghers and peasants at the occupations which have been theirs, and their fathers’ before them, for ages past. He may sit beside the sturdy peasant, in the sand-floored village inn, and from his strong, honest face may call forth many a pleasant smile, as they chat together in the most friendly manner over the important events of this hidden, secret world of trees. And he may discover the fair daughters of the forest, in their most characteristic costumes, with fantastic topknots and plumes waving from their bridal headdresses, as in our initial cut, or clad with their bright coloured skirts and bodices at work in the fields.

In an easy day’s journey from the railway he will seem to have stepped backwards into the Middle Ages; and the unfrequented portions of the Black Forest will certainly tend to keep up the illusion. It is only in this manner that the remnant of the vast Hercynian Forest can be seen to the fullest advantage. To be really known the Schwarzwald must be studied in all its aspects during the different seasons of the year.

The Black Forest on a still, hot day in August, when the tall pines rise motionless against the blue sky, like the beautiful spires of some old cathedral, is not the same Black Forest we see in an autumn storm. Then the whole forest seems to sway to and fro as the winds roar through its myriads of branches and the trees and sky mingle in impenetrable gloom. Nor is it the Black Forest in its white winter robes, when all its sounds are deadened by the thick snow.

But the weird loveliness of the Schwarzwald can only be appreciated by those who have watched the changes that grow upon its stern face under the wondrous lights of sunrise or sunset; or as night creeps slowly over its hills or villages, investing them with a blackness all their own; or again, in the magic hours that follow sunset and precede the dawn. With this object in view, perhaps the best place for the traveller to leave the train is at Somerau. This little station is the highest point on the line, and immediately after leaving it the train begins its long descent. The country in the immediate neighbourhood of this typical village is more open than in many parts; and a rough little path leads up a steep slope where the pines are less dense. A short hour’s climbing brings one to the summit, and the view that bursts upon the sight is surprisingly extensive. In great undulating waves the gloomy hills of the Schwarzwald roll away on every side as far as the eye can reach. The air that sweeps across the summit is sweet and pure, and it is as redolent of the ocean of fragrant pines it has crossed as the sea breeze is of brine and ozone. If the day be dull and the horizon cloudy, the general aspect of the view is so gloomy that the origin of the word Schwarzwald at once suggests itself with great force. It is indeed a black forest.

It is strange that this spot, with its so beautiful view, should have been selected in the dim past as the place of execution for witches and criminals. Yet so it was; and the remnants of the rude gallows still rear themselves up ugly and gaunt into the air—two roughly hewn granite slabs, across the top of which formerly rested a third slab. As late as 1847 there was an execution in this place, when an old witch, so-called, was hanged from these very granite slabs. There seems a refinement of cruelty in the idea that the victim’s last view of mother earth was one so fair. The forbidding blackness of the nearer forest soon fades into the softer blues and rich purples of the far distance; while the various shades between the two enormously enhance the general effect.

Such a view can never, of course, be called bright or glorious. It is too sombre, not to say even monotonous. Yet herein lies the peculiar charm of the Schwarzwald. There is about it a certain grim grandeur; a stateliness and an indefinable dignity that seem to link it with hoar antiquity. It is strangely invested with that sense of strength and greatness that surrounds the ruined old castles of England. The tall, straight pines that guard the dark interior of the Schwarzwald seem to demand of us the respect due to the ancient home of so many wild and beautiful legends, of so many deeds of valour and renown.

The ever-increasing stream of tourists that yearly tramp through the more accessible portions of the forest would certainly seem to be driving to the remoter regions those customs and practices which are more especially peculiar to the people. However this may be, the belief in those picturesque forms of the supernatural—gnomes, fairies, wizards and water nixies—still clings to the haunts that for centuries have been their home. In many a village and farmhouse the past yet lives on in the present, clinging to the hearts of the simple-minded folk that love to cherish it.

At the foot of the bold spur of hills of which we have spoken nestles a charming little village—Furtwangen. It is a centre for straw-plaiting, which, next to woodcarving, is the chief industry of the peasants in the southern portion. But instead of descending the rough path to the valley, let us return to Somerau. Here again we are in a Protestant community, while Furtwangen is Roman Catholic, and the roads are often adorned with little chapels or crucifixes, before which the peasants offer up a short prayer in passing.

Following the railway for a mile or more, we come to the next station, Königsfeld-Peterzell. It is a lonely-looking spot; only a couple or so of houses and a few straggling old barns of enormous capacity. We leave the railway to pursue its downward course, and again ascend through the woods in a northerly direction; occasionally vistas of lovely colours and light opening out on either side.

Suddenly we leave the woods and enter upon a clearing of considerable size, in the centre of which is a little village, the very picture of precise neatness. This is Königsfeld, a Moravian settlement, and one has little difficulty in distinguishing the boys’ and girls’ schools, placed at opposite ends of the village square. In every direction glades in the forest invite to the most delightful walks. Outside the village for some distance one notices the picturesque forms of those huge, unwieldy farmhouses, with barns attached. The wooden walls, darkened with age and weather, are in great part covered with the most curious, and oftentimes the most beautiful lichens; while in the cleared spaces one may find a profusion of wild flowers, conspicuous among which is the rich purple colour of one of the gentians. In the forest itself, under the shade of the grand old trees, the moss, often twelve inches thick, presents a carpet of gorgeous colouring, offering a striking contrast to the dark stems of the pines.

When the slanting rays of the setting sun fall upon a scene like this, setting afire the golden mosses and glinting from one dark tree to another far into the forest depths, the effect is truly magical. Looking to the south, on an ordinary day there is nothing to be seen but the undulating waves of the forest, as it stretches away over the Duchy of Baden and part of Wurtemberg. But on one of those extraordinarily clear days that so often precede long spells of wet weather, a very different sight will greet the eye. From Säntis to Mont Blanc the white forms of the snowy Alps are visible hanging in the sky. So huge, so white, so grandiose do they appear that to one who has been used to the subdued tints of the surrounding Schwarzwald they come like a revelation. They seem to be suspended in the lofty atmosphere like the phantom mountains of some shadowy ghost-land, and one feels that at any moment they may suddenly melt away like a dream. It would seem that the Alps thus occasionally seen are in reality too far below the horizon to be ever actually visible, and that it is only a strong refraction caused by a certain state of the atmosphere that renders them visible at such a height above the horizon. This accounts for the enormous size and general weirdness of their appearance.

The tourist who loves to study the thousand different effects of light on forest scenery, and to converse with nature face to face under some of her most seductive aspects, cannot do better than spend a month or two in this little Moravian settlement, away from the world of noise and fashion, and surrounded by the most typical effects of Black Forest scenery.

There are many others places in the Schwarzwald that we would gladly revisit in imagination, were space and time more generous. The ruins of the old monastery of Allerheiligen—All Saints—lies farther north, in its lonely valley, with its surrounding fringe of pines faithfully guarding it from all irreverent gaze.

With what pleasure would we again stand on the spur of hills that skirts the great plain of the Rhine, where lie the fortified old cities of Strassburg and Rastatt; and from our elevated stand point watch the sunlight gleam on the distant stretches of the Rhine, lighting up the fertile country for many a wide league.

In the early spring, too, when the pines are tipped with the exquisite fresh green that comes but once a year, we would willingly take our readers to many a quaint village and farmhouse, peeping in upon the woodcarvers and the clockmakers at work, and watching the old sawmills cut up the fragrant pine logs. With what pleasure would we visit with them the blue hills that surround Baden-Baden in its beautiful valley, and show the lovely combination of colour that is caused by the mingling of the golden leaves of the early beeches with the dark velvet of the pine woods, and the blue sky seen between. Perhaps, on a future occasion, we may be able to do this, and to plunge deeper still into what will ever be the most romantic of forest lands.

Monsieur Joseph of the Ski

The banners of this gorgeous summer have trailed below the horizon, and already the leaves may be seen drifting over the waters of the Serpentine in their brilliant funeral dress. Autumn is in the air; and, not so very far behind, the least imaginative effort realises the silent gathering of the white winter clans hei marshalling takes time, and the preparation is slow and careful, but it is already under way. It betrays itself in the nip of the uir after sundown, the mist that rises over the meadows with the dusk, the brighter eyes of the stars Iwo months more ind the music of the winds will be set to another key. The intermezzo that we have still to hear, though very beautiful, is brief enough

And so, at the first hint of a change, the minds of hundreds leap across these intervening autumn weeks to think of the next stage—blazing fires in the hall, shrill winds about the house, and the atmosphere of ice and snow and frost. For hundreds of us, the number increasing with every year, the thought brings pictures of snowy slopes lying in dazzling sunshine beneath skies of cloudless blue. The snow throws up a sort of advance mirage, and with the picture and the dream there rises too a curious shape that is a symbol of it all. An outline like a pointing finger rises above the edge of the mind. It is a long and slender strip of wood, gracefully curved, narrow and shapely as a woman’s hand, strong as steel, elastic and alive, and running in front to a delicately tapered point that tilts saucily upwards to the sky—and its name is in Norwegian ski, pronounced, significantly enough, she. For an experienced “runner ” ” thinks of his ski as a man may think of his hunter, a sailor of his ship, or perhaps as fondly even as Ernst and Remenyi thought of their loved and priceless old Cremonas.

It is no time just now to write of the exhilarating delights of ski-ing. The air is still too soft, the sun too warm, the trees too sweetly covered ; but, on the other hand, it zs the moment to burrow into cupboards and sheds and into the dry lofts above the stables where winter things are put away for safety : to hunt up one’s cumbersome ski-boots and see if they will stand ‘ just one more season’; to give them an extra coating of oil before another strike comes on and sends the price up ; and, for some of us, perhaps, to climb with difficulty into the attic and make sure that the grease, rubbed into the wood when last March was whispering about the spring, has done its work, and that the lath-like and mysterious creatures have not cracked or warped in the fierce heats of the intervening summer months. And what lover of outdoor life does not welcome these little detailed duties with the zest of true joy: packing away the implements of the season when it dies and working with keen anticipation over those next in use? The process comes nearer to eating one’s cake and having it than any that | know !

And ski, in particular, repay painstaking care and trouble. Chey run fishing-rods very close in this respect. The careless- ness and ignorance of the ordinary holiday ski-er are dearly paid for in the terms of delay, exhaustion, tiresome and tiring falling, and perhaps of broken bones. For the great majority of winter-sport lovers, who go to the snow for a brief fortnight or three weeks’ holiday, hire their ski on the spot from the hotel or village shop, and thus never know the pleasure of a perfect fit, the value of the right length that suits the character of the country (short ski for trees, where turning is sharp and sudden, longer ski for open, treeless slopes where turning can be leisurely, for instance), the width and kind of wood best adapted to their weight and build and personal idiosynerasy, and a dozen other things that make the personal equation of such importance in the choice of a good pair.

The ski for hire in hotels or village shops are a battered and indifferent chattel at the best, and at the worst a very obvious invitation to various kinds of disaster. The hirer, moreover, pays in a single season probably the cost of two new and perfect pairs. Those who, with more foresight but no better judgment, take a little extra trouble and go to the big winter- sport emporiums in towns like Geneva, Lausanne, Neuchatel, etc., gain little advantage on the other hand. The writer, having passed that stage, knows it to his cost, for once up in an isolated mountain ‘ centre ’’ with bad or defective ski, it is too late for radical remedy, and the season is lost. The ski for hire in these emporiums are probably the least satisfactory article for hire in the whole world. In the room at the back of the shop devoted to that purpose an apprentice hurriedly hammers in the iron clamps that hold the boot firm by the toes. The hirer or purchaser pense que ca va bien because it feels secure, and goes off with an article, highly overpaid, that either turns out to be so loose that effective curving on a slope is impossible, or else so tight that the root of his big toe is sore and bruised at the first tumble and remains so till far into the following summer; while very probably the straps of the ‘ fixations’ have been so carelessly inserted that he cannot kneel (without which essential a fall at high speed may wrench his foot or break his ankle), or, worse still, the fastenings fly suddenly wide open while he is racing down his ‘ best slope ’ ” and he falls forwards with the sharp point of the ski aimed directly into his eyes or mouth or nose !

Nor is the slightly more experienced purchaser treated any better. He has no doubt read a book on ski-ing; he knows something of the ‘ patter,” while behind him he has the advan- tage (?) of last winter’s three weeks’ incessant, wearisome tum- bling—and he is lost! The consequence is that he buys a strip of slow wood with the grain running the wrong way, un-oiled most likely since it left the factory six months before, cheap straps (with peau de bouc doing duty for peau de porc) that freeze stiff and turn unmanageable at the touch of Zero, and fastenings that open at the slightest inducement—probably in mid-descent and leave his foot loose and wobbling upon an express train he cannot control or guide. This is what he carries proudly away with him, highly paid for. The falls that follow he ascribes modestly to his own lack of skill with the remark that ‘ no chap can expect to learn to ski in a single season, you know.’ ”

Others, cleverer as they think, write direct to the big factories at Christiania, sending boot measurements, and are treated much the same, for the dishonesty in the ski business is invited by the ignorance of the ordinary purchaser, and the discomfort and bother the average ski-runner is put to for want of a little trouble and a little guidance amount, in many cases, to the complete spoiling of his brief holiday’s enjoyment The pleasure of the sport, as well as its safety, depend so much upon a perfect fit—length, quality of wood, fine balance and the delicate adjustment of every detail—and can, moreover, be ensured for so small an expenditure of money and _ trouble, that many may like to share my discovery of that rare combina- tion—a ski-artist and an honest fellow, and learn how to avail themselves of his unique services. My own satisfaction has justified the step ; others may like to know. Patience and great skill, as well as love and passion, go to the making of fine ski, and [ can only compare in my mind the relief [ might have felt, after playing for years upon a five-pound factory fiddle, had | suddenly tumbled upon the cottage of some Guarnerius o1 Amati at Cremona making perfect things of beauty for the sheet love of making them.

A grave-faced man with iron grey hair and eyes that rarely smile (how slowly one learns to distrust that trick of facile smiling behind a counter !), he keeps an ironmongery shop in a little watch-making village of the Jura called Ste. Croix. It lies close to the French frontier, nineteen miles from Pontarlie1 to be exact, and is the terminus of a funicular railway that runs up from Yverdon (near Lausanne), the biggest fortified camp the Romans had in Switzerland, and before them a‘ busy centre’ ” ’ of the lake-dwellers. Here you may buy pots, cans and kettles, enamelled tin-ware, cheap skates, chains to carry your pocket knife or keys, and—perfect ski. If you hire a pair, you may be sure they have been well kept all the summer, oiled at proper intervals, and lying in an even temperature, so that December finds them true and fast and in sweet condition every way. ““ Monsieur Joseph ’” will tell you in a few words he economises language as he does his smiles—exactly what you are hiring. And you may believe him. Be you green novice or experienced runner and jumper, it makes no difference ; and if he feels the artist’s contempt for the tyro he conceals it utterly, entering into complete svmpatheti understanding of your needs and powers. Also, with infinite care, he will fit them on to your boots, and sell you the best wax for greasing them, even though his shelves are burdened with more expensive and less efficacious substitutes. He will never suggest to you to buy anythiny at all: the suggestion must come from you ; only, if you are worth talking to, he will talk the lore of ski-ing es a man talks who loves his subject and understands it. Stand- ing among those pots and pans beneath the low ceiling, I have made more than one thrilling mental ski expedition with “ ‘ Monsieur Joseph,’ ” and left the shop forgetting what I had come to purchase !

And if you wish to buy instead of hire it is the same, as you have only to send him your ski-boots, mention your height and weight, add the kind of country you intend to ski over and then leave yourself in his hands. At the close of the season, too, he will keep your things in good condition, for a france or two, till the following year, then send them to any address you mention If, however, you are on the spot, you may go in over- night and see him chalk the outline of your boot upon a piece of paper (nothing is left here to an apprentice !), and upon calling in the morning you will find a perfect fit awaits you. Your toes will not be gripped in a sort of thumb-screw, nor will the foot be so loose that the boot moves sideways without carrying the ski with it. soot and ski will move as one piece. Also, you will be able to kneel and pray with ease and comfort therefore fall, too, with safety at top speed as well. He will tell you in his grave, enthusiastic way the advantages of oak and ash and beautiful swift hickory, for he knows the distinctive values of the woods for speed and durability, as you may know the values of your stocks and shares, your stables or your motor-cars.

In July and August he makes mysterious journeys far afield, as the Cremona artists did, to choose these woods. Here is the great secret, and here come in the skill and love and patience. He has in him the true instinct for the grain, this “Monsieur Joseph ” of the pots and cans. Then, with his precious freight, he comes back to his mountain village and at the back of his modest shop begins the marvellous process by which he converts these lath-like strips of vegetable fibre into swift engines that shall carry human beings silently, swiftly, easily into the furthest recesses of the mountain valleys that he loves. The spirit of the mighty snow slopes is in his ski. To look at them, or run your hand along the velvet grain, is to conjure up visions of far, splendid journeys over virgin wastes into the heart of his frozen, sunny peaks.

Yet, Eugéne Joseph of Ste. Croix is unknown to fame. Only a few of us bless him and are glad. He has a little printed catalogue that travels no further than to the next village or the hotel, and above the shop one reads, ‘ Joseph et Cie,’ wondering what the ‘company’ may include, unless they be strange spirits of the lonely winter valleys. He knows no word of English, and will assuredly never see this article. But if you are ‘ experienced’ in ski you may easily prove the truth of what I say, and if ignorant and a novice, just tell him so frankly, and leave yourself without risk or danger in his competent hands.

A personal interview, of course, is always best, and from Geneva or Lausanne the journey is easy. Take a little imagina- tion with you, guess for a moment, if you can, the passion of the artist, and enter his magic shop one day when the snow is falling thick and silently and the tinware gleams beneath the ceiling in the flickering light of the two oil lamps. You will see him there, grave-faced, with keen brown eyes, watching you solemnly from behind the little counter, with a forest of tapering, slender ski-forms beyond him, where he fits you on in the back shop. Complete your business as briefly as your knowledge will permit you, and then, a little later, when you race across the sunlit slopes, wondering why you curve and steer so easily, and fall so much less than in previous years, admit gratefully that in these days of dishonesty and humbug you are glad to have found a man who will not impose upon your ignorance, nor take your money for an article which, as the idealists say, is ‘not what it appears to be.’ Your ski-ing, to use the telling Yankee phrase, will ‘ go up fifty per cent.’

Mrs. Gurney’s Poems

Poems by Dorothy Frances Gurney,
Reviewed by Algernon Blackwood

It is refreshing always to come across a genuine singer who is not afraid to sing simply of common things; and when that singer is possessed, as evidently Mrs. Gurney is, of a brave and wholesome view of life, the result may be more than merely refreshing: it may be inspiring. Hers is clearly the spontaneous lyrical utterance that sings because it must. There is often depth, but there is never obscurity in what she writes. It is as natural as the flow of a stream, rippling, pellucid, reflecting the homely yet precious flowers along the banks. You open this pretty book of rough-cut edges and attractive binding, and lo! you find yourself at once, and appropriately, in a garden, “God’s Garden”:

“The Lord God planted a garden
In the first white days of the world.”

And the charm and peace of that garden accompany you throughout the little volume, soothing the heart as with the rustle of summer leaves:

“The kiss of the sun for pardon,
The song of the birds for mirth,
One is nearer God’s Heart in a garden
Than anywhere else on earth.”

In these days of so much pretentious, tortured verse, it is delightful to listen to a voice like this, sincere and unaffected, giving melodious and felicitous expression to the common moods that are familiar to us all. Her vision runs like a thread of light through all the day’s events, touching each with beauty. Her gift, for all its modest humility, is no small one; you feel, moreover, the person of the singer behind all she writes: one who is brave enough to find some light and colour even when the darkness seems most hopeless:

“Sometimes when I was near you
The tears would fill my eyes;
To see and feel and hear you
Linked pain to ecstasies.

Now you are gone the stress is
That I must play my part,
And smile while no one guesses
The tears that fill my heart.”

Or in “Service”:

“Oh! Love, I am too small to stand
Beside you as an equal soul,
And meet your gaze and touch your hand
And own a common path and goal,

But this at least is in my power,
To mark your passing day by day,
And here and there to plant a flower,
Or move perhaps a stone away.”

Throughout the hundred pages of this book, including Songs for Music (that might well tempt a composer) and Sonnets, Triolets, Translations and Sacred Poems too, there runs the same simple, spontaneous utterance, whose natural flow hardly challenges criticism. It is genuine poetry of a high, sweet order, the sweeter, too, because it is unambitious; the higher, because the meaning is always clear as sunlight. It has, indeed, the sunny, sparkling quality of the woodland spring. Passion is touched, too, both earthly and divine; and though there is no attempt to thunder nor desire to amaze, there is a depth of suggestion in many of the poems that betray one who has felt or lived and suffered, you never lost sight of joy:

“I have determined what to do
At morning and at evening too;
I will find out a song to sing—
Though it be but a little thing,
’Twill serve to hearten up my days,
To tune my pipe and give God praise!”

One can well imagine Mrs. Gurney’s poems reaching thousands of readers, could they but be known, for it is a book to carry out with one into the woods, upon the hills, to read on a voyage or in the train, to dip into at night before sleep comes, or to open on a dull and weary day and catch its light and hope and beauty. It deserves to be known and loved:

“Down the woods at Godalming
All the ways are green;
Thrush and tit and blackbird sing
Down the woods at Godalming,
For where Love is wandering
And where Spring has been,
Down the woods at Godalming
All the ways are green.”

My Adventure with a Lion

I once served an apprenticeship on a new York newspaper, and some of my experiences as a reporter on the Evening Smile I shall never forget.

A reporter on an American newspaper is like a solider—he is expected to obey orders implicitly, even at the risk of his life. for this reason he is paid well, but a nervous reporter often goes out of the office with his heart in his mouth and an “assignment” that makes him think seriously of taking out another insurance policy on his life.

One gloomy winter’s morning I got down to the office at eight o’clock as usual, and had hardly reached my desk when the news editor—a kind man, who was always giving me opportunities to distinguish myself—came up and began to speak at once in a very mysterious voice.

“Got a dandy assignment for you this morning,” he said.

I looked up gratefully.

“I guess you carry a six-shooter, don’t you?” he asked. “You may need it this trip.”

“Oh!” I managed to gasp.

“A lion’s escaped,” he went on, in the quick, nervous American way of an American news editor.

“Has he really?” I asked wondering what was coming next.

“Jaffray’s Circus came to town last night, the lion somehow got out, and they’ve been chasing it all night. Got it cornered in a stable at last, somewhere in East 19th Street: but it attacked and mauled a valuable horse there, and I understand is still at bay. That’s all I know. Get up there as quick as you like, and get us a regular blazing story of it. You can run to a column,” he added over his shoulder, as he returned to his desk to distribute the other morning assignments, “and let’s have your copy down by messenger in time for the first edition.”

No one ever disputed with the news editor, or asked unnecessary questions, but many a reporter did a log of steady thinking when he got outside the office and safely on to the doorsteps.

I crammed my pocket full of paper from the big heap at the middle table, and swaggered out of the room with my nose in the air, as though hunting escaped lions was a little matter I attended to every day of my life, and that did not disturb me an atom.

An overhead train soon rattled me up to East 19th Street, but it was some time before I found the stable where the lion lion awaited me, for 19th Street runs from Broadway down to the East River, and is a mile or two in length, and bull of stables. Not far from the corner of Irving Place, however, I got on to the scent of my quarry, and I had hardly joined the group that had collected at the corner before a noise like distant thunder rose on the air, and every single person in the group turned tail and began to run for safety,

“What’s the trouble?” I asked of a man as he dashed past me.

“Lion in that stable!” he shouted, pointing to the big wooden doors across the road. “Escaped from the circus, across Savage as they make ’em. Killed a trotting-horse in there, and no one can get near it. They say it’s a man-eater, too!”

Another roar burst out as he spoke, and the crowd that had begun to collect again scattered in an instant in all directions. There was not doubt about that sound: it was a genuine lion’s roar, and it sounded deeper, I thought, that any roar I had ever heard before.

But, news was news, and in this case news was bread-and-butter. I must get the facts, and be quick about it, too, for my copy had to written out and in the office of the Evening Smile in time for the first edition. There was barely and hour in which to do the whole business.

I forced by way through the crowd now gathering again in the corner, and made my way across the road to where a group of men was standing not far from the stable doors. They moved about a bit when the roars came, but none of them ran, and I noticed that some of them had pistols in their hands, and some heavy crowbars, and other weapons. Evidently, I judged, they were men connected with the circus, and I joined the group and explained my mission.

“Well, that’s right enough,” said one of them. “You’ve got a grand newspaper story this time. Old Yellow Hair’s in there, sure pop! And, what’s more I don’t see how we’re ever going to get him out again.”

“The horse must be stiff by now,” said another. “He was mauled half to death an hour ago.”

“It’d be a shame to have to shoot him,” added a third, meaning the lion. “He’s the best animal in the whole circus; but he is awful savage.”

“That’s a fact,” chimed in a fourth. “There’s no flies on old Yellow Hair.”

Some one touch me on the arm and introduced himself as a report from the Evening Grin—a fellow-worker in distress. He said he didn’t like the job at all. He wanted us to go off and concoct a “fake story.” But I wouldn’t agree to this, and it fell through; for unless all the evening papers conspire to write the same story there’s always trouble at the office when the reporters get back.

Other reporters kept joining the group, and in twenty minutes from the time of my arrival on the scene there must have been a good dozen of us. Every paper in town was represented. It was a first-class news story, and the men who were paid by space were already working hard to improve its value by getting new details, such as the animal’s history and pedigree names of previous victims, human or otherwise, the description and family history of its favourite keeper, and every other imaginable detail under the sun.

“There’s an empty loft above the stable,” said one of the circus men, pointing to a smaller door on the storey above; and before ten minutes had passed some one arrived with a latter, and the string of unwilling reporters was soon seen climbing up the rungs and disappearing like rats into a hole through the door of the loft We drew logs for places, and I came fifth.

Before going up, however, I had got a messenger-boy stationed on the street below to catch my “copy” and hurry off with it to the Evening Smile as soon as I could compose the wonderful story and throw it down to him. The reporter on an evening paper in New York has to write his “stuff,” as we call it, in wonderful and terrible places, and under all sorts of conditions. The only rules he must bear in mind are: Get the news, and get it quick. Accuracy is a mere detail for later editions—or not at all.

The loft was dak and small, and we only just managed to squeeze in. It smelt pleasantly of hay. But there was another odour besides, that no one understood at first, and that was decidedly unpleasant. Overhead were thick rafters. I think every one of us noticed these before he noticed anything else, for the instant the roar of that lion sounded up through the boards under our feet the reporters scattered like chaff before the wind, and scuttled up into those rafters with a speed, and dust, and clatter that I have never seen equalled. It was like sparrows flying from the sudden onslaught of a cat.

Fat men, lean men. long men, short men—I never saw such a collection of news-gatherers: smart men from the big papers, shabby fellows from the gutter press, hats flying, papers fluttering; and in less than a second after the roar was hear there was not a solitary figure to be seen on the floor. Every single man had gone aloft.

We all came down again when the roar ceased, and with subsequent roars we got a little more accustomed to the shaking of the boards under our feet. But the first time at such close quarter, with only a shady wooden roof between us and “old Yellow Hair,” was no joke, and we all behaved naturally and without pose of affectation, and ran for safety, or rather climbed for it.

There was a trap-door in the floor through which, I suppose, the hay was passed down to the horses under normal circumstances. One by one we crawled on all-fours to this trap-door and peered through. The scene below I can see to this day. As soon as one’s eyes got a little accustomed to the gloom the outline of the stalls became first visible. Then a human figure seated on the top of a old refrigerator, with a pistol in one hand, pointed at a corner opposite, came into view. Then another man, seated astride the division between the stalls, could be seen. And last, but not least, I saw the dark mass on the floor in the far corner, where the dead horse lay mangled and the monster of a lion sprawled across his carcass, with great paws outstretched, and shining eyes.

From time to time the man on the ice-box fired his pistol, and every time he did this the lion roared, and the reporters flow and climbed aloft The trap-door was never occupied a single second after the roar began , and as the number of persons in the loft,increased, and the thin wooden floor began to bend and shake, a number of these adventurous news-gatherers remained aloft and never put foot to ground. Braver reporters threw their copy out of the door o the messenger-boys below and every time this feat was accomplished the crowd, safely watching on the corners opposite, cheered and clapped their hands. A steady stream of writing dropped from the loft-door and poured all the morning into the offices of the evening newspapers; while the morning-newspaper men sat quietly and looked on, knowing that they could write up their own account from the reports in the evening sheets.

The men in the stable below, occupying positions of great peril, were, of course, connected with the traveling circus. We shouted down question to them, but more than often got a pistol-shot instead of a voice by way of reply. Where all those bullets went to was a matter for anxious speculation amongst us, and the roaring of the lion combined with the reports of the six-shooter to keep us fairly dancing on that wooden floor as if we were practising and cake-walk.

A sound of cheering from the crown outside, swelling momentarily as the neighborhood awoke to the situation, brought us with a rush to the top of the ladder.

“It’s the strong man!” cried several voices. “The strong man of the circus. He’ll fix up the lion quick enough. Give him a chance!”

A huge man, who, rightly enough, proved to be the performing strong man of the circus, was seen making his way through the crowd, asking questions as he went. A pathway opened up for him as if by magic, and, carrying a might iron crowbar, he reached the foot of the ladder and began to climb up.

Thrilled by the sight of this monster with the determined-looking jaw, a dozen men rushed forward to hold the bottom of the ladder while he ascended; but when he was about half-way up, the lion was inconsiderate enough to give forth a most terrifying roar, with the immediate result that the men holding the ladder turned tail with one accord and fled. The ladder slipped a few inches, and the ascending Samson, crowbar and all, very nearly came to the ground with a crash. Fortunately, however, he just managed to grab the ledge of the door, and a dozen reporters seized him by the shoulders and ragged him, safe, but a trifle undignified, into the loft.

Talking very loud, and referring to the lion with a richness of epithets I have never heard equalled before of since, he crossed the floor and began to squeeze through the hole into the dangerous regional below. In a moment he was hanging with legs dangling, and a second later had dropped heavily into a pile of hay underneath hi. We lowered the crowbar to him, breathless with admiration; and then a strange thing happened. For, while the lion roared and the pistols banged, and we reporters tumbled over each other to get a glimpse of the attack of the lion on strong man, or vice versa, lo! a voice below shouted to close the trap, and the same instant a board from below shot across the opening and completely obliterated our view.

“We’ll have to fake that part of the fight,” said a reporter. “Must all agree on the same yarn.”

The sounds from below prevented the details being agreed upon just at that moment, for such a hoolabaloo as we then heard is simply indescribably—shooting, lion roaring, strong man shouting, crowbar clanging, and the sound of breaking wood and heavy bodies falling.

Outside the crowd heard it too, and remained absolutely silent. Most of them, indeed, had vanished! Every minute they expected to see the doors burst open and the enraged animal rush out with the strong man between his jaws, and their silence was accordingly explained by their absence.

At least half of the reporters were still among the rafters when the trap-door shot back in the floor, and a voice cried breathlessly that the strong man had caged the lion.

It was, indeed a thrilling moment. We clambered down the ladder and out into the street just in time to see the great doors open and a procession emerge that was worth all the travelling circuses in the world put together to see.

First came the trainer, with a pistol in either hand. Following him was the man with the small crowbar who had sat on the division between the stalls. Then came a great iron cage, which had been in the stable all the time, but with a little out of our line of vision in the dark corner, so that no one had observed it.

In this cage lay the huge exhausted lion, panting, on its side, with lather dripping from its great jaws.

And on the top of the cage, seated tailor-wise, dressed in a very loud check ulster, and wearing a bell-shaped opera-hat on the side of his head, was the proud figure of the victorious strong man. The expression on his face was worth paining, but it is wholly beyond me to describe it. Such exultation and glorious pride was worthy of the mightiest gladiator that ever fought in an arena.

His long curly hair, shining with oil, escaped in disorder from his marvellously shaped top hat, and the massive crowbar that brought him his hard-won victory stood upright on one end, grasped in his gigantic hand. He smiled round on the gathering crowd, and the procession moved proudly up the streets till within half an hour the people following and cheering must have numbered many thousands.

We reporters rushed off to our various offices, and the streets were soon afterwards lively with newspaper-boys shouting the news and waving sheets of terrible and alarming headlines about the “escaped lion and his fearful ravages,” and the “strong man who had captured it after a ghastly battle for his life.”

Next day the morning papers did not publish a solitary line about the great event; but in the advertising columns of every newspaper appeared the prospectus of the travelling circus just come to town, and in particular bold type the public were told to be sure and see Yellow Hair, the savage man-eating lion, that had escaped the day before and killed a valuable horse in a private stable where it had been chased by the terrified keepers; in, in the paragraph below, the details followed of the wonderful strong man, Samson, who had caught and caged the lion single-handed, armed only with a crowbar.

It was the best advertisement a circus ever had; and most of it was not paid for!

“Guess you knew it was all a fake?” queried the news editor next morning, as he gave me the usual assignment.

It was my first week on an American paper, and I stared at him, waiting for the rest.

“That lion hasn’t a tooth in its head. They dragged in a dead horse in the night. You wrote a very good story, though. Cleaned your pistol, yet?”

Nephelé

I

The change of atmosphere at Carsholt began probably soon after Sir Mark’s discovery of the Roman cinerary urn that very morning, but the discordant element in the castle household was not noticeable until Lady Shute betrayed her jealousy with the remark: “It’s that interfering girl again! Why in the world should she go digging about the grounds like this?” Her eyes were questioning; her lips became very thin. “Above all, what possessed her to do it now?”

Her husband, the famous archeologist, a stern-faced, elderly man, with an expression, evidently habitual, of great concentration yet aloofness, replied without looking up at first. The mouth was kindly, even tender, though it wore no smile at the moment. “Marjory is invaluable to me, you forget, dear; her memory, accuracy, insight—” he raised his eyes to his wife a moment. “Her knowledge of Roman things in particular is unusual. I often wish she had been with me in Crete and Egypt—”

He spoke soothingly, but the words were evidently the reverse of what his wife desired.

“Miss Trench,” came the sharp interruption, “was an excellent governess before you stole her from the children for your archaeology. I don’t grudge you her invaluable services,” with a tiny sneer of dis. belief. “You know that. It’s her taking up your time and attention at this particular moment that’s so annoying. The house full of guests, the Christmas Theatricals coming on tonight, the children helpless without her—for rehearsals, dresses, everything—and then she must needs go and dig up a buried antiquity in the Park, and carry you off, and—

“I—not she—dug it up, Emily,” he corrected her, with a patient smile that secretly enraged her. He knew of her jealousy of his passionate work and, indirectly, of all concerned with it. “As a matter of fact, it was Tiger’s burrowing that did it. A mass of earth, softened by the rain, buried the dog; I went to extricate him—and there—think of it, Emily!—there was the stonework, leading to a cavity”—his eyes shone with the smile of an enthusiastic boy—“a stone cist! I put my hand in. An urn, a lead casket, a Roman burial-place beyond question not far away—!”

“Mark, dear,” interrupted Lady Shute, her voice harsh yet pleading, as of one bearing a grievance nobly, “they had lain there several hundred years. It wouldn’t have hurt them to le a few days longer, would it?”

The conversation was interrupted by a servant, and Sir Mark, outwardly apologetic, but inwardly glowing with his discovery, watched his wife disappear upon some urgent errand, then slowly made his way down a corridor to his study.

“We must be patient, Marjory, for another twenty-four hours or so,” he mentioned, on finding her waiting for him to examine the treasures they had brought into the house only a few hours before. “ Once the performance is over, and the people gone, we can get to work again.” And he explained the situation in his blunt fashion, while the girl watched with eager, close attention his slightest word and gesture.

The urn had not yet been thoroughly examined. Sir Mark now brought a movable electric lamp from another table. It was a moment of real life for the two delighted experts. The enthusiastic pair could contain themselves no longer.

“Still quite untouched,” said the girl, in a tone a devotee might have used about some holy relic. “How lucky that you found it, instead of some clumsy workman with the point of a pick!” With her experienced, clever fingers she began to clear away the earth and stains of mould that still clung to the entrancing object. Her voice almost trembled with excitement as she added in a quick whisper: “Look, Sir Mark, look!” She pointed. “There’s an inscription onit! I do believe—yes, there’s an inscription! Look!”

He lowered his grey head beside her own, and thrust the light against the beautifully curved side of the precious urn.

“Nephelé,” she whispered, making out the Greek letters before he did, “Nephelé—”

“The Dancer”—he deciphered the Latin words that followed. “Nephelé the Dancer,” he repeated, easily deciphering the full inscription, now that she had shown the way. “Nephelé the Dancer,’ he repeated to himself.

He suddenly straightened up and stared hard at her. “Marjory!” he exclaimed, as though for the first time he realised her presence close beside him as a human being and not a secretary merely. “ Marjory!”

She stared back at him, a light in her eyes that was not a reflection from the electric lamp he now held askew. “Nephelé the Dancer,” she replied, looking straight into his face, and standing upright, while her breath came quickly. “That means no ordinary slave girl, but probably a celebrated dancer—someone exceptional -

“They took Greek names, yes—the best of them. It was the fashion, wasn’t it, in those days?” It seemed he asked her, as though he leant upon her special knowledge. The pair of them certainly were thrilled. Yet he was the great expert, she the assistant merely. He waited for her words, a curious look of expectancy in his eyes.

“A purebred Roman most likely!” she replied, after a moment’s pause. “The villa that stood here, remember, was the residence of the District Governor. We are reasonably sure of that. And he”—the sudden curious inflection in her voice he did not notice, nor the bolder expression that flamed an instant in her usually veiled eyes—“and he would certainly have the best—the very best obtainable—wouldn’t he:

“No ordinary slave girl, no mere dancer, as you say”—his words went fumbling rather—“would have been buried in this careful, honoured way—that’s certain,” he agreed, regarding her with the first touch of personal, admiring wonder he had ever shown. “Marjory!’ he exclaimed again, “it’s wonderful—very, very wonderful!”

There fell a momentary pause between them that iid pon by Sir Mark suddenly rubbing his hands hee - mex and excitement, as he summoned his thoughts back to the consideration of the present. He turned to fetch some other objects to the light, objects that only an expert could have recognised at all, so broken and fragmentary were they, for the small metal box containing them beside the urn had not been properly fastened, the damp had entered, and the result was little more than a discoloured dust.

“A tibia, evidently,” said Miss Trench, quietly ; “this was once a little sweet-toned tibia, a flute of sorts you remember.” She took up the crumbled atoms with loving care, as a mother might have lifted the tiny offspring of her own flesh and blood. “And this,” she went on, half to herself, “quite possibly—I wonder?—might well have been a lyra that twanged the accompaniment to the dancing.”

“My dear!” exclaimed Sir Mark with keen interest, and yet keener surprise. “You may be right. How clever of you i

“The merest guesswork,” replied the girl. “I may just as well be quite wrong, though somehow—I don’t think I am.” Her manner was intent, absorbed; he was as moved as she was. They handled and fingered the mysterious little things of dust and powdery wood, piecing them together again, as it were; making technical, expert comments ; yet both stirred to their hearts by the human emotions that seemed still clinging about these pathetic symbols of ancient joy and gaiety.

“The casket! Now for the little casket!” exclaimed the archeologist, his eyes lighting up afresh. He glanced at his companion. “We will open it together, you and I—eh?” He went over quickly to another shelf, the girl so close on his heels that unconsciously she laid her hand upon his arm, and her shining face almost brushed his cheek as they bent down together, then carried back to the light a small, dull object that had lain for twenty centuries beside the urn—the leaden casket. “The chisel, Marjory! The cold chisel—quick—where is it?” But already her swift fingers had passed it to him, and she wes pages his deft movements as he gently prised up the lead all round the top.

“It over tlapped, you see,” she remarked. “It was hammered down to the sides so as to form an airtight joint all round. You can see the scallop-shell moulding too.” “Admirable, admirable!” he murmured. “If only you had been with me years ago in Crete

It’s the Roman things I’m best at,” replied the girl simply.

The opening of the casket was accomplished without damage, revealing inside a second box, whose Hid threetened to crumble as they touched it. “Cedar wood.” said Miss Trench, “fastened with a leather thong.” The leather was in good preservation. They peered inside. Two flat, brownish objects lay at che Loctom of the little cedar box that still exhaled faint aroma of its original fragrance ; and as Sir Mark puzzled at first, lifted them out tenderly for examination, ti of the archeologist rose in him to a degree he had never iever experienced before, not even in his former Egyptian days of wonderful excavation and discovery. For a second his sight diame and became curiously blurred. “Footwear of soem kind,” he muttered, “slippers probably, or—” “Sandals,” came the low, clear voice in his ear, even before his own sentence was completed. “Her dancing sandals. Nephelé’s!”

Her employer turned and stared at her without a word for several seconds; then presently passed over to her, almost automatically, the precious remnants ofthe centuries. In spite of their great age, the sandals were still soft and pliable, the thongs that once bound them to the twinkling feet still serviceable.

“How neatly made and finished! How strong and flexible!’ the girl said in a low voice, holding them to her eyes. “The leather—some imported hide, from Africa probably—gazelle, most likely. And what small feet she had—Nephelé. How marvellously light they are—feel them, Sir Mark—they seem almost alive. And her jewellery—some of her jewellery, too!”

The girl held in her hand a square piece of crystal attached to a fine gold chain. For a moment she hung it upon her dress, the gold chain touching the skin of her neck, the crystal swinging to and fro against her bosom. Very becoming to her was this ornament of the Roman dancing-girl of two thousand years ago. “It was in the bottom of the cedar box,” she explained in a slow, quiet voice, looking down admiringly at it. “Nephelé wore it, of course, when she danced. I feel—somehow—she loved dancing to this Roman Governor. She gave of her very best. I’m sure she danced divinely, and perhaps”—her voice sank away, fading curiously in volume—“she loved him 7

Her companion, examining the crystal and gold chain in his fingers, was not listening, apparently, to her fanciful description. “Of no great value,’ he remarked, “of no particular value, but interesting all the same—extraordinarily interesting. Ome can see the whole thing,” he continued, half to himself, half to her, “the scene itself, the girl dancing, the great Roman looking on. One can hear the flutes, the twanging of the harps. It’s easily reconstructed, isn’t it? I wonder what she wore, and what he wore; what she felt, and what he felt? She must have been beautiful, yes, a beautiful dancer, of course, and, as you say, she may—”

The hoot and drone of arriving motors broke in upon his words ; the sound of a dressing-gong followed harshly ; a servant knocked and entered, bearing an urgent message “from her ladyship” that the dinner guests were already within the castle gates and both archeologist and his assistant were needed by the tyrant Present. Sir Mark broke off, listening with a vague impatience.

“Thus,” he said, turning with a smile to Miss Trench, “do the centuries repeat themselves—eh? Somewhat in this way, perhaps, Nephelé herself was summoned to prepare for her performance!”?

They exchanged an understanding glance which proved that one and the same sympathy taught both minds, and that both shared a similar vision of reconstruction. Behind the servant, meanwhile, came Hugo Trench, already dressed ; as Judge of the rival factions which were to perform after dinner, he was alert and interested like themselves, though in a different way.

“The audience is pouring in,” he announced laughingly, “and as I’m a famous dramatic critic as well as arbiter, I insist upon your being ready, Marjory. Every child in the castle’s calling for you, and Lady Shute” with a glance at his host-—“declares you re wanted in every room at once.” He turned to Sir Mark, as his sister hurried away. “You must let me into the secret too,” he observed, “as soon as the great performance is over. I’m not an expert, like my sister, but I’m eager to see and learn.”

And Sir Mark, drawing up his mind and manners to the surface of today again, explained briefly what the precious objects were. “Marjory,” he mentioned, “your sister—her instinct is quite extraordinary where Roman things are concerned, really wonderful. I hope—she won’t overtire herself tonight with all this acting, children business. She seemed to me a trifle—overwrought—just now. It’s the twofold excitement, of course.”

“Her own part is a small one,” replied his guest, “and she knows it backwards, she tells me, though I’ve no idea what it is myself. But she’s stage-manager, dresser, scene-shifter, and prompter in addition. How she loves and enjoys it all, though!”

“She’s most competent, most gifted,” added Sir Mark, hurrying off with an excuse to make himself ready, and leaving the critic in charge of the relics on the table.

Hugo Trench, left alone with the musty treasures on the table before him, examined them with the merely curious interest of a well-read, cultivated mind. The sandals in particular he looked at closely for some minutes, since dancing was his absorbing hobby, and it was his “Study of Classical Dancing in Relation to the Modern Ballet” that had won for him his present eminent position in the artistic world.

At the moment, however, a more human interest, and one nearer to his heart, divided his attention. He was thinking of his sister’s passionate adoration for a man thirty years her senior ; wondering whether Lady Shute had—and why her husband had not—divined it; hoping that no unhappiness need result from so strange a relationship, involving perhaps the loss of lucrative and pleasant work; asking himself chiefly, however, wherein lay the cause of the recent and sudden increase in the girl’semotion. It had become so intense that her face betrayed her. Its radiance lent her positively a new beauty. Holding the sandals in his hands, stroking, examining them, his real interest was not with Nephelé, their wearer, whose name even he did not know, but with his sister Marjory, who, it seemed to him, was becoming somewhat deeply entangled in an awkward set of circumstances.

II

The Hall had certainly come into its own tonight, with a quiet air of grandeur, a dignity, a spaciousness which had accumulated during the passing of the ages. Two immense log-fires roared upon capacious hearths that once had roasted oxen whole; and near the roof, lost among shadows, the faded battle flags of inter-tribal battles long ago hung motionless and grim. The fitful light gleamed on the stands of armour round the walls, and the big candles that alone lit the table might have been torches of resinous wood flaring upon boar’s head, mead in goblets, tankards of foaming ale, instead of upon champagne for the elders and lemonade for the children who formed a large proportion of “those present.”

These annual festivities were a serious affair at Carsholt. Before the climax of the Christmas Tree, there would take place the time-honoured rivalry between the Shutes of the Upper and the Lower Valley, each side giving its performance respectively amid keenest competition. Children, of course, were the actors, only two grownups, one of either sex, being permitted to take part ; and Lady Shute of Carsholt, zealous partisan of her own Lower Valley, was persuaded that Miss Trench, though her part was a small one, would this time lead her side to victory. The girl’s ten minutes on the stage affected the entire cast, lifting the little play to almost a professional standard. The Upper Valley, she was convinced, could boast no such talent among its grown-up helpers. The prize, an enormous box of chocolates, she did not care about: it was the honour of the Lower Valley she had at heart. There were cousins, too, she longed to see crestfallen after defeat, and the fact that her own children were performing was, of course, an added incentive to her keen desires. Both sides, with a hundred performances behind them, were at present equal. This was a decisive occasion. She certainly counted upon Miss Trench.

The Judge, moreover, was Miss Trench’s famous brother, whose unanimous appointment lent a further distinction to the occasion. Amid much excited laughter and applause he was duly installed after dinner in the stiff chair belonging to his exalted office, the few electric lights Sir Mark permitted were turned out, and in the soft glow of a hundred candles the troupe from the Upper Valley gave a finished performance of the piece they had been rehearsing for weeks, if not for months, beforehand.

Its success, judging by the spontaneous applause from both sides, was beyond question, and Hugo Trench, busily making the notes he was expected to make, watched by numerous anxious eyes, registered as well the mental comment that “if the Lower Valley 1s going to beat that,” the Shute tribe would indeed be a uncommonly gifted set of people. For the excellence of the performance had genuinely surprised him - * had expected to be mildly bored, but fie been an admiring and interested spectator. Sir Mark beside him in the background of the crowded room, clapped long and loudly, while Lady Shute flashed acutely enquiring glances in his direction, though forced to conceal her anxiety, and to applaud as well. Only Marjory, in a chair just behind her host, gave no outward sign of approbation, an omission her brother ascribed to her preoccupation with her own part in the following rival piece. The Banqueting Hall echoed with enthusiastic curtain-calls, and in the general buzz of voices and bustle of excited movement, neither he nor Sir Mark noticed exactly when she left her seat. Being behind them both, indeed, and this end of the hall being but dimly lit by the big fires, her actions were easily concealed. Shadows draped all three of them, for that matter, and several empty rows intervened between them and the main body of the audience. What happened to Marjory Trench at the moment, in any case, no one apparently observed.

Suddenly there came an abrupt lowering of voices everywhere, and the appearance of a figure on the stage announced the approaching excitement of the rival troupe. In the hush that instantly descended upon the audience, the boy of fifteen, stage-manager and impresario, stood with shy self-consciousness before the row of candles and made his solemn announcement. After telling the “ladies and gentlemen” that what they were about to see was “of an unparalleled nature,” and had “never been excelled on any stage,” he added: “And I’m very sorry, ladies and gentlemen, we hope you won’t mind much, but really we must turn all the lights out for it, please!”

The chorus of protest, half-shudderingly made, might have overwhelmed any less confident public man than this one who stuck manfully to his guns, and, availing himself of a pause the Judge obtained for him, carried his point at length successfully. “You see, ladies and gentlemen, the night has turned out fine, and there’s a lot of moonlight now, so the place won’t really be a bit too dark, and the bright light would spoil our piece. Thank you very much, ladies and gentlemen”—and he was gone again behind the curtain to the sound of clamorous applause. A moment later a footman appeared and extinguished the footlight candles, while another servant drew back the heavy curtains from the narrow, deep-set windows. The great body of the hall sank down into obscurity. At once a soft stream of moonlight stole upon the stage with a delightful and mysterious effect.

It was at this moment, perhaps, that the change of atmosphere, lurking hitherto unnoticed behind the general details of the day, stepped forward a little from the background and proclaimed itself a recognisable item in the programme. A soft, mysterious gloom pervaded the whole place, and a shudder of enjoyable creepiness ran among the children in an audible wave. The hall now doubled in size, the lofty ceiling reared away among deep shadows that blurred all outlines, and the sudden absence of glare from the stage candles made it difficult to welcome the swift change from brilliance to obscurity.

It is a fact, moreover, that into this pause when the voices ceased and talk died away, there fell abruptly an unexpected sound—the barking of dogs, muffled by distance, but answering one another with distinctness in the night outside. With the faint moonlight, now streaming across the stage from the uncurtained windows, entered also this curiously mournful sound. The Carsholt hounds were baying the wintry moon, no more, no less ; yet over that packed audience, obeying automatically the spell of semidarkness—as men and women must and ever will—stole the faint presage of the singular change. It almost seemed that the deep baying of the uneasy dogs, as by some preconcerted signal, had announced it.

“Admirable—quite admirable, really!” exclaimed the Judge beneath his breath, as though both baying and the moonlight were artificial tricks of the producer’s—and at the same time wondering whence came the shiver that chilled his skin uncomfortably and made him look across his shoulder. “A wonderful mise en scéne, isn’t it—so dramatic?” he whispered to his host, who stood upright at his side, one arm resting on the stiff-backed chair. “We’re going to see something exceptional, I do believe!”

Sir Mark, apparently, was too intent upon the empty stage to answer; his eyes stared fixedly, he showed no sign of having heard; and Trench turned next to take an impression of his sister, whose chair, placed behind and below his own, left her in shadow somewhat. But before sight picked her up, he forgot his first intention. The performance had _ begun. From that moment, in any case, Hugo Trench, as critic, as man, as Judge, forgot everything in the world except the thing he saw and heard upon the little improvised Carsholt stage.

“It’s really capital, first class!” ran his murmured exclamations, as the strings stole deliciously across the dark spaces of the immense old hall. “How in the world do they manage it? It’s too delightful!” For this sound of harp-strings plucked very far away seemed to enter the room from the Park beyond the narrow windows; the players, no doubt, were standing, muffled to the eyes, upon the moonlit lawns outside ; and the effect, as the soft twanging sent its small vibrations through the vaulted hall, was most cleverly conceived and carried out. As the strings grew louder, the sense of anticipation became yet more keen, and when low flutes took up a delicate melody to the harps’ accompaniment, the critic knew a moment of positive enchantment that he, for one, had never yet experienced upon any stage before.

“The youthful impresario was right,” he whispered to his host. “Where—who are the players? How do they manage that sound so well?’ He interrupted himself with a long-drawn “Sshhh’ ” to the audience, who still kept up their whispering too loudly. “Very, very clever!” he went on, “but I wish they’d shut that door or window—ugh!” and he shivered a second time, then gave a little start. Sir Mark, in an effort to see and hear better, had leaned over and lurched rather heavily against his chair, but the same second almost was rigid again.

“Harps! Flutes! It’s astonishing!” he was muttering, though to himself rather than to his guest. “A curtain has been drawn,” his whisper continued, “and someone looks forth on us!”

“Perfect, perfect!” repeated the Judge, as the tune quickened and the strings now sounded close behind the curtain. “It’s Marjory’s idea, no doubt,” he added proudly, too excited to notice the strangeness of the other’s language, and then came once more his vehement hiss, half-angrily this time, since the audience obstinately refused to maintain a proper silence. It was in the obedient hush following this time the authority of the Judge’s chair, that a figure all had been waiting for slipped round the edges of the immense plush curtains and began to dance.

Trench was aware of two things: that someone had omitted to close the open door through which the cold winter’s air came in with the musicians—and that he was’spell-bound. He forgot even to chide the stupid, chattering audience into silence. He watched with an amazement that increasingly mastered him. “I didn’t know—I simply never guessed she haditinher … !” he exclaimed aloud once to his neighbour, then fell to silence, enchanted, strangely moved, caught out of himself by something he had never seen before on any stage.

In his day he had known much solo interpretative dancing, the best the capitals of Europe had to offer, and his criticism had picked out its almost invariable weakness—the inability to tell the story clearly. Hence, then, the miracle that now arrested the experienced soul in him, with a startled wonder and wholehearted admiration that took his breath away. The story that the figure interpreted in her dancing was clear as print. It was, moreover, a deep, a subtle story. How many, he wondered maliciously, among that country audience grasped it too?

For all that, his mind seemed confused—and curiously confused—between two sets of values. He watched, he felt, he analysed; he did not wholly understand ; there was a missing item of immense importance somewhere that evaded him. That his sister possessed this touch of genius, that it explained her previous odd excitement, that her performance really must be seen in London, Paris, Milan—herein lay one set of values he could deal with easily enough. It was the other that puzzled him, even to laying a shadow upon his heart and mind.

In some way he could not define exactly, the exquisite performance he witnessed slipped just, though only just, beyond the edge of what was explicable and normal, This fact both puzzled and enthralled him, but it was the zyfe of dancing that added the element of distress. Never before had he seen its like; its genve was unfamiliar; wholly new to him indeed. There were moments when Hugo Trench, who signed weekly articles in a newspaper of authority, doubted hisowneyes. This lovely draped figure with the masses of dark, unfastened hair falling below her waist, a jewel gleaming on her breast, her bright feet flashing, twinkling; these gestures and movements that so superbly rendered the drama, now passionate, now pathetic, of a soul in the anguish of a great yet unuttered love—that this was his own sister Marjory, dancing upon the Carsholt stage for a Christmas gathering, seemed incredible. For the face, hidden by falling hair and flowing drapery, was never clearly visible in the uncertain moonlight, while the sound of the little feet, well-nigh inaudible too in their fairy lightness, was drowned even by the faintly plucked strings and soft-blown flutes. He was aware ofa deep lost meaning that went drifting, fluttering, hanging in the air before him, though of one he could not wholly seize. …

Yet the story itself certainly unravelled itself clearly enough before his enchanted eyes, and to a setting of deep emotion only great art and even greater conviction could have hoped to waken: the story of a faithty] love divinely felt, but of a love unspoken because unrecognised by the object of its worship; a love therefore, heroically concealed. By what power, by what art, was conveyed, further, the spiritual grandeur belonging to a passion that was unearthly in the sense that it was deathless, able to survive all possible barriers of space and time? It was this touch of majesty that arrested the critic’s soul with a wondering amazement, making him ask himself repeatedly: “How can she do this thing? Can this really be Marjory?”

So profound was the impression made upon him by the interest of the story, that he was less surprised than might otherwise have been the case when, to questions his brain asked occasionally, there rose from somewhere instantaneous and adequate replies. That an inner voice came to his assistance in this way, answering questions in his mind, satisfying moments of doubt he felt from time to time in the dance—he was as positive of this, as he was that these replies were absolutely true. Did he fail sometimes to follow ” the rapid, concentrated drama, did the meaning become momentarily obscure or wavering, then instantly rose this voice with a few true words that supplied the lost intention. Guided by these infallible, mysterious comments, he followed the brief story with a divination beyond his normal powers. For it was not the action merely that he sometimes failed to grasp, but rather the motives, desires, hopes and fears that lay deeply buried in the dancer’s beating heart ; it was these the mysteriously understanding voice made clear. …

Far from her native land, beneath skies alien yet not unfriendly, the girl danced this great love she could not, dared not, otherwise express. Her secret was her life ; she told it, offered it, in ecstasy. And not entirely in vain; her lavish giving of all she had to give was not wasted utterly ; for, though unrecognised by him who called it forth, her passionate beauty enriched the curtained eyes, sweetened the heart, of him who thought he delighted merely in her perfect art. His days stole some strange added happiness, whose origin he did not trouble himself to ask. …

“He never knew, he never recognised …” rose the inner voice in explanation. “He remained blind—almost to the end …”

The figure bent lower, as the dance now drew towards its close; the jewel flashed in the moon upon her heaving breast ; she kissed the alien soil he also trod ; the masses of dark hair fell forward abruptly in a final gesture of sacrificial pain and happiness, covering her young face and outline as with the night of death.

“.. until she died at his very feet, falling with his name upon her lips, her secret told in the eyes’ last look … so that too late … he knew?

A shock of surprise and fear fell suddenly on the listener’s heart. This voice was real. It was not an inner, an imagined voice, but one he knew and recognised. It was close beside him, against his very ear. It was his host’s. Also he now recognised the jewel, the sandals too; the very music was not what he had the right to hear. This, beyond all question, was his sister Marjory, but in what borrowed, stolen guise, he asked himself. The blood for a moment left his heart, then rushed back with uncomfortable pressure, as he turned to the man at his elbow who had all along been supplying him with these uncanny, whispered explanations.

An instant of blinding confusion, of values that refused to right themselves, swept over him. Added to this, came the rising whispers of the impatient audience but whether in praise of the performance just over—the figure had disappeared—or to welcome the young stage manager who now tried to stammer a few words, he could not say. This, too, remained a blurred picture in his troubled mind. Memory, indeed, hardly registered normally for some minutes, and it was partly the marble-white face of his host, and partly another thing as well, that undoubtedly caused his momentary loss of self-control. Sir Mark lurched heavily a second time against his chair. A sound immediately behind them both had rendered his balance insecure. Trench turned in the grip of a supreme amazement. The voice was that of his sister. It issued from the lips of Marjory, as she collapsed yet deeper into the chair she had never, he now realised, for one moment left.

“Help me! We must get her out—away from this,’ cried Sir Mark, yet quietly, his tone perfectly steady and controlled. It was exactly as though he knew and understood something his guest just failed to grasp—the very item, indeed, that had eluded him during the entire evening. It was he, the brother, however, who divined the fuller truth, and divined it perhaps alone—that the girl had been unconscious during the whole of the little act. Her cry was not uttered in the moment of fainting, but uttered out of an unconscious state she had lain in for the past half-hour and more.

Trench, though he made a great effort to recover his mental balance, was too surprised, too shocked still, to succeed entirely. He moved as in a dream. He remembers inaccurately what happened. He had just lived a dream ; that dream continued oddly. The interest of the audience in the second piece, now about to begin, enabled the two men to carry the gir] out of the room unnoticed ; the rows of empty seats, the darkness, and the proximity of a side door helped them further. Once in the lighted passage outside, he remembers hearing, with a vague dull anger in his heart, some words his host muttered about “the sandals, the very sandals … and the jewel. I saw them on her. I must—forgive me a moment—I’ll see if they’re still safe …’ He broke off,

almost letting drop the feet he carried, and was gone, deep in the preoccupation of his personal and passionate concern, shaking the little human interest from his obstinate mind, as though he shook off at the same time the recognition of something that he knew was true, yet dreaded.

Trench managed to carry his sister, unaided, to her room. Before he reached it, however, her eyes had opened and her normal state already begun to return. It was the rapidity of this return from unconsciousness, otgether with the first words she uttered, that confused her anxious brother even more, but at the same time convinced him finally that he had indeed witnessed something that had not been “seen on any stage before.”

“Nephelé …” she murmured, staring at him with moist eyes and quivering lips; “she told him … she gave her secret. But did he realise … understand?”

“N-no, no,” stammered her brother in reply. “He never understood, He never willl”

He was shaking. He spoke with curious conviction, wondering at himself. His words—her own as well—came evidently from the glamour of his dream, belonged still to the story that had so vehemently possessed him. He supported the girl’s arm as he led her to the sofa. Who was she? Who was Nephelé? Who was Marjory? Who, above all, was—this other? The questions rose flooding into his bewildered mind.

“He’s gone to make sure his precious relics are safe,’ came lamely, stupidly from his lips, as he watched his sister now putting her hair tidy before the mirror. She had refused to lie down. She declared she felt all right again. “You—you wore them, you know—Marjory,” he added, in spite of his desire not to say this thing.

She did not understand apparently, perhaps she did not catch his words. The normal expression rapidly reestablished itself on her face. She was calm.

“I fainted—didn’t I?” she was asking quietly. She looked about her, her grey eyes clear and soft, her voice quite steady. “Where are we? Oh, my room, of course. How idiotic of me! I’ve never fainted in my life before.”

For a moment there passed through her eyes a distant expression as of things remembered but not explained, then vanished again. “Where is—” she had an air of searching vaguely—“I mean—has the second piece begun?” She changed the sentence. “Quick, Hugo, I must hurry! Lady Shute will never forgive me if I’m late.” With a few deft touches to her dress, she ran with anxiety, yet laughingly, to the door. “You too, Hugo,” she exclaimed, as she opened it to the sound of excited voices coming up the passage. “You’re Judge, remember!”

Following the excited voices, in came the young stage manager and the breathless Lady Shute herself.

“Oh, I say, Miss Trench, wherever have you been?” cried the aggrieved boy.

“We have all been waiting for you,” put in the exasperated lady, a jealous anger gleaming behind the frigid manner. “You were nowhere to be found. It’s really unforgivable ie

The Judge took the blame upon himself as they hurried downstairs ; but the second piece, thus delayed, went poorly, for the players were upset, and Miss Trench, herself flustered and apologetic, gave an uninspired, even a mediocre performance of her own particular part. The Judge was forced to decide in favour of the Upper Valley, to the intense and venomous annoyance of his hostess. Sir Mark was not present. He arrived only just in time to make his customary little speech to the assembled rival tribes, and to hand the prize to the delighted winners.

”That stupid, selfish, irresponsible girl!” his wife relieved her mind at the first opportunity afterwards. “Her mind was elsewhere the whole time. And I’d counted on her so absolutely. Really she might—you, too, Mark—might have left your dead specimens in their grave just one day longer! I think,” she added acidly, ”it’s time that Miss Trench’s work was done by a man.”

He made no adequate reply, his wife’s grievance was admitted.

“The girl could hardly help fainting, I suppose,” he mumbled. “She’s been overdoing it lately a bit perhaps—”

“Men don’t faint,” his wife informed him. “You should have a man secretary. As for the girl—I’ve packed her off to bed, and I think it’s time you engaged another assistant, dear.”

Sir Mark sympathised, staring at his enraged wife somewhat blankly. There was justice and common sense in what she said. He was aware of this. Then, suddenly, he was aware of another thing—that an unalterable firmness lay in him with regard to something she had said, a fixed decision. He would never dismiss Miss Trench from his employment. …

It was long after midnight, the last guests gone, the children sound asleep, and the moon looking down softly upon Carsholt and the timeworn valley of the Shute.

In the mind of the archaeologist, as he stood gazing down upon his treasures before going to bed, stirred a faint, inexplicable warmth of awakened imagination, whose trail, as he followed it, led him out into the wintry sky beyond the old stone walls. Upon one open palm lay the little pair of shining sandals, upon the other gleamed the bright crystal jewel. He gazed down at them in silence, forgetting that his guest sat smoking by the fire, watching him.

“They say,” he murmured, “that history repeats itself. It certainly was passing strange and wonderful! Can I believe that—?”

”Genius,” remarked the critic, not wishing to play unwilling eavesdropper, ”is ever strange—particularly in its spasmodic appearances.” Sir Mark’s face was not visible, his back being to the glare of the electric light. “Never on any stage before,” he went on, slowly, “have I witnessed anything—”

His host turned sharply with a look on his face that stopped his companion dead. Tenderly laying down the treasures, he came over to the fire where his guest sat watching, listening, wondering.

“Let me tell you this,” he said thickly, “that what we witnessed tonight is something that our old world has not seen for close upon—two thousand years.”

He laid a hand gently upon the other’s shoulder. “I suggest, Trench,” he added in a lowered voice trembling with emotion, “that it remain our secret, since you and I were the only witnesses. Tomorrow I shall replace these relics in their ancient tomb. I shall bury them again.”

He did, then an amazing thing. Turning back to the table, he raised the sandals to his lips and kissed them with a reverent devotion. He kissed the shining jewel too.

“Let us, too, bury in our hearts,” he said softly, “those treasures which we appreciate—but may not use.

News v. Nourishment

The first thing I saw of him was the dome of his bald head and the strip of wandering black hair that strayed across it like a bit of seaweed left by an ebbing tide. The rest was hidden behind the opened newspaper which he devoured while waiting for his luncheon. He was a little man. I saw the tips of square boots with knobs on them projecting beneath the table, and later I noted that his nose was aquiline, and that he had large comfortable ears. He may have been something in a Forwarding Office; he was not spruce enough for banking or insurance circles. He read that evening edition as if the future of the race depended on it.

Then the girl, a lackadaisical, birdlike creature, brought his plate of “braised beef an’ carruts” swimming in thick brown gravy, and set it down with noisy clatter upon the marble table. He was so absorbed that the dishes came as a surprise; and as he looked up, startled, the paper descended softly upon the thick brown gravy. This was the first disaster; for when he lifted it to find his place the columns of print resembled a successful flypaper. He looked round at everybody, bewildered. For the moment, however, I was so interested in the wandering strip of seaweed on his skull that I hardly noticed his efforts to free the newspaper, himself, his neighbours, and the cruet-stand from the adhesive entanglement of this portion of his luncheon. There was a sound of scattering—then the girl had somehow managed it for him with her grimy napkin. But that remnant of a tide forgotten, as I came to regard it, fascinated me. It strayed, lonely as a cloud; it was so admirably fastened, down; the angle, curve, and general adjustment had been evidently chosen with so much care. Its “lie” upon that dome of silence had been calculated to a nicety, so that it should relieve with the best possible effect the open waste around it. It was like a mathematical problem. Only when his grave, dark eyes met mine did I realise that I was staring rudely.

But long before my own hurried luncheon came, the difficulties in which this stranger opposite was involved had fascinated me afresh The contents of the now mutilated evening paper absorbed him to the point of positive conflict. It may have been the racing news, police reports, or a breach of promise case; it may have been some special article and leader, or it may have been merely advertisements, perhaps; I cannot say. But his efforts to read and eat at the same time made me wonder with a growing excitement for the final issue of the battle. Had I not been alone, I would have laid a bet—with odds, I think, against “braised beef an’ carruts.”

He did it all so gravely and so earnestly, aware of the claims of both contestants, yet determined to be conscientious. Determined he most certainly was. A man doing anything with all his heart is always interesting to watch, but a man solemnly doing two things at once wins admiration and respect as well. My sympathies went out to him. I longed to give him hints. And the only time my attention wandered from this contest between news and nourishment was when I watched that strip of lonely seaweed rise and fall, vanish and reappear, with the movement of his head in eating. The way it dived to meet the fork, then rose again to greet the paper, was like the motion of a swimmer among waves.

He arranged his sight so cleverly, dividing it in some swift, extraordinary manner, yet without squinting, between the occupants of the arena. An eye and a half on each alternately seemed to be the plan, the extra half left over being free to bring immediate first-aid when needed; but his mind, I felt, was really with the paper all along. The nourishment was pleasure, the news was duty. There was heroism in this little man.

He would heap his fork with a marvelously balanced pyramid of beef and carrots and bread, smear it over with thick gravy, top it with a dash of salt—all with one hand, this!—then leave it hovering above the plate while he looked back keenly at the paper, searching to find his place. For between mouthfuls he always lost his place. It distressed me till he found it again, my interest centred on the piled-up fork. But what distressed me even more was that every time he found it and shot an eye back again to the loaded implement—that pyramid tumbled! Three times out of four, at least, it dropped its burden in this way; and the look of weariness, surprise, and disappointment on his face at each collapse was almost more than I could bear—in silence. He looked at that fork as some men look at a dog—with mortified astonishment. “I’m surprised at you,” his expression said, “after all those years, too!” I longed to ask, “Why did you add that carrot to the top? You might have known by this time—!” But his own expression said quite plainly, “I built you up so very carefully—all with one hand, too. You really might have stayed!”

My own tension became too keen then for mere amusement. I found myself taking sides alternately with the beef and paper. I was conscious of a desire to steady the fork for him while he read, and then to guide it straight into his mouth. For it next became most painfully obvious that he rarely found the opening—at the first attempt. With that overloaded, overbalanced fork, a dripping carrot perched on the apex of the pile, he jabbed successively his lower lip, his cheek, his chin, and once at least the tip of his nose, before the proper terminus was reached and delivery accomplished. Small beauty-spots of brown remained dotted here and there to mark the inaccuracy of his aim and the firmness of his persistence.

For he was so patient. Both jobs he did so thoroughly. I began to wonder if he did two things at once at other times as well: whether, for instance, he buttoned his collar with one hand while with the other he led that strip of seaweed into safety for the day’s adventure. Surely, it seemed, he must excel at those parlour tricks which involve patting the breast with one hand and rubbing it up and down with the other simultaneously. Something of the sort he surely practised. Although the way, with a piece of bread speared on his fork, he groped all round the table for the gravy that was cooling on his plate, made me question his absolute skill sometimes.

He was too absorbed to notice things around him. The stout, bespectacled woman, for instance, who sat beside him on the leather couch, might not have existed at all. The way she looked him up and down, hinting for more room, was utterly lost upon him. So was the way she moved her glass of steaming milk and her undersized bananas to and fro to dodge the paper he constantly flapped beneath her very nose. He took far more than his proper share of space, and she clearly resented it most bitterly, yet was afraid to speak. The movements of her glass and fruit were like a game of chess; he played the stronger gambit and forced her moves. She sulked—and lost.

The girl came up and whisked his unfinished plate away, asking him with a sideways bend of the head, birdlike rather, if he wished to order anything else, and his face shot up above the edge of the paper as though she had interrupted him in the midst of a serious business transaction.

“Didn’t I order something, miss?” he was heard to inquire resentfully, one eye glued still to the sheet.

“Nothing not yet,” came the disinterested reply.

“Bring me sultana pudding hot—no, cold, I mean—with sauce, please,” he said, as if remembering some quotation learnt by heart—and down he plunged once more beneath that sea of print.

But with the arrival of the cold sultana pudding came the crisis of the battle. For the pudding was slippery. It stood on end amid its paste-like sauce, impatient of amateur attack, inviting more skill than evidently he possessed. He caught my warning eye once or twice upon him, but disregarded it. These wholehearted people never take advice. Smothering the toppling form with sugar, he seized a fork and aimed; but, before striking, buried his eyes again in the paper. The shot flew wild. The pyramid of dough went slithering round the plate as though alive, scattering sauce upon the marble table. A second shot, delivered with impatience, took off the top and side. He speared the broken piece—still without looking up to direct it properly—gathered a little sauce and sugar on the way; then, flushed with success, the face turned sideways towards the paper, rushed recklessly for his mouth—and bit an empty fork. The load had slipped aside en route; or, rather, the paper, holding the best position in the field, had taken it prisoner. For it fell with a soft and sticky thud into the column nearest to his waistcoat. This time he spooned it up, and for a little time after that he had success. The paper and the pudding ran neck and neck along the homestretch. He read with absorbing interest; he ate without waste of attention. I watched him with amazement. This performance of a divided personality must be given somewhere every day at the luncheon hour. The mood of the afternoon hung probably upon its accomplishment without disaster. The pudding had dwindled to its last titbit without attempting further ausflüge, and his eyes had just begun to feast upon a freshly turned page of the newspaper, when, crash, bang—there came complete discomfiture.

Drunk with success, he made a violent misdirected shot. He had waited long for that titbit, had nursed it carefully, keeping a little pool of sauce and sugar especially for it, when this careless aim sent it flying off the plate several inches into the middle of the table. The woman with the milk and the banana gave a little scream—of indignation. He turned abruptly, noticing her presence for the first time. He realised that he had edged her almost off the couch. He also realised, with the other eye, that the bit of pudding lay beyond redemption or recapture. Several people were watching him. He could not possibly, without total loss of dignity, restore it to an edible condition. He shunted down the seat with the sideways movement of a penguin, quietly replaced the errant morsel on his plate, called for his bill, then waited resignedly with a sigh, a defeated man.

Our eyes met in that moment full and square across the room. “I told you so,” mine said; “you were too reckless with it.” But in his own there shone a look of misery and regret I shall not easily forget. For a single instant his face vanished behind the crumpled but victorious paper, to emerge, scarlet, a moment later with the strip of seaweed drawn out of its normal bed into an unaccustomed route towards one tilted eyebrow. In his distress the man had passed a hand absentmindedly across his forehead. The woman, putting on her spectacles, eyed with relief his preparations for departure. He went. But he took the paper with him.

And through the window I caught my final glimpse of him as he climbed outside a passing omnibus. He was small and rotund. His eyes shone in a flushed and disappointed face. His coattails spread sideways in the wind. Like an irate and very swollen sparrow he looked, defeated in some wretched gutter combat, yet eager for more, and certain to return to the arena as long as life should last—about the luncheon hour.

Old Clothes

I

Imaginative children with their odd questionings of life and their delicate nervous systems must be often a source of greater anxiety than delight to their parents, and Aileen, the child of my widowed cousin, impressed me from the beginning as being a strangely vivid specimen of her class. Moreover, the way she took to me from the first placed quasi-avuncular responsibilities upon my shoulders (in her mother’s eyes), that I had no right, even as I had no inclination, to shirk. Indeed, I loved the queer, wayward, mysteri- ous little being. Only it was not always easy to advise; and her somewhat marked peculiarities certainly called for advice of a skilled and special order. It was not merely that her make-believe was unusually sincere and haunting, and that she would talk by the hour with invisible playmates (touching them, putting up her lips to be kissed, opening doors for them to pass in and out, and setting chairs, foot- stools and even flowers for them), for many children in my experience have done as much and done it with a vast sincerity; but that she also accepted what they told her with so steady a degree of conviction that their words influenced her life and, accordingly, her health. They told her stories, apparently, in which she herself played a central part, stories, moreover, that were neither comforting nor wise. She would sit in a corner of the room, as both her mother and myself can vouch, face to face with some make–believe Occu- pant of the chair so carefully arranged; the footstool had been placed with precision, and sometimes she would move it a little this way or that; the table whereon rested the invisible elbows was beside her with a jar of flowers that changed according to the particular visitor. And there she would wait motion- less, perhaps an hour at a time, staring up into the viewless features of the person who was talking with her—who was telling her a story in which she played an exceedingly poignant part. Her face altered with the run of emotions, her eyes grew large and moist, and sometimes frightened; rarely she laughed, and rarely asked a whispered question, but more often sat there, tense and eager, uncannily absorbed in the inaudible tale falling from invisible lips—the tale of her own adventures. But it was the terror inspired by these singular recitals that affected her delicate health as early as the age of eight, and when, owing to her mother’s well- meant but ill–advised ridicule, she indulged them with more secrecy, the effect upon her nerves and character became so acute that I was summoned down upon a special advisory visit I scarcely appreci- ated. “Now, George, what do you think I had better do? Dr. Hale insists upon more exercise and more com- panionship, sea air and all the rest of it, but none of these things seem to do any good.” “Have you taken her into your confidence, or rather has she taken you into hers?” I ventured mildly. The question seemed to give offence a little. “Of course,” was the emphatic answer. “The child has no secrets from her mother. She is perfectly devoted to me.” “But you have tried to laugh her out of it, haven’t you now?” “Yes. But with such success that she holds these conversations far less than she used to—” “Or more secretly?” was my comment, that was met with a superior shrug of the shoulders. Then, after a further pause, in which my cousins distress and my own affectionate interest in the whim- sical imagination of my little niece combined to move me, I tried again—“Make-believe,” I observed, “is always a bit puzzling to us older folk, because, though we indulge in it all our lives. We no longer believe in it; whereas children like Aileen—” She interrupted me quickly— “You know what I feel anxious about,” she said, lowering her voice. “I think there may be cause for ser- ious alarm.” Then she added frankly, looking up with grave eyes into my face, “George, I want your help— your best help, please. You’ve always been a true friend.” I gave it to her in calculated words. “Theresa,” I said with grave emphasis, “there is no trace of insanity on either side of the family, and my own opinion is that Aileen is perfectly well-balanced in spite of this too highly developed imagination. But, above all things, you must not drive it inwards by making fun of it. Lead it out. Educate it. Guide it by intelligent sympathy. Get her to tell you all about it, and so on. I think Aileen wants careful observing, per- haps—but nothing more.” For some minutes she watched my face in silence, her eyes intent, her features slightly twitching. I knew at once from her manner what she was driving at. She approached the subject with awkwardness and cir- cumlocution, for it was something she dreaded, not feeling sure whether it was of heaven or of hell. “You are very wonderful, George,” she said at length, “and you have theories about almost every thing—” “Speculations,” I admitted. “And your hypnotic power is helpful, you know. Now—if—if you thought it safe, and that Providence would not be offended—” “Theresa,” I stopped her firmly before she had committed herself to the point where she would feel hurt by a refusal, “let me say at once that I do not con- sider a child a fit subject for hypnotic experiment, and I feel quite sure that an intelligent person like yourself will agree with me that it’s unpermissible.” “I was only thinking of a little ‘suggestion,’” she murmured. “Which would come far better from the mother.” “If the mother had not already lost her power by using ridicule,” she confessed meekly. “Yes, you never should have laughed. Why did you, I wonder?” An expression came into her eyes that I knew to be invariably with hysterical temperaments the precursor of tears. She looked round to make sure no one was listening. “George,” she whispered, and into the dusk of that September evening passed some shadow between us that left behind an atmosphere of sudden and inex- plicable chill, “George, I wish—I wish it was quite clear to me that it really is all make-believe, I mean—” “What do you mean?” I said, with a severity that was assumed to hide my own uneasiness. But the tears came the same instant in a flood that made any intel- ligent explanation out of the question. The terror of the mother for her own blood burst forth. “I’m frightened—horribly frightened,” she said between the sobs. “I’ll go up and see the child myself,” I said comfort- ingly at length when the storm had subsided. “I’ll run up to the nursery. You mustn’t be alarmed. Aileen’s all right. I think I can help you in the matter a good deal.”

II

In the nursery as usual Aileen was alone. I found her sitting by the open window, an empty chair oppos- ite to her. She was staring at it—into it, but it is not easy to describe the certainty she managed to convey that there was some one sitting in that chair, talking with her. It was her manner that did it. She rose quickly, with a start as I came in, and made a half ges- ture in the direction of the empty chair as though to shake hands, then corrected her self quickly, and gave a friendly little nod of farewell or dismissal—then turned towards me. Incredible as it must sound, that chair looked at once slightly other wise. It was empty. “Aileen, what in the world are you up to?” “You know, uncle,” she replied, without hesitation. “Oh, rather! I know!” I said, trying to get into her mood so as later to get her out of it, “because I do the same thing with the people in my own stories. I talk to them too—” She came up to my side, as though it were a matter of life and death. “But do they answer?” I realized the overwhelming sincerity, even the seriousness, of the question to her mind. The shadow evoked down-stairs by my cousin had followed me up here. It touched me on the shoulder. “Unless they answer,” I told her, “they are not really alive, and the story hangs fire when people read it.” She watched me very closely a moment as we leaned out of the open window where the rich per- fume of the Portuguese laurels came up from the lawns below. The proximity of the child brought a dis- tinct atmosphere of its own, an atmosphere charged with suggestions, almost with faint pictures, as of things I had once known. I had often felt this before, and did not altogether welcome it, for the pictures seemed framed in some emotional setting that in vari- ably escaped my analysis. I understood in a vague way what it was about the child that made her mother afraid. There flashed across me a fugitive sensation, utterly elusive yet painfully real, that she knew moments of suffering by rights she ought not to have known. Bizarre and unreasonable as the conception was, it was convincing. And it touched a profound sympathy in me. Aileen undoubtedly was aware of this sympathy. “It’s Philip that talks to me most of the time,” she volunteered, “and he’s always, always explaining—but never quite finishes.” “Explaining what, dear little Child of the Moon?” I urged gently, giving her a name she used to love when she was smaller. “Why he couldn’t come in time to save me, of course,” she said. “You see, they cut off both his hands.” I shall never forget the sensation these words of a child’s mental adventure caused me, nor the kind of bitter reality they forced into me that they were true, and not merely a detail of some attempted rescue of a “Princess in a Tower.” A vivid rush of thought seemed to focus my consciousness upon my own two wrists, as though I felt the pain of the operation she mentioned, and with a swift instinct that slipped into action before I could control it, I had hidden both hands from her sight in my coat pockets. “And what else does ‘Philip’ tell you?” I asked gently. Her face flushed. Tears came into her eyes, then fled away again lest they should fall from their softly- coloured nests. “That he loved me so awfully,” she replied; “and that he loved me to the very end, and that all his life after I was gone, and after they cut his hands off, he did nothing but pray for me—from the end of the world where he went to hide—” I shook myself free with an effort from the envelop- ing atmosphere of tragedy, realizing that her imagina- tion must be driven along brighter channels and that my duty must precede my interest. “But you must get Philip to tell you all his funny and jolly adventures, too,” I said, “the ones he had, you know, when his hands grew again—” The expression that came into her face literally froze my blood. “That’s only making-up stories,” she said icily. “They never did grow again. There were no happy or funny adventures.” I cast about in my mind for an inspiration how to help her mind into more wholesome ways of inven- tion. I realized more than ever before the profundity of my affection for this strange, fatherless child, and how I would give my whole soul if I could help her and teach her joy. It was a real love that swept me, rooted in things deeper than I realized. But, before the right word was given me to speak, I felt her nestle up against my side, and heard her utter the very phrase that for some time I had been dread- ing in the secret places of my soul she would utter. The sentence seemed to shake me within. I knew a hur- ried, passing moment of unspeakable pain that is utterly beyond me to reason about. “You know,” was what she said, “because it’s you who are Philip!” And the way she said it—so quietly, the words touched somehow with a gentle though compassion ate scorn, yet made golden by a burning love that filled her little person to the brim—robbed me momentarily of all power of speech. I could only bend down and put my arm about her and kiss her head that came up barely to the level of my chin. I swear I loved that child as I never loved any other human being. “Then Philip is going to teach you all sorts of jolly adventures with his new hands,” I remember saying, with blundering good intention, “because he’s no longer sad, and is full of fun, and loves you twice as much as ever!” And I caught her up and carried her down the long stairs of the house out into the garden, where we joined the dogs and romped together until the face of the motherly Kempster at an upper window shouted down something stupid about bed-time, supper, or the rest of it, and Aileen, flushed yet with brighter eyes, ran into the house and, turning at the door, showed me her odd little face wreathed in smiles and laughter. For a long time I paced to and fro with a cigar between the box hedges of the old-time garden, thinking of the child and her queer imaginings, and of the profoundly moving and disquieting sensations she stirred in me at the same time. Her face flitted by my side through the shadows. She was not pretty, prop- erly speaking, but her appearance possessed an ori- ginal charm that appealed to me strongly. Her head was big and in some way old-fashioned; her eyes, dark but not large, were placed close together, and she had a wide mouth that was certainly not beautiful. But the look of distressed and yearning passion that some- times swept over these features, not otherwise prepos- sessing, changed her look into sudden beauty, a beauty of the soul, a soul that knew suffering and was acquainted with grief. This, at least, is the way my own mind saw the child, and therefore the only way I can hope to make others see her. Were I a painter I might put her upon canvas in some imaginary portrait and call it, perhaps, “Reincarnation”—for I have never seen any thing in child-life that impressed me so vividly with that odd idea of an old soul come back to the world in a new young body—a new Suit of Clothes. But when I talked with my cousin after dinner, and consoled her with the assurance that Aileen was gifted with an unusually vivid imagination which time and ourselves must train to some more practical end— while I said all this, and more besides, two sentences the child had made use of kept ringing in my head. One—when she told me with merciless perception that I was only “making-up” stories; and the other, when she had informed me with that quiet rush of certainty and conviction that “Philip” was—myself.

III

A big-game expedition of some months put an end temporarily to my avuncular responsibilities; at least so far as action was concerned, for there were certain memories that held curiously vivid among all the absorbing turmoil of our camp life. Often, lying awake in my tent at night, or even following the tracks of our prey through the jungle, these pictures would jump out upon me and claim attention. Aileen’s little face of suffering would come between me and the sight of my rifle; or her assurance that I was the “Philip” of her imagination would attack me with an accent of reality that seemed queer enough until I analyzed it away. And more than once I found myself thinking of her dark and serious countenance when she told how “Philip” had loved her to the end, and would have saved her if they had not cut off his hands. My own Imagination, it seemed, was weaving the details of her child’ s invention into a story, for I never could think of this latter detail without positively experiencing a sensation of smarting pain in my wrists...! When I returned to England in the spring they had moved, I found, into a house by the sea, a tumbled-down old rookery of a building my cousin s father had rarely occupied during his lifetime, nor she been able to let since it had passed into her posses- sion. An urgent letter summoned me thither, and I travelled down the very day after my arrival to the bleak Norfolk coast with a sense of foreboding in my heart that increased almost to a presentiment when the cab entered the long drive and I recognized the grey and gloomy walls of the old mansion. The sea air swept the gardens with its salt wash, and the moan of the surf was audible even up to the windows. “I wonder what possessed her to come here?” was the first thought in my mind. “Surely the last place in the world to bring a morbid or too-sensitive child to!” My further dread that something had happened to the little child I loved so tenderly was partly dispelled, however, when my cousin met me at the door with open arms and smiling face, though the welcome I soon found, was chiefly due to the relief she gained from my presence. Something had happened to little Aileen, though not the final disaster that I dreaded. She had suffered from nervous attacks of so serious a character during my absence that the doctor had insisted upon sea air, and my cousin, not with the best judgment, had seized upon the idea of making the old house serve the purpose. She had made a wing habit- able for a few weeks; she hoped the entire change of scene would fill the little girl’s mind with new and happier ideas. Instead—the result had been exactly the reverse. The child had wept copiously and hyster- ically the moment she set eyes on the old walls and smelt the odour of the sea. But before we had been talking ten minutes there was a cry and a sound of rushing footsteps, and a scampering figure, with dark, flying hair, had dived headlong into my arms, and Aileen was sobbing— “Oh, you’ve come, you’ve come at last! I am so awfully glad. I thought it would be the same as before, and you’d get caught.” She ran from me next and kissed her mother, laughing with pleasure through her tears, and was gone from the room as quickly as she had come. I caught my cousin’s glance of frightened amazement. “Now isn’t that odd?” she exclaimed in a hushed voice. “Isn’t that odd? Those are the tears of happi- ness,—the first time I’ve seen her smile since we came here last week.” But it rather nettled me, I think. “Why odd?” I asked. “Aileen loves me, it’s delightful to—” “Not that, not that!” she said quickly. “It’s odd, I meant, she should have found you out so soon. She didn’t even know you were back in England, and I’d sent her off to play on the sands with Kempster and the dogs so as to be sure of an opportunity of telling you everything before you saw her.” “You see, she knew perfectly well you were here— the instant you came.” “But there’s nothing in that,” I asserted. “Children know things just as animals do. She scented her favourite uncle from the shore like a dog!” And I laughed in her face. That laugh perhaps was a mistake on my part. Its well-meant cheerfulness was possibly overdone. Even to myself it did not ring quite true “I do believe you are in league with her—against me,” was the remark that greeted it, accompanied by an increase of that expression of fear in the eyes I had divined the moment we met upon the doorstep. Find- ing nothing genuine to say in reply, I kissed the top of her head. In due course, after the tea things had been removed, I learned the exact state of affairs, and even making due allowance for my cousin’s excited exagger- ations, there were things that seemed to me inexplic- able enough on any ground of normal explanation. Slight as the details may seem when set down seri- atim, their cumulative effect upon my own mind touched an impressive and disagreeable climax that I did my best to conceal from outward betrayal. As I sat in the great shadowy room, listening to my cousin’s jerky description of “childish” things, it was borne in upon me that they might well have the profoundest possible significance. I watched her eager, frightened face, lit only by the flickering flames the sharp spring evening made necessary, and thought of the subject of our conversation flitting about the dreary halls and corridors of the huge old building, a little figure of tragedy, laughing, crying and dreaming in a world entirely her own—and there stirred in me an unwel- come recognition of those mutinous and dishevelled forces that lie but thinly screened behind the com- mon-place details of life and that now seemed ready to burst forth and play their mysterious rôle before our very eyes. “Tell me exactly what has happened,” I urged, with decision but sympathy. “There’s so little, when it’s put into words, George; but—well, the thing that first upset me was that she— knew the whole place, though she’s never been here before. She knew every passage and staircase, many of them that I did not know myself; she showed us an underground passage to the sea, that father himself didn’t know; and she actually drew a scrawl of the house as it used to be three hundred years ago when the other wing was standing where the copper beeches grow now. It’s accurate, too.” It seemed impossible to explain to a person of my cousin’s temperament the theories of pre-natal memory and the like, or the possibility of her own knowledge being communicated telepathically to the brain of her own daughter. I said therefore very little, but listened with an uneasiness that grew horribly. “She found her way about the gardens instantly, as if she had played in them all her life; and she keeps drawing figures of people—men and women—in old costumes, the sort of thing our ancestors wore, you know—” “Well, well, well!” I interrupted impatiently; “what can be more natural? She is old enough to have seen pictures she can remember enough to copy—?” “Of course,” she resumed calmly, but with a calmness due to the terror that ate her very soul and swallowed up all minor emotions; “of course, but one of the faces she gets is—a portrait.” She rose suddenly and came closer to me across the big stone hearth, lowering her voice to a whisper, “George,” she whispered, “it’s the very image of that awful—de Lorne!” The announcement, I admit, gave me a thrill, for that particular ancestor on my father’s side had largely influenced my boyhood imagination by the accounts of his cruelty wickedness in days gone by. But I think now the shiver that ran down my back was due to the thought of my little Aileen practising her memory and pencil upon so vile an object. That, and my cousin’s pale visage of alarm, combined to shake me. I said, however, what seemed wise and reasonable at the moment. “You’ll be claiming next, Theresa, that the house is haunted,” I suggested. She shrugged her shoulders with an indifference that was very eloquent of the strength of this other more substantial terror. “That would be so easy to deal with,” she said, without even looking up. “A ghost stays in one place. Aileen could hardly take it about with her.” I think we both enjoyed the pause that followed. It gave me time to collect my forces for what I knew was coming. It gave her time to get her further facts into some pretence of coherence. “I told you about the belt?” she asked at length, weakly, and as though unutterable things she longed to dis own forced the question to her unwilling lips. The sentence shot into me like the thrust of a naked sword.... I shook my head. “Well, even a year or two ago she had that strange dislike of wearing a belt with her frocks. ‘We thought it was a whim, and did not humour her. Belts are necessary, you know, George,” she tried to smile feebly. “But now it has come to such a point that I’ve had to give in.” “She dislikes a belt round her waist, you mean?” I asked, fighting a sudden inexplicable spasm in my he art. “It makes her scream. The moment anything encloses her waist she sets up such a hubbub, and struggles so, and hides away, and I’ve been obliged to yield.” “But really, Theresa—!” “She declares it fastens her in, and she will never get free again, and all kinds of other things. Oh, her fear is dreadful, poor child. Her face gets that sort of awful grey, don’t you know? Even Kempster, who if anything is too firm, had to give in.” “And what else, pray?” I disliked hearing these details intensely. It made me ache with a kind of anger that I could not at once relieve the child’s pain. “The way she spoke to me after Dr. Hale had left— you know how awfully kind and gentle he is, and how Aileen likes him and even plays with him and sits on his knee? Well, he was talking about her diet, regulat- ing it and so forth, teasing her that she mustn’t eat this and that, and the rest of it, when she turned that horrid grey again and jumped oft his knee with her scream—that thin wailing scream she has that goes through me like a knife, George—and flew to the nursery and locked herself in with—what do you think?—with all the bread, apples, cold meat and other eatables she could find!” “Eatables!” I exclaimed, aware of another spasm of vivid pain. “When I coaxed her out, hours later, she was trembling like a leaf and fell into my arms utterly exhausted, and all I could get her to tell me was this— which she repeated again and again with a sort of beseeching, appealing tone that made my heart bleed —” She hesitated an instant. “Tell me at once.” “‘I shall starve again, I shall starve again,’ were the words she used. She kept repeating it over and over between her sobs. ‘I shall be without anything to eat. I shall starve!’ And, would you believe it, while she hid in that nursery cupboard she had crammed so much cake and stuff into her little self that she was violently sick for a couple of days. Moreover, she now hates the sight of Dr. Hale so much, poor man, that it’s useless for him to see her. It does more harm than good.” I had risen and begun to walk up and down the hall while she told me this. I said very little. In my mind strange thoughts tore and raced, standing erect before me out of unbelievably immense depths of shadow. There was nothing very pregnant I found to say, however, for theories and speculations are of small avail as practical help—unless two minds see eye to eye in them. “And the rest?” I asked gently, coming behind the chair and resting both hands upon her shoulders. She got up at once and faced me. I was afraid to show too much sympathy lest the tears should come. “Oh, George,” she exclaimed, “I am relieved you have come. You are really strong and comforting. To feel your great hands on my shoulders gives me cour- age. But, you know, truly and honestly I am frightened out of my very wits by the child—” “You won’t stay here, of course?” “We leave at the end of this week,” she replied. “You will not desert me till then, I know. And Aileen will be all right as long as you are here, for you have the most extraordinary effect on her for good.” “Bless her little suffering imagination,” I said. “You can count on me. I’ll send to town tonight for my things.” And then she told me about the room. It was simple enough, but it conveyed a more horrible cer- tainty of something true than all the other details put together. For there was a room on the ground floor, intended to be used on wet days when the nursery was too far for muddy boots—and into this room Aileen could not go. Why? No one could tell. The facts were that the first moment the child ran in, her mother close behind, she stopped, swayed, and nearly fell. Then, with shrieks that were even heard outside by the gardeners sweeping the gravel path, she flung her- self headlong against the wall, against a particular corner of it that is to say, and beat it with her little fists until the skin broke and left stains upon the paper. It all happened in less than a minute. The words she cried so frantically her mother was too shocked and flabbergasted to remember, or even to hear properly. Aileen nearly upset her in her bewildered efforts next to find the door and escape. And the first thing she did when escape was accom- plished, was to drop in a dead faint upon the stone floor of the passage outside. “Now, is that all make-believe?” whispered Theresa, unable to keep the shudder from her lips. “Is that all merely part of a story she has make up and plays a part in?” We looked one another straight in the eyes for a space of some seconds. The dread in the mother’s heart leaped out to swell a terror in my own—a terror of another kind, but greater. “It is too late to-night,” I said at length, “for it would only excite her unnecessarily; but to-morrow I will talk with Aileen. And—if it seems wise—I might —I might be able to help in other ways too,” I added So I did talk to her—next day

IV

I always had her confidence, this little dark-eyed maid, and there was an intimacy between us that made play and talk very delightful. Yet as a rule, without giving myself a satisfactory reason, I pre- ferred talking with her in the sunlight. She was not eerie, bless her little heart of queerness and mystery, but she had a way of suggesting other ways of life and existence shouldering about us that made me look round in the dark and wonder what the shadows con- cealed or what waited round the next corner. We were on the lawn, where the bushy yews drop thick shade, the soft air making tea possible out of doors, my cousin out driving to distant calls; and Aileen had invited herself and was messing about with my manuscripts in a way that vexed me, for I had been reading my fairy tales to her and she kept asking me questions that shamed my limited powers. I remember, too, that I was glad the collie ran to and fro past us, scampering and barking after the swallows on the lawn. “Only some of your stories are true, aren’t they?” she asked abruptly. “How do you know that, young critic?” I had been waiting for an opening supplied by herself. Anything forced on my part she would have suspected. “Oh, I can tell.” Then she came up and whispered without any hint of invitation on my part, “Uncle, it is true, isn’t it, that I’ve been in other places with you? And isn’t it only the things we did there that make the true stories?” The opening was delivered all perfect and com- plete into my hands. I cannot conceive how it was I availed myself of it so queerly—I mean, how it was that the words and the name slipped out of their own accord as though I was saying something in a dream. “Of course, my little Lady Aileen, because in ima- gination, you see, we—” But before I had time to finish the sentence with which I hoped to coax out the true inwardness of her own distress, she was upon me in a heap. “Oh,” she cried, with a sudden passionate out- burst, “then you do know my name? You know all the story—our story!” She was very excited, face flushed, eyes dancing, all the emotions of a life charged to the brim with experience playing through her little person. “Of course, Miss Inventor, I know your name,” I said quickly, puzzled, and with a sudden dismay that was hideous, clutching at my throat. “And all that we did in this place?” she went on, pointing with increased excitement to the thick, ivy- grown walls of the old house. My own emotion grew extraordinarily, a swift, rushing uneasiness upsetting all my calculations. For it suddenly came back to me that in calling her “Lady Aileen” I had not pronounced the name quite as usual. My tongue had played a trick with the conson- ants and vowels, though at the moment of utterance I had somehow failed to notice the change. “Aileen” and “Helen” are almost interchangeable sounds....! And it was “Lady Helen” that I had actually said. The discovery took my breath away for an instant —and the way she had leaped upon the name to claim it. “No one else, you see, knows me as ‘Lady Helen,’” she continued whispering, “because that’s only in our story, isn’t it? And now I’m just Aileen Langton. But as long as you know, it’s all right. Oh, I am so awf’ly glad you knew, most awf ’ly, awf’ly glad.” I was momentarily at a loss for words. Keenly desirous to guide the child’s “pain-stories” into wiser channels, and thus help her to relief, I hesitated a moment for the right clue. I murmured something soothing about “our story,” while in my mind I searched vigorously for the best way of leading her on to explain all her terror of the belt, the fear of starva- tion, the room that made her scream, and all the rest. All that I was most anxious to get out of her little tor- tured mind and then replace it by some brighter dream. But the insidious experience had shaken my con- fidence a little, and these explicable emotions des- troyed my elder wisdom. The little Inventor had caught me away into the reality of her own “story” with a sense of conviction that was even beyond witchery. And the next sentence she almost instantly let loose upon me completed my discomfiture— “With you,” she said, still half whispering, “with you I could even go into the room. I never could— alone—!” The spring wind whispering in the yews behind us brought in that moment something upon me from vanished childhood days that made me tremble. Some wave of lost passion—lost because I guessed not its origin or nature—surged through the depths of me, sending faint messages to the surface of my con- sciousness. Aileen, little mischief-maker, changed before my very eyes as she stood there close—changed into a tall sad figure that beckoned to me across seas of time and distance, with the haze of ages in her eyes and gestures, I was obliged to focus my gaze upon her with a deliberate effort to see her again as the tumble- haired girl I was accustomed to. . . . Then, sitting in the creaky garden chair, I drew her down upon my knee, determined to win the whole story from her mind. My back was to the house; she was perched at an angle, however, that enabled her to command the doors and windows. I mention this because, scarcely had I begun my attack, when I saw that her attention wandered, and that she seemed curiously uneasy. Once or twice, as she shifted her position to get a view of something that was going on over my shoulder, I was aware that a slight shiver passed from her small person down to my knees. She seemed to be expecting something—with dread. “We’ll make a special expedition, armed to the teeth,” I said, with a laugh, referring to her singular words about the room. “We’ll send Pat in first to bark at the cobwebs, and we’ll take lots of provisions and— and water in case of a siege—and a file—” I cannot pretend to understand why I chose those precise words—or why it was as though other thoughts than those I had intended rose up, clamour- ing for expression. It seemed all I could manage not to say a lot of other things about the room that could only have frightened instead of relieving her. “Will you talk into the wall too?” she asked, turning her eyes down suddenly upon me with a little rush and flame of passion. And though I had not the faintest conception what she meant, the question sent an agony of yearning pain through me. “Talking into the wall,” I instantly grasped, referred to the core of her trouble, the very central idea that frightened her and provided the suffering and terror of all her ima- ginings. But I had no time to follow up the clue thus mys- teriously offered to me, for almost at the same moment her eyes fixed themselves upon something behind me with an expression of tense horror, as though she saw the approach of a danger that might— kill. “Oh, oh!” she cried under her breath, “he’s com- ing! He’s coming to take me! Uncle George—Philip —!” The same impulse operated upon us simultan- eously, it seems, for I sprang up with my fists clenched at the very instant she shot off my knee and stood with all her muscles rigid as though to resist attack. She was shaking dreadfully. Her face went the colour of linen. “Who’s coming——?” I began sharply, then stopped as I saw the figure of a man moving towards us from the house. It was the butler—the new butler who had arrived only that very afternoon. It is impossible to say what there was in his swift and silent approach that was—abominable. The man was upon us, it seemed, almost as soon as I caught sight of him, and the same moment Aileen, with a bursting cry, looking wildly about her for a place to hide in, plunged headlong into my arms and buried her face in my coat. Horribly perplexed, yet mortified that the servant should see my little friend in such a state, I did my best to pretend that it was all part of some mad game or other, and catching her up in my arms, I ran, calling the collie to follow with, “Come on, Pat! She’s our pris- oner!”—and only set her down when we were under the limes at the far end of the lawn. She was all white and ghostly from her terror, still looking frantically about her, trembling in such a way that I thought any minute she must collapse in a dead faint. She clung to me with very tight fingers. How I hated that man. Judging by the sudden violence of my loathing he might have been some monster who wanted to torture her. “Let’s go away, oh, much farther, ever so far away!” she whispered, and I took her by the hand, comforting her as best I could with words, while realizing that the thing she wanted was my big arm about her to pro- tect. My heart ached, oh, so fiercely, for her, but the odd thing about it was that I could not find anything of real comfort to say that I felt would be true. If I “made up” soothing rubbish, it would not deceive either of us and would only shake her confidence in me, so that I should lose any power I had to help. Had a tiger come upon her out of the wood I might as well have assured her it would not bite! I did stammer something, however— “It’s only the new butler. He startled me, too; he came so softly, didn’t he?” Oh! How eagerly I searched for a word that might make the thing seem as ordinary as possible—yet how vainly. “But you know who he is—really!” she said in a crying whisper, running down the path and dragging me after her; “and if he gets me again ... oh! Oh!” and she shrieked aloud in the anguish of her fear. That fear chased both of us down the winding path between the bushes. “Aileen, darling,” I cried, surrounding her with both arms and holding her very tight, “you need not be afraid. I’ll always save you. I’ll always be with you, dear child.” “Keep me in your big arms, always, always, won’t you, Uncle—Philip?” She mixed both names. The choking stress of her voice wrung me dreadfully. “Always, always, like in our story,” she pleaded, hiding her little face again in my coat. I really was at a complete loss to know what best to do; I hardly dared to bring her back to the house; the sight of the man, I felt, might be fatal to her already too delicately balanced reason, for I dreaded a fit or seizure if she chanced to run across him when I was not with her. My mind was easily made up on one point, however. “I’ll send him away at once, Aileen,” I told her. “When you wake up to-morrow he’ll be gone. Of course mother won’t keep him.” This assurance seemed to bring her some measure of comfort, and at last, without having dared to win the whole story from her as I had first hoped, I got her back to the house by covert ways, and saw her myself up-stairs to her own quarters. Also I took it upon myself to give the necessary orders. She must set no eye upon the man. Only, why was it that in my heart of hearts I longed for him to do something outrageous that should make it possible for me to break his very life at its source and kill him...? But my cousin, alarmed to the point of taking even frantic measures , finally had a sound suggestion to offer, namely that I should take the afflicted little child away with me the very next day, run down to Harwich and carry her off for a week of absolute change across the North Sea. And I, meanwhile, had reached the point where I had persuaded myself that the experiment I had hitherto felt unable to consent to had now become a permissible, even a necessary one. Hypnotism should win the story from that haunted mind without her being aware of it, and provided I could drive her deep enough into the trance state, I could then further wipe the memory from her outer consciousness so completely that she might know at last some happiness of childhood.

V

t was after ten o’clock, and I was still sitting in the big hail before the fire of logs, talking with lowered voice. My cousin sat opposite to me in a deep arm- chair. We had discussed the matter pretty fully, and the deep uneasiness we felt clothed not alone our minds but the very building with gloom. The fact that, instinctively, neither of us referred to the possible assistance of doctors is eloquent, I think, of the emo- tion that troubled us both so profoundly, the emotion, I mean, that sprang from the vivid sense of the reality of it all. No child’s make-believe merely could have thus caught us away, or spread a net that entangled our minds to such a point of confusion and dismay. It was perfectly comprehensible to me now that my cousin should have cried in very helplessness before the convincing effects of the little girl’s calamitous dis- tress. Aileen was living through a Reality, not an Invention. This was the fact that haunted the shadowy halls and corridors behind us. Already I hated the very building. It seemed charged to the roof with the memories of melancholy and ancient pain that swept my heart with shivering, cold winds. Purposely, however, I affected some degree of cheerfulness, and concealed from my cousin any men- tion of the attacks that certain emotions and alarms had made upon myself: I said nothing of my replacing “Lady Aileen” with “Lady Helen,” nothing of my passing for “Philip,” or of my sudden dashes of quasi- memory arising from the child’s inclusion of myself in her “story,” and my own singular acceptance of the rôle. I did not consider it wise to mention all that the sight of the new servant with his sinister dark face and his method of stealthy approach had awakened in my thoughts. None the less these things started con- stantly to the surface of my mind and doubtless betrayed themselves somewhere in my “atmosphere,” sufficiently at least for a woman’s intuition to divine them. I spoke passingly of the “room,” and of Aileen’s singular aversion for it, and of her remark about “talk- ing to the wall.” Yet strange thoughts pricked their way horribly into both our minds. In the hall the stuffed heads of deer and fox and badger stared upon us like masks of things still alive beneath their fur and dead skin. “But what disturbs me more than all the rest of her delusions put together,” said my cousin, peering at me with eyes that made no pretence of hiding dark things, “is her extraordinary knowledge of this place. I assure you, George, it was the most uncanny thing I’ve ever known when she showed me over and asked questions as if she had actually lived here.” Her voice sank to a whisper, and she looked up startled. It seemed to me for a moment that some one was com- ing near to listen, moving stealthily upon us along the dark approaches to the hall. “I can understand you found it strange,” I began quickly. But she interrupted me at once. Clearly it gave her a certain relief to say the things and get them out of her mind where they hid, breeding new growths of abhorrence. “George,” she cried aloud, “there’s a limit to ima- gination. Aileen knows. That’s the awful thing—.” Something sprang into my throat. My eyes moistened. “The horror of the belt——” she whispered, loath- ing her own words. “Leave that thought alone,” I said with decision. The detail pained me inexpressibly—beyond belief. “I wish I could,” she answered, “but if you had seen the look on her face when she struggled—and the— the frenzy she got into about the food and starving—I mean when Dr. Hale spoke—oh, if you had seen all that, you would understand that I—” She broke off with a start. Some one had entered the hall behind us and was standing in the doorway at the far end. The listener had moved upon us from the dark. Theresa, though her back was turned, had felt the presence and was instantly upon her feet. “You need not sit up, Porter,” she said, in at one that only thinly veiled the fever of apprehension behind, “we will put the lights out,” and the man with- drew like a shadow. She exchanged a quick glance with me. A sensation of darkness that seemed to have come with the servant’s presence was gone. It is wholly bey- ond me to explain why neither myself nor my cousin found anything to say for some minutes. But it was still more a mystery, I think, why the muscles of my two hands should have contracted involuntarily with a force that drove the nails into my palms, and why the violent impulse should have leaped into my blood to fling myself upon the man and strangle the life out of his neck before he could take another breath. I have never before or since experienced this apparently causeless desire to throttle anybody. I hope I never may again. “He hangs about rather,” was all my cousin said presently. “He’s always watching us—” But my own thoughts were horribly busy, and I was marvelling how it was this ugly and sinister creature had ever come to be accepted in the story that Aileen lived, and that I was slowly coming to believe in. It was a relief to me when, towards midnight. Theresa rose to go to bed. We had skirted through the horrors of the child’s possessing misery without ever quite facing it, and as we stood there lighting the candles, our voices whispering, our minds charged with the strain of thoughts neither of us had felt it wise to utter, my cousin started back against the wall and stared up into the darkness above where the stair case climbed the well of the house. She uttered a cry. At first I thought she was going to collapse. I was only just in time to catch the candle. All the emotions of fearfulness she had repressed during our long talk came out in that brief cry, and when I looked up t o discover the cause I saw a small white figure come slowly down the wide staircase and just about to step into the hall. It was Aileen, with bare feet, her dark hair tumbling down over her night- gown, her eyes wide open, an expression in them of anguished expectancy that her tender years could never possibly have known. She was walking steadily, yet somehow not quite as a child walks. “Stop!” I whispered peremptorily to my cousin, putting my hand quickly over her mouth, and holding her back from the first movement of rescue, “don’t wake her. She’s walking in her sleep.” Aileen passed us like a white shadow, scarcely aud- ible, and went straight across the hall. She was utterly unaware of our presence. Avoiding all obstructions of chairs and tables, moving with decision and purpose, the little figure dipped into the shadows at the far end and disappeared from view in the mouth of the cor- ridor that had once—three hundred years ago—led into the wing where now the copper beeches grew upon open lawns. It was clearly a way familiar to her. And the instant I recovered from my surprise and moved after her to act, Theresa found her voice and cried aloud—a voice that broke the midnight silence with shrill discordance— “George, oh, George! She’s going to that awful room...!” “Bring the candle and come after me,” I replied from halfway down the hall, “but do not interrupt unless I call for you,” and was after the child at a pace to which the most singular medley of emotions I have ever known urged me imperiously. A sense of tragic disaster gripped my very vitals. All that I did seemed to rise out of some subconscious region of the mind where the haunting passions of a deeply buried past stirred in their sleep and woke. “Helen!” I cried, “Lady Helen!” I was close upon the gliding figure. Aileen turned and for the first time saw me with eyes that seemed to waver between sleep and waking. They gazed straight at me over the flick- ering candle flame, then hesitated. In similar fashion the gesture of her little hands towards me was arres- ted before it had completed itself. She saw me, knew my presence, yet was uncertain who I was. It was astonishing the way I actually surprised this moment- ary indecision between the two personalities in her— caught the two phases of her consciousness at grips— discerned the Aileen of Today in the act of waking to know me as her “Uncle George,” and that other Aileen of her great dark story, the “Helen” of some far Yester- day, that drew her in this condition of somnambulism to the scene in the past where our two lives were linked in her imagination. For it was quite clear to me that the child was dreaming in her sleep the action of the story she lived through in the vivid moments of her waking terror. But the choice was swift. I just had time to signal Theresa to set the candle upon a shelf and wait, when she came up, stretched her hands out in completion of the original gesture, and fell into my arms with a smothered cry of love and anguish that, coming from those childish lips, I think is the most thrilling human sound I have ever known. She knew and saw me, but not as “Uncle” George of this present life. “Oh, Philip! “she cried, “then you have come after all—” “Of course, dear heart,” I whispered. “Of course I have come. Did I not give my promise that I would?” Her eyes searched my face, and then settled upon my hands that held her little cold wrists so tightly. “But—but,” she stammered in comment, “they are not cut! They have made you whole again! You will save me and get me out, and we—we—” The expressions of her face ran together into a queer confusion of perplexity, and she seemed to tot- ter on her feet. In another instant she would probably have wakened; again she felt the touch of uncertainty and doubt as to my identity. Her hands resisted the pressure of my own; she drew back half a step; into her eyes rose the shallower consciousness of the present. Once awake it would drive out the profoundly strange passion and mystery that haunted the cor- ridors of thought and memory and plunged so obscurely into the inmost recesses of her being. For, once awake, I realized that I should lose her, lose the opportunity of getting the complete story. The chance was unique. I heard my cousin’s footsteps approach- ing behind us down the passage on tiptoe—and I came to an immediate decision. In the state of deep sleep, of course, the trance condition is very close, and many experiments had taught me that the human spirit can be subjected to the influence of hypnotism far more speedily when asleep than when a wake; for if hypnotism means chiefly—as I then held it to mean—the merging of the little ineffectual surface-consciousness with the deep sea of the greater subliminal consciousness below, then the process has already been partially begun in normal slumber and its completion need be no very long or difficult matter. It was Aileen’s very active subconsciousness that “invented” or “remembered” the dark story which haunted her life, her subconscious region too readily within tap. . . . By deepening her sleep state I could learn the whole story. Stopping her mother’s approach with a sign that I intended she should clearly understand, and which accordingly she did understand, I took immediate steps to plunge the spirit of this little sleep-walking child down again into the subconscious region that had driven her thus far, and wherein lay the potential- ities of all her powers, of memory, knowledge and belief. Only the simplest passes were necessary, for she yielded quickly and easily; that first look came back into her eyes; she no longer wavered or hesitated, but drew close against me, with the name of “Philip” upon her lips, and together we moved down the long passage till we reached the door of her horrid room of terror. And there, whether it was that Theresa’s following with the candle disturbed the child—for the subcon- scious tie with the mother is of such unalterable power—or whether anxiety weakened my authority over her fluctuating mental state, I noticed that she again wavered and hesitated, looking up with eyes that saw partly “Uncle George,” partly the “Philip” she remembered. “We’ll go in,” I said firmly, “and you shall see that there is nothing to be afraid of.” I opened the door, and the candle from behind threw a triangle of light into the darkness. It fell upon a bare floor, pictureless walls, and just tipped the high white ceiling overhead. I pushed the door still wider open and we went in hand in hand, Aileen shaking like a leaf in the wind. How the scene lives in my mind, even as I write it to-day so many years after it took place: the little child in her nightgown facing me in that empty room of the ancient building, all the passionate emotions of a tra- gic history in the small young eyes, her mother like a ghost in the passage, afraid to come in, the tossing shadows thrown by the candle and the soft moan of the night wind against the outside walls. I made further passes over the small flushed face and pressed my thumbs gently along the temples. “Sleep!” I commanded; “sleep—and remember!” My will poured over her being to control and protect. She passed still deeper into the trance condition in which the somnambulistic lucidity manifests itself and the deeper self gives up its dead. Her eyes grew wider, rounder, charged with memories as they fastened themselves upon my own. The present, which a few minutes before had threatened to claim her con- sciousness by waking her, faded. She saw me no longer as her familiar Uncle George, but as the faithful friend and lover of her great story, Philip, the man who had come to save her. There she stood in the atmosphere of bygone days, in the very room where she had known great suffering—this room that three centuries ago had led by a corridor into the wing of the house where now the beeches grew upon the lawns. She came up close and put her thin bare arms about my neck and stared with peering, searching eyes into mine. “Remember what happened here,” I said resol- utely. “Remember, and tell me.” Her brows contracted slightly as with the effort, and she whispered, glancing over her shoulder to wards the farther end where the corridor once began, “It hurts a little, but I—I’m in your arms, Philip dear, and you will get me out, I know——” “I hold you safe and you are in no danger, little one,” I answered. “You can remember and speak without it hurting you. Tell me.” The suggestion, of course, operated instantly, for her face cleared, and she dropped a great sigh of relief. From time to time I continued the passes that held the trance condition firm. Then she spoke in a low, silvery little tone that cut into me like a sword and searched my inmost parts. I seemed to bleed internally. I could have sworn that she spoke of things I knew as though I had lived through them. “This was when I last saw you,” she said, “this was the room where you were to fetch me and carry me away into happiness and safety from—him,” and it was the voice and words of no mere child that said it; “and this was where you did come on that night of snow and wind. Through that window you entered;” she pointed to the deep, embrasured window behind us. “Can’t you hear the storm? How it howls and screams! And the boom of the surf on the beach below.... You left the horses outside, the swift horses that were to carry us to the sea and away from all his cruelties, and then—” She hesitated and searched for words or memor- ies; her face darkened with pain and loathing. “Tell me the rest,” I ordered, “but forget all your own pain.” And she smiled up at me with an expres- sion of unbelievable tenderness and confidence while I drew the frail form closer. “You remember, Philip,” she went on, “you know just what it was, and how he and his men seized you the moment you stepped inside, and how you struggled and called for me, and heard me answer—” “Far away—outside—” I interrupted quickly, help- ing her out of some flashing memory in my own deep heart that seemed to burn and leave a scar. “You answered from the lawn!” “You thought it was the lawn, but really, you see, it was there—in there,” and she point ed to the side of the room on my right. She shook dreadfully, and her voice dwindled most oddly in volume, as though com- ing from a distance—almost muffled. “In there?” I asked it with a shudder that put ice and fire mingled in my blood. “In the wall,” she whispered. “You see, some one had betrayed us, and he knew you were coming. He walled me up alive in there, and only left two little holes for my eyes so that I could see. You heard my voice calling through those holes, but you never knew where I was. And then—” Her knees gave way, and I had to hold her. She looked suddenly with torture in her eyes down the length of the room—towards the old wing of the house. “You won’t let him come,” she pleaded beseech- ingly, and in her voice was the agony of death. “I thought I heard him. Isn’t that his footsteps in the corridor?” She listened fearfully, her eyes trying to pierce the wall and see out on to the lawn. “No one is coming, dear heart,” I said, with convic- tion and authority. “Tell it all. Tell me every thing.” “I saw the whole of it because I could not close my eyes,” she continued. “There was an iron band round my waist fastening me in—an iron belt I never could escape from. The dust got into my mouth—I bit the bricks. My tongue was scraped and bleeding, but before they put in the last stones to smother me I saw them—cut both your hands off so that you could never save me—never let me out.” She dashed without warning from my side and flew up to the wall, beating it with her hands and cry- ing aloud— “Oh , you poor, poor thing. I know how awful it was. I remember—when I was in you and you wore and carried me, poor, poor body! That thunder of the last brick as they drove it in against the mouth, and the iron clamp that cut into the waist, and the suffoca- tion and hunger and thirst!” “What are you talking to in there?” I asked sternly, crushing down the tears. “The body I was in—the one he walled up—my body—my own body!” She flew back to my side. But even before my cousin had uttered that “mother-cry” that broke in upon the child’s deeper consciousness, disturbing the memories, I had given the command with all the force of my being to “forget” the pain. And only those few who are familiar with the instantaneous changes of emotion that can be produced by suggestion under hypnosis will understand that Aileen came back to me from that moment of “talking to the wall” with laughter on her lips and in her eyes. The small white figure with the cascade of dark hair tumbling over the nightgown ran up and jumped into my arms. “But I saved you,” I cried, “you were never properly walled-up; I got you out and took you away from him over the sea, and we were happy ever after wards, like the people in the fairy tales.” I drove the words into her with my utmost force, and inevitably she accepted them as the truth, for she clung to me with love and laughter all over her child’s face of mystery, the horror fading out, the pain swept clean away. With kaleido- scopic suddenness the change came. “So they never really cut your poor dead hands off at all,” she said hesitatingly. “Look! How could they? There they are! And I first showed them to her and then pressed them against her little cheeks, drawing her mouth up to be kissed. “They’re big enough still and strong enough to carry you off to bed and stroke you into so deep a sleep that when you wake in the morning you will have forgotten everything about your dark story, about Philip, Lady Helen, the iron belt, the starvation, your cruel old husband, and all the rest of it. You’ll wake up happy and jolly just like any other child—” “If you say so, of course I shall,” she answered, smiling into my eyes. And it was just then there came in that touch of abomination that so nearly made my experiment a failure, for it came with a black force that threatened at first to discount all my “suggestion” and make it of no account. My new command that she should forget had apparently not yet fully registered itself in her being; the tract of deeper consciousness that con- structed the “Story” had not sunk quite below the threshold. Thus she was still open to any detail of her former suffering that might obtrude itself with suffi- cient force. And such a detail did obtrude itself. This touch of abomination was calculated with a really superhuman ingenuity. “Hark!” she cried—and it was that scream in a whisper that only utter terror can produce—“Hark! I hear his steps! He’s coming! Oh, I told you he was coming! He’s in that passage!” pointing down the room. And she first sprang from my arms as though something burned her, and then almost instantly again flew back to my protection. In that interval of a few seconds she tore into the middle of the room, put her hand to her ear to listen, and then shaded her eyes in the act of peering down through the wall at the far end. She stared at the very place where in olden days the corridor had led into the vanished wing. The win- dow my great-uncle had built into the wall now occu- pied the exact spot where the opening had been. Theresa then for the first time came forward with a rush into the room, dropping the candle-grease over the floor. She clutched me by the arm. The three of us stood there—listening—listening apparently to nought but the sighing of the sea-wind about the walls, Aileen with her eyes buried in my coat. I was standing erect trying in vain to catch the new sound. I remember my cousin’s face of chalk with the flutter- ing eyes and the candle held aslant. Then suddenly she raised her hand and pointed over my shoulder. I thought her jaw would drop fr om her face. And she and the child both spoke in the same breath the two sharp phrases that brought the climax of the vile adventure upon us in that silent room of night. They were like two pistol-shots. “My God! There’s a face watching us...!” I hear d her voice, all choked and dry. And at the same second, Aileen— “Oh, oh! He’s seen us! ... He’s here! Look.... He’ll get me ... hide your hands, hide your poor hands!” And, turning to the place my cousin stared at, I saw sure enough that a face—apparently a living human face—was pressed against the window-pane, framed between two hands as it tried to peer upon us into the semi-obscurity of the room. I saw the swift momentary rolling of the two eyes as the candle glare fell upon them, and caught a glimpse even of the hunched-up shoulders behind, as their owner, stand- ing outside upon the lawn, stooped down a little to see better. And though the apparition instantly with- drew, I recognized it beyond question as the dark and evil countenance of the butler. His breath still stained the window. Yet the strange thing was that Aileen, struggling violently to bury herself amid the scanty folds of my coat, could not possibly have seen what we saw, for her face was turned from the window the entire time, and from the way I held her she could never for a single instant have been in a position to know. It all took place behind her back.... A moment later, with her eyes still hidden against me, I was carrying her swiftly in my arms across the hall and up the main staircase to the night nursery. My difficulty with her was, of course, while she hovered between the two states of sleep and waking, for once I got her into bed and plunged her deeply again into the trance condition, I was easily able to control her slightest thought or emotion. Within ten minutes she was sleeping peacefully, her little face smoothed of all anxiety or terror, and my imperious command ringing from end to end of her conscious- ness that when she woke next morning all should be forgotten. She was finally to forget ... utterly and com- pletely. And, meanwhile, of course, the man, when I went with loathing and anger in my heart to his room in the servants’ quarters, had a perfectly plausible explana- tion. He was in the act of getting ready for bed, he declared, when the noise had aroused his suspicions, and, as in duty bound, he had made a tour of the house outside, thinking to discover burglars.... With a month’s wages in his pocket, and a consid- erable degree of wonder in his soul, probably—for the man was guilty of nothing worse than innocently ter- rifying a child’s imagination!—he went back to Lon- don the following day; and a few hours later I myself was travelling with Aileen and old Kempster over the blue waves of the North Sea, carrying her off, curi- ously enough, to freedom and happiness in the very way her “imagination” had pictured her escape in the “story” of long ago, when she was Lady Helen, held in bondage by a cruel husband, and I was Philip, her devoted lover. Only this time her happiness was lasting and com- plete. Hypnotic suggestion had wiped from her mind the last vestige of her dreadful memories; her face was wreathed in jolly smiles; her enjoyment of the journey and our week in Antwerp was absolutely unclouded; she played and laughed with all the radiance of an unhaunted childhood, and her imagination was purged and healed. And when we got back her mother had again moved her household gods to the original family man- sion where she had first lived. Thither it was I took the restored child, and there it was my cousin and I looked up the old family records and verified certain details of the history of De Lorne, that wicked and semi-fabulous ancestor whose portrait hung in the dark corner of the stairs. That his life was evil to the brim I had always understood, but neither myself nor Theresa had known—at least had not consciously remembered—that he had married twice, and that his first wife, Lady Helen, had mysteriously disappeared, and Sir Philip Lansing, a neighbouring knight, sup- posed to be her lover, had soon afterwards emigrated to France and left his lands and property to go to ruin. But another discovery I made, and kept to myself, had to do with that “room of terror” in the old Norfolk house where, on the plea of necessary renovation, I had the stones removed, and in the very spot where Aileen used to beat her hands against the bricks and “talk to the wall,” the workmen under my own eyes laid bare the skeleton of a woman, fastened to the granite by means of a narrow iron band that encircled the waist—the skeleton of some unfortunate who had been walled-up alive and had come to her dreadful death by the pangs of hunger, thirst and suffocation centuries ago.

On Wings

No thinking man can watch the flight of birds, especially of big birds, without grave thoughts of wonder and delight rising in him. Their ease and grace and strength of movement, their light and sure supremacy over the medium which they navigate with such consummate facility, their speed and dropping swiftness, are all so incomparably superior to any mechanical motor skill that we possess ourselves. No other living organisms, perhaps, express so well the joy of motion. It is difficult to watch the circling seagulls, the poised and hovering hawk, the darting swallows, or the soaring lark, without feeling that here is life really enjoying itself in the best possible form of free, unimpeded motion. No wonder that poets give the angels wings, and that the symbolism of wings is found in the most vital thoughts of all religions. The wings of the soul, the wings of the imagination, these are more than mere empty phrases!

The choice of the air to illustrate some imagined spiritual region, of course, is obvious enough, for air will most certainly be the last department of Nature men will conquer; and, apart from unwieldy mechanical contrivances, men will never really fly—as birds do. To pass through and across the air is quite another thing to flying as the birds know flying. The religious temperament made a_ wise, instinctive selection of flying to describe the motion of a “spirit,” for nothing could be further from possible corporeal achievement. The weight of men’s bodies in proportion to their muscular development for ever blocks the way; whereas the power of the muscles that drive the wings of birds, compared to the weight of their slender, delicate frames, their tiny bones, their hollow quills, is overwhelmingly to their advantage. A drumming partridge can flap its sturdy wings four hundred times to the minute. It is doubtful if the supplest man can “flap”’ his arms at a quarter of this speed, and a broad wing offers far more resistance to the air than the thin line of a human arm. The eye cannot even follow the beats of a flying pigeon’s wings to count their number.

To watch the seagulls from the stern of some steamer is a keen delight. One notes the cunningly-contrived arrangement of the feathers, which lie one upon another in such a way that the downward stroke is not exactly counterbalanced by the upward. In the former the air presses them closer together, thus supplying the resistance necessary to rise; whereas in the upward stroke they open out, letting the air slip through. With what minimum of effort, too, they compass the maximum of movement; with how tiny a tilting of the body they steer to avoid collision; how rapid, almost instantaneous, is their judgment when to dive, seizing an opening in the flash of an eye, or rising, swerving, swooping for a plunge! There is nothing in all Nature to compare with their consummate skill and lightning ease. The accuracy of a marten’s or a swallow’s aim in darting through mid-air to snap at a zigzag-flying insect is an exhibition of surpassing skill.

And equally fascinating to watch, perhaps, is the adroit and wonderful balancing a bird displays in hovering with motionless wings outstretched, and the way it uses every current of air to sustain or propel its perfectly-adjusted weight. One could almost imagine that there ran through every feather down to the very tips some exquisite system of nerves more delicate even than those of human beings. They seem to feel the wind, to be forewarned of every slightest change, to sense the advance and retreat of every little current.

It was always the sea-birds that, as a boy, I envied most. Their mastery over two elements seemed so unfair, They are free of more of the earth than is their right, as it were. But one never grudged the birds their happiness and powers for long. Childhood always loves the birds—their mystery lies closer to the dreams of imaginative childhood, perhaps, than the mystery of four-footed life, and in proportion to their number they contain fewer fierce and savage, certainly fewer dangerous, species. The air would mean to us so little without them; their song and movement seem to interpret all the vault of sky. The passion of a single lark can set a whole spring morning to music; and where would be half the beauty of the summer dusk without the whistle of a blackbird across the lawn, the trill of a thrush in the laurels, the glory of the nightingales in the shrubberies and larches?

Scenery for some comes back most vividly to the mind with the memory of the bird-life associated with it. To hear the laughter of the loons, so weirdly human in its note, and see their straight and level flight across wide, lonely lakes, so close that their feet must catch the spray of every wave, recalls for me the Canadian backwoods far more completely than any memory of deer or moose or bear. For me personally the birds divide this reconstructive power about equally with the smells of trees and flowers, or, above all, the odour of wood smoke. A line of dark cormorants, or the storks and herons fishing in the shallows, are more evocative for me of the Hungarian reaches of the Danube, where I once canoed, than any other detail of the banks or landscape I can call to mind. Those circling hawks of giant size above the endless marshes! Those flocks of grey crows rising from some shingled island in mid-stream as our canoe approached! The great white swans of the upper sections in the Black Forest and Bavaria! All the little pictures of the thousand-mile journey that come back to haunt the mind with their separate bits of loveliness have bird-life in them somewhere. The rest, even the rapids, dangerous rocks and whirlpools, lie indistinct and rather vague; these with the birds, on the contrary, stand out sharply and well defined.

Last year, while crossing the Black Sea in early May towards the Caucasus, our steamer had from time to time strange winged visitors who certainly paid no passage-money. Vessels were few and far between, and many birds rested in their long flight from shore to shore upon the rigging. Some accompanied the boat for days together, and one and all were obviously very weary. There were brown birds, like pigeons, only smaller, that rested on the stern rails, flew off for long detours about the ship, then presently returned again to settle; there was a large, dark hawk that perched high up upon the cross-trees watching them hungrily (and, happily, in vain); and there were numerous smaller fry of various kinds, whose names I knew not, for ever dodging the cats and passengers. Swallows, evidently belated, came to join them, and would flit up and down in front of the rows of occupied deck-chairs after dinner in search of sleeping-places. There was one in particular that showed no fear of human kind, but calmly fluttered on to my cap and settled itself down comfortably, after a little preliminary fidgeting, for sleep. Being in the middle of a story that necessitated turning the head to neighbours on either side of me, the attention at first was awkward, and the interest in the bird eclipsed all interest in the story. But the compliment, I felt, was greater than that of applause, and I soon found that it was possible to turn the head so carefully that the little creature need not be disturbed. At any rate, it stayed for fully half-an-hour, doubtless sound asleep, and fortunately for its feelings no one on deck wore hats with stuffed birds on them! Several of the brown, pigeon-like birds, however, came to a curious end. Whether in their weariness they dropped into the sea and were drowned, or whether waiting and watching fish pulled them under, as the ship’s doctor affirmed, was hard to say. One saw them skimming beside the steamer, so close to the waves they almost touched their crests, then suddenly—disappear. They went under at once. There certainly was no struggle of any kind, and no attempt to swim or rise again. Without a flutter of the wings they simply vanished.

Onanonanon

Certain things had made a deep impression in his childhood days; among these was the incident of the barking dog.

It barked during his convalescence from something that involved scarlet and a peeling skin; his early mind associated bright colour and peeling skin with the distress of illness. The tiresome barking of a dog accompanied it. In later years this sound always brought back the childhood visualisation: across his mind would flit a streak of vivid colour, a peeling skin, a noisy dog, all set against a background of emotional discomfort and physical distress.

“It’s barking at me!” he complained to his old nurse, whose explanation that it was “Carlo with his rheumatics in the stables ”brought no relief. He spoke to his mother later; ‘ It never, never stops. It goes on and on and on on purpose—onanonanon! ”

How queer the words sounded! He had got them wrong somewhere—onanonanon. Or was it a name, the name of the barking animal—Onan Onan Onanonanon?

His mother’s words were more comforting: “Carlo’s barking because you’re ill, darling; he wants you to get well.” And she added: ” Soon I’ll bring him in to see you. You shall ride on his back again.”

“Would he peel if I stroked him?” He enquired, a trifle frightened., “Is the skin shiny like mine?”

She shook her head and smiled. “I’ll explain to him,” she went on, ” and then he’ll understand. He won’t bark any more.” She brought the picture-book of natural history that included all creatures in Ark and Zoo and Jungle. He picked out the brightly-coloured tiger.

“A tiger doesn’t bark, does it?” he asked, and her reply added slightly to his knowledge, but much to his imagination. “But does it ever bark}’* he persisted. “That’s really what I asked.”

“Growls and snarls,” said a deep voice from the doorway, He started; but it was only his father, who then came in and amused him by imitating the sound a tiger makes, .until Carlo’s naughtiness was forgotten, and the world went on turning smoothly as before.

After that the barking ceased; the rheumatic creature sniffed the air and nosed the metal biscuit tray in silence. He understood apparently. It had been rather dreadful, this noise he made. The sharp sound had broken the’ morning stillness for many days; no one but the boy was awake at that early hour; the boy and the dog had the dawn entirely to themselves. He used to lie in bed, counting the number of barks. They seemed endless, they jarred, they never stopped. They came singly, then in groups of thrqe and four at a time, then in a longer series, then singly again. These single barks often had a sound of finality about them, the creature’s breath was giving out, it was tired; it was the full-stop sound. But the true full-stop, the final bark, never came—and the boy had complained.

He loved old Carlo, loved riding on his burly back that wobbled from side to side, as they moved forward very slowly; in particular he loved stroking the thick curly hair; it tickled his fingers and felt nice on his palm. He was relieved to know it would not peel. Yet he wondered impatiently’why the creature he loved to play with should go on making such a dreadful noise. “Doesn’t he know.? Can’t he wait till I’m ready?” There were moments when he doubted if it really was Carlo, when he almost hated the beast, when he asked himself, “I’s this Carlo, or is it Onanonanon … ?” The idea alarmed him rather. Onanonanon was not quite friendly, not quite safe.

At the age of fifty he found himself serving his King during the Great War—in a neutral country whose police regarded him with disfavour, and would have instantly arrested and clapped him into gaol, had he made a slip. He did not make this slip, though incessant caution had to be his watchword. He belonged to that service which runs risks yet dare claim no credit. He passed under another name than his-own, and his alias sometimes did things his true self would not do. ’This alter ego developed oddly He projected temporarily, as it were, a secondary personality—which he disliked, often despised, and sometimes even feared. His sense of humour, however, made lieht of the split involved. When he was followed, he used to chu(^le: I wonder if the sleuths kiiow which of the two they re tracking down—myself or my alias?”“

It was in the melancholy season between autumn and winter, snow on the heights and fog upon the lower levels, when he was suddenly laid low by the plague that milked the world. The Spanish influenza caught him. He went to bed; he had a doctor and a nurse; no one else in the hotel came near his room; the police forgot him, and he forgot the police. His hated alias, Baker, also was forgotten, or perhaps merged back into the parent self. … Outside his quarters on the first floor the plane-trees shed I rain-soaked leaves, letting them fall with an audible plop upon the gravel path *, he heard the waves of the sullen lake in the distance; the crunching of passing fwt he heard much closer. The heating was indifferent, the light too weak to read by. It was a lonely, dismal time. On the floor above two people died, three on the ^e below, the French officer next door was carried out. The hotel, like many others, became a hospital.

In due course, the fever passed, the intolerable aching ceased, he forgot the times when he had thought he was ^ing to die. He lay, half convalescent, remembering the recent past, then the remoter past, and so slipped back to dim childhood scenes when the cross but faithful old nurse had tended him. He smelt the burning leaves in the kitchen-garden, and heard the blackbird whistle beyond the summer-house. The odour of moist earth in the tool-house stole back, with the fragrance of sweet apples in the forbidden loft. These earliest layers of memory fluttered their ghostly pictures like a cinema before his receptive mind. There were eyes long closed, voices long silent, the touch of hands long dead and gone. The rose-garden on a sultry August afternoon was vivid, with the smell of the ram-washed petals, as the sun blazed over them after a heavy shower. The soaked lawn emitted warm little bubbles like a soft squeezed sponge, audibly; even the gravel steamed. He remembered Carlo, with his rheumatism, his awkward gambol, his squashy dog-biscuit beside the kennel and—his bark.

In the state of semi-unconsciousness he lay, weary, weak, depressed and very lonely. The nurse, on her rare visits, afflicted him, the hotel guests did not ask after him. To the Service at home he was on the sick-list, useless. The morning newspaper and the hurried, perfunctory visits of the doctor were his only interest. It seemed a pity he had not died. The mental depression after influenza can be extremely devastating. He looked forward to nothing.

Then, suddenly, the dog began its barking.

He heard it first at six o’clock when, waking, hot and thirsty in a bed that had lost its comfort, he wondered vz^uely if the day was going to be fine or wet. His window opened on to the lake. He watched the shadows melt across the dreary room. The late dawn came softly, its hint of beauty ever unfulfilled. Would it be gold or grey behind the mountains? The dog went on barking.

He dozed, counting the barks without being aware that he did so. He felt hot and uncomfortable, and turned over in bed, counting automatically as he did so: “fifteen, sixteen, seventeen”—pause—“eighteen, nineteen”—another pause, then with great rapidity, “twenty, twenty-one, twenty-two, twenty-three—” He opened his eyes wide and cursed aloud. The barking stopped.

The wind came softly off the lake, enter\ig the room. He heard the last big leaf of the plane-trees rattle to the gravel path. As it touched the ground the barking began again, his counting—now conscious counting—^began with it.

“Curse the brute! ” he muttered, and turned over once more to try and sleep. The rasping, harsh, staccato sound reached his ears piercingly through sheets and blankets; not even the thick duvet could muffle it. Would no one stop it? Did no one care? He felt furious, but helpless, dreadfully helpless.

It barked, stopped, then barked again.^ There were solitary, isolated barks, followed by a rapid series, short and hurried. A shower of barks came next. ^ Pauses were frequent, but they were worse than the actual sound. It continued, it went on, the dog barked without ceasing. It barked and barked. He had lost all count. It barked and barked and barked. It stopped.

“At last!” he groaned. “My God! Another minute, and I—!”

His whole body, as he turned over, knew an immense, deep relaxation. His jangled nerves were utterly exhausted. A great sigh of relief escaped him. The silence was delicious. It was real silence. He rested at last. Sleep, warm and intoxicating, stole gently back. He dozed. Forgetfulness swam over him.’ He by in down, in cotton-wool. Police, alias, nurse and loneliness were all obliterated, when, suddenly, across the blissful peace, cracked out that sharp, explosive sound again—the bark.

But the dog barked differently this time; the sound was much nearer. At first this puzzled him. Then he guessed the truth; the animal had come into the hotel and up the Stairs ; it was outside in the passage. He opened his eyes and sat up in bed. The door, to his surprise, was being cautiously pushed ajar. He was just in time to see who pushed it with such gentle, careful pressure. Standing on the landing in the early twilight was Baker, his other self, his alias, the personality he disliked and sometimes dreaded. Baker put his head round the corner, glanced at him, nodded familiarly, and withdrew, closing the door instantly, making no slightest sound. But, before it closed, and before he had time even to feel astonishment, the dog had been let in. And the dog, he saw at once, was old Carlo!

Having expected a little stranger dog, this big, shag^, familiar beast caused him to feel a sense of curious wonder and bewilderment.

“But were you the dog down there ifiat barked?” he asked aloud, as the friendly creature came waddling up to the bedside. ” And have you come to say you’re sorry?”

It blinked its rheumy eyes and wagged its stumpy tail. He put out his hand and stroked its familiar, wobbly back. His fingers buried themselves in the stiff crinkly hair. Its dim old eyes turned affectionately up at him. It smiled its silly, happy smile. He went on rubbing. “Carlo, good old Carlo \ he mumbled; “well, I’m blessed! I’ll get on your back in a minute and ride—”

He stopped rubbing. *^Why did you come in?” Ke asked abruptly, and repeated the question, a touch of anxiety in his voice. “How did you manage it, really? Tell me. Carlo?”

The old beast shifted its position a little, making a sideways motion that he did not like. It seemed to move its hind legs only. Its muzzle now rested on the bed. Its eyes, seen full, looked not quite so kind and friendly. They cleared a little. But its tail still wagged. Only, now that he saw it better, the tail seemed longer than it ought to have been. There was something unpleasant about the dog—a faint inexplicable shade of difference. He stared a moment straight into its face. It no longer blinked in the silly, affectionate way as at first. The rheum was less. There was a light, a gleam, in the eyes, almost a flash.

Are you—Carlo?” he asked sharply, uneasily, or are you—Onanonanon?”

It rose abruptly on its hind legs, laying the front paws on the counterpane of faded yellow. The legs made dark streaks against this yellow.

He had begun stroking the old back again. He now stopped. He withdrew his hand. The hair was coming out It came off beneath his fingers, aM each stroke he made left a line of lighter skin behind it. This skin was yellowish, with a slight tinge, he thought, of sc^let.

The dog—he could almost swear to it—had altered; it was still altering. Before his very eyes, it grew, became curiously enlarged. It now towered over him. It was longer, thinner, leaner than before, its tail came lashing round its hollow, yellowing flanks, the eyes ^one brilliantly, its tongue was a horrid red. The brute straightened its front paws. It was huge. Its open mouth grinned down at him. ,

He was petrified, with terror. He tried to scream, but the only sound that came were little innocent words of childhood days. He almost lisped them, simpering vaA horror: “I’d get on your back—if I was allowed out of bed. You’d carry me. I’d ride.” « *

It was a desperate attempt to pacify the beast, to persuade it, even in this terrible’ moment, to be friendly, a feeble, hopeless attempt to convince himself that it was—Carlo. The Monster was twelve feet from head to tail, of, dull yellow striped with black. The gfreat jaws, wide open, dripped upon his face. He saw the pointed teeth, the stiff, quivering whiskers of white wire. He felt the hot breath upon his cheeks and lips. It was foetid. He tasted it.

He was on the point of fainting when a step sounded outside the door. Someone was coming.

“Saved!” he gasped.

The suspense and relief were almost intolerable. The touch of a hand feeling cautiously, stealthily, over the door was audible. The handle rattled faintly.

“Saved!” his heart repeated, as the great brute turned its giant head to listen.

He knew that touch. It was Baker, his hated alias, come in the nick of time to rescue him. Yet the door did not open. Instead, the monster lashed its tail, it stiffened horribly, it turned its head back from watching the door, and lowered itself appallingly. The key turned in the lock, a bolt was shot. He was locked in alone with a tiger. He closed his eyes.

His recurrent nightmare had ruined sleep again, and outside, in the dreary autumn dawn, a little dog was yapping fiendishly on and on and on and on.

Our Adventure with the Danube “River-Police”

In July of last year, while travelling down the Danube in a flat-bottomed boat, an adventure befell us that I am sure will long live in the memories of all who took part in it. Certainly, the impudent Bavarian who was the central figure in it (as well as the deserving victim) is not likely to forget it in a hurry, or to repeat an experiment that cost him dear in the eyes of his companions, and secured him an unwelcome dousing in the river into the bargain!

Our party consisted of four persons, two ladies and two men; and we steered our own boat, put up our tents on the shores wherever we happened to find ourselves at nightfall, and cooked our own meals in the most approved camping fashion.

We were three weeks on the river all told, and by the time we reached Buda-pesth we had travelled a good many hundred miles from our starting-point; but, although there are rapids and whirlpools and one or two nasty bridges to negotiate for a small boat, we accomplished the journey without serious misadventure, and the only time we came into unpleasant conflict with the natives was on the occasion of the incident which I am about to describe.

Having already been down the Danube before (as told in the B.O.P. two years ago), we “knew the ropes” pretty well, and remembered that there were certain things it was just as well to bear in mind. And one of these was that all the way down a narrow strip of the banks on both sides belongs to the German Government; no private property can run down quite to the river’s edge as it does, of course, on the Thames. This ensures the banks being kept in good repair, and the rule is probably intended in case of war; but the important thing for campers like ourselves was that the only people who had the right to interfere with our tents and nightly bivouacs were the police—die Polizei. No mere private individual or gamekeeper could ever turn us off.

On previous trips, when we camped too near the towns, die Polizei often came to ask us what our business was. Often, too, they were very disagreeable and troublesome, poking about in our tents, searching through our kit in the boat, evidently suspicious that we were spies of some kind. Sometimes they asked if we were gypsies (for in Germany and Austria the gypsies are very numerous and troublesome, and the law does not allow them to camp for more than a single night in any one place); and sometimes—very rarely—they grasped the fact that we were merely a party of quiet Englander enjoying a holiday. But in every case we had learned that our best plan was to be very polite and quiet with them, to show them our things readily, and to answer all their (often stupid) questions without demur, because if we made them angry they had the nght to arrest us, to seize our baggage, and to hold us in the local lockup until by one way or another we had proved to their satisfaction that we were really what we said we were—innocent holidaymakers. Of course, nothing serious could have happened to us, but the delay would have been extremely annoying, and the night in the village lockup, instead of under the stars, would have been, no doubt, too horrible to contemplate!

This year we had got a long way down the river from Ulm (Bavaria), and had enjoyed a dozen camps unmolested by anyone, so that we began to think we should escape visits from die Polizei altogether perhaps. The river was in flood and we travelled very fast, and took pains to camp as far away from towns and villages as possible, so that our fires and our little white tents should not attract attention.

This, however, was not always possible, and one night we were fairly caught. All day long a head wind had delayed us, and made paddling a weariness to the flesh. The map showed a long string of villages for a dozen miles or more, no one village being far enough from the next one to ensure a really safe and quiet camp. Then, for a mile or two, the current slowed down too, and this sealed our fate definitely, for it meant that we could not hope to get free of the villages before dark. And, after dark, no man in his senses would care to paddle down a river like the Danube in flood.

So we made the best of a bad job and, choosing the most deserted bit of ground we could find, we pitched our camp a short hour before sunset on the right bank, and made cosy for the night. Opposite us, on the other shore, were the houses of a long, straggling village, but, though the river was swift and as much as three-quarters of a mile wide, there was a rope-ferry, which enabled people to go to and fro without much difficulty. Thus, although our own bank was deserted—consisting of fields and rows of willow-bushes close to the water—we did not feel very secure from interruption.

We made a small fire for cooking, put up one tent for the ladies to sleep in, and hauled the boat high up the shingly shore to be safe in case the river rose farther in the night. My cousin and myself decided not to put up our own tent, but to use it as a sleeping-bag We often did this on hot nights, and very easy it was. By spreading our cork mattresses on one side of the tent, we could draw the other side over us lke a blanket. It was waterproof and kept out the dew, and was so large that we had far more room to turn about in than if the tent were standing. It made a giant sleeping-bag.

Wood was rather scarce, and we had to hunt about a good deal to collect enough to make the fire last till bedtime, but otherwise there was nothing against the camp, and it was no worse and no better than a dozen others.

Just before reaching this place we had passed a large quarry in the hills, and now, as we cooked our evening meal, we saw the men coming home from their work on the opposite shore. They passed along in straggling fashion for the best part of an hour, and some of them, seeing our smoke, shouted to us across the water and asked us laughingly if we had got leave to camp. One man in particular stood for a long time and shouted at us. He asked if we had the necessary papers and passports, and what we should have to say when the police came to turn us off, and a lot more besides that the great width of the river only just enabled us to hear. Naturally, we took no notice of any of them, but just went on with our cooking as though we did not hear them, and when the dusk came down and hid the opposite shore in shadows, they all moved on to the little inn half a mile lower down and left us in peace. We felt sure, however, that we had not seen the end of them.

“They’ll come across and pay us a visit after supper,” said my cousin, “if only for curiosity, and to see who we are and what we’re doing.”

“Probably,” I made answer. “We’ve camped too near the ferry. But they won’t stay long. Those fellows work too hard, and have to get up too early in the morning to sit up late.”

And come they did, though not exactly in the way we meant.

It was about nine o’clock when we first heard steps on the grass behind our camp. The ferry was round the bend of the river, just out of sight, and we had not seen it come across, but we found out later that it had brought over a load of a dozen men, most of whom were at that minute standing behind the willow-bushes watching us as we lay smoking and chatting round the camp fire. It was difficult for us to see anything outside the circle of the blazing wood.

“Hulloa!” exclaimed my cousin, “here they are at last!”

We all looked up and saw a couple of men enter the circle of light. The one in front was a fine-looking fellow, who held himself like an officer; he had a red beard and was smartly dressed, and he was followed closely by another man in a sort of peasant’s overall. The man with the red beard drew his heels together with snap and saluted.

“Good evening,” he said in German. “Have you got your papers of identification? Kindly show them.”

“It’s the police,” whispered my cousin’s wife, turning to her husband, who, suspecting nothing, began laboriously to produce his passport from the leather pocket of his belt. He handed it across the fire to the man, who stooped down and held it close to the flames for inspection.

At first, apparently, he could rot make head or tail of it, for he turned it over and over, upside down and sideways, in his endeavour to decipher the English sentences; but a passport, especially one that has been much viséd, is a formidable-looking document, and a local country policeman who had never seen one before might well be excused for being somewhat puzzled what to make of it. The man studied it for some minutes in silence.

“It’s a passport,” I explained in German, “signed by the Minister of Foreign Affairs and viséd by the consuls of the various countries we have passed through.”

The red-bearded man looked up sharply.

“It’s not sufficient,” he said. “You must produce something more than this. This does not identify you.”

The tone in which he spoke betrayed at once that he wished to make things awkward for us, and that he had come with that intention. At the same time something about his voice and manner roused my suspicions. In almost every case previously the police had been amply satisfied with a passport. It rather impressed them as a rule. This man was so very quick to object and find fault, and for some reason it struck me as a little overdone.

“We are English people,” I explained, “and we are making a holiday trip down the river to Buda-pesth. These papers are all we have, and they have always been held sufficient by the police everywhere. What more do you want?”

The man turned with a quick look to his companion who stood close behind him, and said something in patois we could not understand. The second man shrugged his shoulders.

“This paper is not enough,” he said brusquely, standing upright and fixing me with his eye. “It does not tell sufficient about you. You cannot travel here—in this part of Bavaria—without proper papers. I fear it will be my duty to hold you till the Commissaire comes up from Regensburg. I regret it, but I cannot let you pass. You would only be stopped at Regensburg, even if I did.”

This time the man had said too much. He had quite overdone his part. I knew the police at Regensburg from the experiences of a former trip. They were the most polite and reasonable people in the world, and, instead of asking for papers, they volunteered all sorts of useful information about the river, with advice where to camp, and what dangerous rapids to look out for, etc. I was quite certain then that the man’s sole object was to extort a good fat tip on the plea of allowing us to proceed. And the group of men standing on the grass behind were watching the fun. They were the quarrymen who had seen us pass in the afternoon, and had shouted across the river to us. When we had paid the ten marks to be left in peace they would retire to the inn and roar over their successful joke with unlimited beer and sausages at our expense.

At the moment, however, I did not feel positive of my suspicions. It was never wise to be too certain in a foreign country.

“Are you from the police?” I asked suddenly.

“Of course I am,” he said with a snap.

“But the police wear uniform. I know them well. They are always very polite and intelligent, whereas you—you have no uniform at all,” I said.

“I belong to the Strand Polizei (river police), who are always in plain clothes,” he answered, quick as a flash.

The answer came a little too pat, and made me suspect a lesson carefully learned in the beer-room of the inn where the plot had been hatched. But, of course, I could not be sure yet of my suspicions.

“I have been down the Danube before,” I said, “and have made friends with the police all the way down; but I never heard of the Strand Polizei before.”

“Our duties are to watch the banks and to prevent trespassing, and see that no damage is done. Fires, for instance”—here he pointed to ours—“are not permitted at all. And your explanation of a holiday trip is not enough. It will be my duty to detain you.”

“Rot! Tommyrot!” I heard my cousin whisper in my ear, and, indeed, all that the man said was so utterly contrary to our former experience with the police, that I now felt more certain than ever it was all a clumsy plot to get money out of us.

“All right,” I said, “then if you wish to arrest us you are at liberty to do so. We have shown our papers and given sufficient explanation. You can take the risk of holding us if you wish. We are quite at your disposal.”

The man stared hard at me for a moment, as though hardly knowing what to say. His companion muttered something in patois of which the only word I caught was “Regensburg.” (Regensburg was a couple of miles farther down the river.)

“Precisely,” he said at length; “I must detain you here while I go back across the river to telephone to my Commissaire at Regensburg. He will send me instructions what to do with you—” His change of plan, though very quick and adroit, of course, did not escape us.

“Better hurry up, or he may have taken his hot bath and gone to bed,” interrupted my cousin, but in such bad German that the man did not understand, and evidently imagined that his words had produced the desired impression of alarm.

“Only I must first examine your boat,” he added, and moved down towards the bank. I then noticed for the first time that he walked unsteadily. He had evidently been drinking.

“You will do nothing of the sort,” I said, jumping up and moving in front of him. “You are no more a policeman than I am. You have shown no proof of your identity. You have produced no papers.”

The shot told. The red-bearded man and his companion hesitated a moment, measuring myself and my cousin who stood before them with their eyes. The sight of two six-foot Englishmen, perhaps, did not invite an attempt at violence. Anyhow, they did nothing. The fact that they made no effort to arrest us themselves, but pretended they must wait instructions from their chief, convinced me finally beyond all possible doubt that they were humbugs.

“I shall go at once and telephone to Regensburg,” said the man, though with much less assurance, “and later we shall come back together and arrest you.”

“We shall expect you when we see you,” I made reply with a laugh, “and what is more, I shall report, to the Regensburg police that two of the workmen from the quarry came to our camp and impersonated the police and made threats. I shall describe you so that you will be easily recognised.”

“Good night,” said the man, saluting, and paying no attention to my words. “Good night; we shall be back again in a couple of hours, and you will be arrested.” And they were gone, my cousin and I following them at a distance through the darkness, and just making out the group of men that joined them behind the willow bushes and made off to the ferry with them.

For another half-hour we heard their voices, growing fainter and fainter as they floated to us across the river. We heard the booming sound the great wooden ferry made as it landed on the rocks, and then the voices and shouting of the men died away as they returned to their beer in the inn and discussed the details of a plot that failed.

“We shan’t see him again,” I said with a laugh, as I piled the wood on for a final blaze before turning in. “And his pals will make endless fun of him, I expect, for playing his cards so badly. No doubt they expected at least a twenty-mark piece.”

But when, half an hour later, the women-folk had gone to their tent, and my cousin and I were sitting round the dying embers for a last pipe he turned to me and said suggestively:

“I think we ought to sleep with one eye open tonight, don’t you?” He jerked his head in the direction of the opposite bank, where the sounds of the men’s voices at the inn were still faintly audible.

“You think they’ll try something else on?” I asked. “You think they might come back, perhaps?”

“Not with the police, of course; that was all humbug, but out of revenge they’d play us a trick if they could.”

“I suppose they feel rather foolish, yes. Still, I hardly see what they could do.”

“I shall sleep in my clothes all the same,” he said, “to be ready for them if they do come.”

So that night we both crawled into our great cosy sleeping-bag with all our clothes on. There was no danger of the fire spreading, and for some time we watched the glow it threw on the leaves of the willow bushes. The sky was cloudless and a crescent moon hung over the tops of the hills across the river. We heard the dull roar of the rushing water at our feet and looked up at the stars, thinking of our journey on the following day. Already the outside cover of our tent was wet with dew, and a dozen yards away we saw the white shape of the other tent glistening faintly in the last rays of the moon before it sank below the hills. A dreadful sleepiness came over me. It was all very well to talk of sleeping with one eye open; that is easier said than done after twelve strenuous hours in the open air, and before eleven o’clock sounded from the church tower across the river I had slipped away into the regions of utter forgetfulness, and was so soundly asleep that I think nothing short of a tidal wave or a cannonball whizzing over the willow bushes behind could have made me stir a muscle.

The next thing I knew was that something warm and soft lay tightly over my mouth. I struggled and sat up. It was my cousin’s hand. His face was close to mine in the darkness.

“Hush,” he whispered softly, “don’t make a sound. There’s somebody about the camp.”

In an instant my senses were alert and I was wide awake.

“Those fellows have come back?” I whispered. And he nodded his head by way of reply. “I think so,” he said under his breath. “I’ve heard movements for some time. There’s someone quite close.”

The night was very dark, for the moon had disappeared below the hills and there was only the light of the stars. We lay still and listened, and after a bit my eyes got more accustomed to the gleam, and I made out the line of hills and the outline of the other tent. The fire had long since gone out. It was after two in the morning.

Almost immediately I heard sounds of rustling in the willow bushes behind us, and the same-minute two dark forms moved stealthily out and stood looking down at us a few feet away. We lay absolutely still. The men were evidently waiting to see that we were asleep, for after several minutes’ inspection they moved past us on tiptoe, and made their way down very softly towards the river. My companion nudged me under the blankets, and approached his head cautiously towards mine.

“They’re going to the boat,” he whispered, and then lay stock still again with a quick “Look out!” in my ear, for a third figure issued at the same moment from the trees, and walked close past us after the other two. Our movement, however, had been so slight that in the darkness the man had failed to note it, and the figure disappeared among the shadows of the river edge. Then followed a slight rattling noise as though the chain that held the boat was being very carefully moved over the shingle.

My cousin leaned over quickly and whispered again in my ear.

“They’re going to steal the boat,” he said. “Grab a stick, and let’s make a rush at them. Hit anything you see and shout at the top of your voice. We’ll scare the impudent rascals to death.”

The same second we both leaped out of our blankets. My cousin seized the heavy six-foot paddle which always lay beside us in the night, and I grabbed the first thing I could find in the darkness—a stout iron rod, with a hook at one end and a sharp point at the other. It was the iron rod we used to hang the kettles over the fire, and a very formidable weapon indeed.

Thus armed, we ran down in the direction of the boat, shouting lustily with a noise to wake the dead. And at the same instant the women in the other tent (who, it appeared, had heard the sounds for some time and were thoroughly frightened) put their heads out of the door-flaps and sent a series of high-pitched and wild screams into the night that woke the echoes from the opposite hills, and must have made all who heard them think that at least murder was being done. I never heard such a sudden burst of sound as the combined noise of our shouting and their screaming, and to think of it to this day makes me roar with laughter.

What the men thought I have no conception. Everything happened so quickly, and there was such a scurrying of feet over the shingle and up towards the shelter of the bushes, that in the darkness it was impossible to know what was going on or who was who. I only know that we saw the three men on the edge of the river by our boat, and that two of them who stood pushing her off into the water, stopped, caught in the act, and dashed past us like winged shadows, but very noisy and frightened shadows! And that as they tore past us my cousin raised his huge paddle and caught one of them such a crack in the back that the sound of it lives in my memory to this day.

The force of the swing, however, upset his balance, and as he lay struggling on the shingle, the second man tripped and fell across him, so that for several seconds I was afraid to use my iron hook for fear of hitting my cousin instead of the rascally thief. In a few seconds, however, they disentangled themselves, and the first German ruffian was on his feet and away, and though I was too late to sting up the second one in the back as I should have liked to do, I was just in the nick of time to catch his flying foot with the hook end of my iron, so that he landed upon his face with a crash that must have loosened every tooth in his head.

In a second he was up again, and in another second down again, for the hook caught the same foot—by pure luck, for it was too dark, and I was too flustered to aim correctly—and he sprawled on the stones, puffing and shouting in his unintelligible patois, as though all the demons from the underworld were after him. The third time, however, he got up again with such a terrific spring in his terror, and made so furious a lunge forward, that the force and weight of his leg drew the iron out of my hand, and I heard him thrashing away down the stony beach, with the rod clanking and rattling at his heels, until at last he got free of its clutch, and made off over the fields in final escape.

The second man, meanwhile, had made good his escape into the darkness without a scratch, and at that minute, to our great delight, the women-folk came running down from their tent with a couple of lanterns. They had recovered from their fright at the sound of our laughter, and had pluckily done the very thing that was best. And the first thing we saw in the glare of the two lanterns was the figure of the red-bearded man standing sheepishly and foolishly in the boat, unable to escape past us by the shore, and equally unable to escape by way of the river, because the chain was still fast to the pegs that held it to the bank.

For a second we all stood and stared at him. Then, with a shout, my cousin dashed into the boat, and, talking the worst German I have ever heard in the whole course of my life, explained to the man that he was a rascal and a thief, and that we had caught him in the act of stealing, and he must now accept the consequences of his acts.

The man said no word in reply. He made one dash for the shore-end of the boat, but my cousin was too quick for him, and had him round the waist in a twinkling. A second later that red-bearded German was dipped, struggling, fighting, kicking, shouting, spluttering, into the cold water of the rushing Danube. I stood by ready to help if necessary, but my cousin was far more than a match for the beery Teuton and needed no assistance, so that I stood on the bank holding the lantern and shaking with laughter till I thought I should drop.

Three times he went under the water, and three times came up gasping and spitting, and would doubtless have undergone his well-earned punishment a fourth time, but for the intervention of my cousin’s wife, who was so afraid that the man would slip from the arms that held him and be drowned, that she begged her husband to desist.

“Now you’ve had your bath you may go,” he shouted at him; but the grammar was so bad that the wretched man did not understand what was meant, and evidently thought something more was in store for him. My cousin accordingly took him by the hand and led his dripping figure off the boat, and pointing towards the ferry (where, doubtless, lay the boat that had brought them all across) told him to get home to bed as quickly as he could.

“And tomorrow,” I added, “we shall inform the police at Regensburg of your wickedness, for you not only impersonated the police, with the clear intention getting money, but you also deliberately came back to steal our boat in the night.”

The man went off with a sploshy sound of dripping clothes, his boots making & noise like sponges, and was soon lost in the darkness.

By this time all desire to sleep had left us. There was a faint red glow in the east already, and the morning air was fresh and cool.

“Let’s make coffee and strike camp,” I suggested, and all agreed.

An hour later, under the grey dawn, we were whizzing again down the swift Danube, and two hours more saw us watching the sunrise several miles below Regensburg; for we considered that, on the whole, the red-bearded man had been sufficiently punished, and we did not land to inform the police as we had threatened. We learn later, however, that there is no such thing at all as the Strand Polizei, and that if any man along the river shores came up and pretended to belong to the police the proper thing to do was to ask him to show his Polizei Anweta (police badge), without which “none are genuine.”

Petershin and Mr. Snide

Petershin, a retired Insurance Surveyor, had always nursed a private terror that one day the night express would catch him on a level crossing, that his foot would get jammed between the rails, and that he would not have the courage to saw it off with his penknife.

This secret dread had haunted his mind since childhood.

Owing to circumstances that need no particular mention at the moment, he let out his secret one evening to a valued acquaintance. He spoke of it, in some detail, to John Snide, a bookseller in a small way and a publisher of occasional pamphlets, a married man of education and authority.

“Really, Petershin,” observed Mr. Snide. “Now, that’s very odd. It’s a coincidence, I might say. For, d’you know, now that you mention it, I may say I’ve always had a similar dread myself.” He took off his glasses and wiped them thoughtfully.

“No,” exclaimed Petershin with lively interest. “Have you really?” He was relieved to find that his terror was not so peculiar after all that no one else could share it. Raising his eyebrows he listened attentively.

“I have, indeed,” Mr. Snide assured his friend. “Only in my case”—he put his glasses on his nose and looked over them at his companion—“in my case Petershin, there’s—a difference.” He was addressing, of course, an inferior fellow.

Both voice and manner betrayed a slight suggestion of superiority, as though it would hardly do to feel precisely what the other felt. Apparently, a shade more value had to be inserted.

Petershin accepted the slight rebuke. “A difference, Mr. Snide!” he echoed, as one whom a fellow-sympathy made intelligently understanding. That he was accustomed to keep his place was conveyed in the familiar yet respectful “Mr.”

“In my own case,” resumed the other, nodding with what he might have called, had he been pressed, a “soupçon” of advantage, “the difference is, that, while my foot will be jammed somewhat as you describe, I shall have,” he went on carelessly, “no penknife on me.” “Really! Now, if that isn’t peculiar!” declared Petershin, where an inferior mind must have phrased it “Well—I’m damned!” He hoped he had suitably conveyed the admiration of his friend’s courage.

Mr. Snide nodded with comfortable assurance, and the talk, thus begun, continued volubly for an hour or so, Mrs. Snide not being in the particular building at the time. …

Petershin liked Mr. Snide. He rather looked up to him as being a cultured man, learned in books, even something of a scholar. The way he quoted from authors proved this. He saw little of him, however, because he was afraid of Mrs. Snide, whom he considered “too particular.” Once or twice he had gone into the shop, just a little before lunch time, and had invited Mr. Snide to join him in a few minutes’ stroll, and Mrs. Snide had distinctly mentioned that it was inconvenient—“Gentlemen didn’t go for a stroll just before mealtime—when it was raining.” She had noticed, too, his celluloid collar, with a remark he did not quite catch, but an unfavourable remark, he felt sure; because, later, when Petershin advised Mr. Snide to use one, the latter said: “Yes, Petershin, they are practical, I admit, and a saving too, no doubt, but—er—the wife thinks they’re not quite the thing for me, being—as I might say—among books, you see.”

“Reelly they don’t catch fire,” explained Petershin eagerly, not understanding at first what was meant. “There’s not the smallest danger of that sort—”

“A man—the wife holds—is what he wears,” Mr. Snide interrupted him.

From which moment Petershin despised and feared Mrs. Snide, realising that she was “too particular.” The phrase, moreover, was obviously a quotation from some book, and a quotation from a great author invariably overwhelmed Petershin with a painful sense of his own inferiority, reducing him to an uncomfortable and admiring silence.

Mrs. Snide, Petershin had ascertained, disapproved of him for another reason than that of his external appearance, for her husband had been detained one night, getting home at 3 a.m., to be exact—and his explanation had not quite satisfied “the wife.”

“Oh, I was out with an insurance man,” he said. “A surveyor, my dear,” he added, when pressed, “with Mr. Petershin, in fact.”

That was all Mr. Snide said; but, apparently, his wife had said a good deal more. Mr. Snide had mentioned the matter to him afterwards—briefly. Wherefore it was that Petershin did not see as much of his friend as he would have liked to see, and was, in addition, rather afraid of Mrs. Snide.

The tendency to coincidence already mentioned continued, nevertheless, to bring the two acquaintances together by chance, finding both, as if by chance again, affected by a similar, or as Mr. Snide might have said, an identical emotion. This emotion they shared accordingly, exchanging confidences, as two intelligent men will when actuated by the same desire simultaneously. Yielding to Mrs. Snide’s disapproval, however, they were cautious in the matter of referring to these chance meetings afterwards—at least Mr. Snide was, being a tactful and experienced man. Nor again, respecting Mrs. Snide’s wishes, did they meet before a meal. Petershin no longer called at the shop just before luncheon for a little stroll. It was usually after dinner that the spirit of confidence brought one across the other’s path.

These occasions began invariably with Petershin’s saying invitingly:

“Now, here we are! And what’s it going to be, Mr. Snide? Eh?”

They ended invariably with an observation from Mr. Snide—much later:

“Well—I’ll be getting on, Petershin. Time slips away on rapid wing. The wife’ll be expecting me,” a glance at his friend’s collar conveying the hint that its wearer was not expected to accompany him, and the quotation, if it were such, having its invariable effect.

One of these occasions, however, though inaugurated by Petershin’s usual greeting, did not end quite according to formula, the reason being that Mrs. Snide had gone to the country to see her mother who was very ill, and had telegraphed that her return that night was uncertain: “Mother very gravely ill indeed may not be back tonight. Ada.”

“Dear me,” offered Petershin, by way of sympathy. “Worse, is she?”

“Much worse, yes, apparently,” replied Mr. Snide. “In fact, I might say, dying.”

“Dear me, dear me!” repeated the other, his voice lower, his eyebrows higher. “Is she reelly?”

“I’m afraid so,” was Mr. Snide’s considered opinion, given slowly and repeated for the sake of emphasis. “I’m afraid she is.” He reflected a moment, idly fingering a glass that happened to be near his hand, then adding as a result of his reflection: “I might say I’m sure of it.” And immediately thereafter, before his friend could offer anything further by way of condolence, he brushed the entire matter from his mind with a free gesture of the hand and elbow, and invited Petershin to join him in the discussion of the various interests they possessed in common.

“For why meet trouble halfway?” he added, as an afterthought. “A wise man should float above sorrow and keep his head well above water always.”

“Say when,” Petershin interrupted, happening to be pouring out some water at the moment.

“And that’s courage, it seems to me?” the other finished his sentence, ignoring the interruption, though quickly holding up two fingers in an absentminded yet peremptory manner.

“It is indeed,” concurred Petershin sympathetically, and with a touch of respect due to his persuasion that he had listened to a quotation from some famous author. “That is courage, yes,” he repeated, adding with a slight inconsequence, “Here’s to you, sir!” Whereupon the conversation led easily into exchanges of a personal, even of a confidential nature, the two friends being evidently in a chatty and exuberant mood that favoured such intimate exchanges. …

Outside, the weather was cold and dreary, a bitter wind from the north threatening snow. Darkness had fallen, as with a clap of suddenness, before its time. It was inclement weather, as Mr. Snide might have said, or, as Petershin in other company would have described it—filthy. Unfavourable, anyhow, each felt in his own particular way, to Mrs. Snide’s mother.

“No weather for an invalid, Mr. Snide, this—is it?” was what Petershin remarked, to which the other replied briefly but with energy, indeed, with gusto, as he might have said—“dangerous, I call it dangerous.”

Both references, it is seen, were indirect; an allusion of sympathy to the illness, each felt, was proper and desirable, while yet it need not detain them. There were other matters to discuss. … The sense of leisure was pleasant, the warmth of the room was comfortable, each man found the other’s conversation stimulating. Ideas certainly flowed. The hours slipped easily away. …

It was Petershin who made the first move to leave: “You’ll be getting anxious, Mr. Snide,” he observed. “I mushtn’t keep you up.” He crossed cautiously to the window and, wiping the moisture off with the curtain, peered out into the night. “Shnowing, by gad!” he exclaimed. “Shnowing thickanfasht!” His manner held an unaccustomed dignity. It was a stiff, exaggerated dignity.

Behind his back Mr. Snide, first looking at his watch, replied easily, as one who is master of circumstances: “Not a bit, Petershin. Be an optimist, my lad. Those whom the gods love die young—”

“But, I tell you it is,” interrupted Petershin brusquely, thinking his veracity was called in question. “Evershings white already. The air’s thick with it. Like a Chrismhascard.” Then, returning to his seat, he caught his companion’s powerful eye fixed on him. “Mr. Shnide,” he added, with an effort, “beg pardon, but it izsch—reelly.” He sat down, fumbling with his watch. He did not want a disagreement with his superior friend. He made no further comment.

“The nightsh still young,” Mr. Snide mentioned presently. “Let it snow. Wha’dowe care, Pee’shin?”

And they chatted on for another timeless interval. …

“Shtill snowing, I igspec’,” Petershin offered in the middle of something Mr. Snide was saying with great deliberation. He had not gone to the window to look. It was merely that Mr. Snide had been talking for a very long time about a “sosh’listic pamphlet” he was publishing, and that he, Petershin, had the impression it was time for him to say something by way of comment. Only, not having listened attentively, he could find no “reelly” intelligent comment.

Mr. Snide paused, glowering heavily at him.

“To hell withyer shnow” he said angrily. “You’ve not been lis’ning to what I washayin.” And before Petershin could find a tactful answer by way of soothing him, Mr. Snide looked at his watch, rose from his chair, stood for a moment hesitating, and then abruptly sat down again, a broad smile upon his face,

“Pe’ershin, my boy, the night is young,” he said with the emphasis of one who knows. His momentary annoyance was quite forgotten. “Time wearsh along, but the night, I shure you, ish still young. And Mrs. Shnide is far from—far from ’ome.”

Petershin agreed with a nod. It was partly a quotation.

An hour later, when they rose to take their leave (as Mr. Snide might have said, but did not actually say), the driving snow was so thick in their faces and upon the ground that Mr. Snide, catching his companion by the arm with delightful friendliness, observed:

“We’ll take zhe shor’cut. Thaswashwe’ll do. An’ you come to my placesh. Accept my hospital’ty for the night. I’ll put you up, Pe’shin. She’s probly dead. Sh’ll right, old boy. The godsh love thoshwho die young.”

“No thanksh,” Petershin replied with dignity, “prefer to be excushed,” but, perhaps yielding to the spell of the quotation about the gods, he accompanied Mr. Snide forthwith arm in arm, into the inclement snowstorm.

It was what Snide might have called “reelly a heavy storm.” Thick snow swirled about them, drove into their faces, plastered their clothes with big clinging flakes, so that in five minutes they were white from head to foot. They panted with effort. It was no time for speech. Petershin, blindly confident in his friend’s leadership, ploughed forward heavily. No other pedestrians were out on such a night. They passed no single person, and the snow lay six inches deep upon the ground. It was the wind, of course, that made them sway.

To Mr. Snide first occurred the idea of calling a halt to recover breath; he accompanied the action with an observation of some violence which his companion did not quite catch.

“Pardon?” bawled Petershin, looking up a second into a red face whose eyebrows and moustache were hung with white dripping flakes.

“Thisis an orspishcashun,” roared Mr. Snide, but again the words were whirled from his lips by the tremendous wind. He stood with his back to the gusts, Petershin facing him.

“Can’t hear wotyoushay,” yelled the latter, and then turned his back to the storm. He now stood sideways to his friend, and being sheltered a little he glanced up and repeated very loudly “What?”

Mr. Snide roared back at him: “I only said orspishcashun”—the wind again whipping the syllables into space, while at the same time it upset his balance a trifle, so that he reeled slightly towards his companion. They collided, in fact, though speedily separating themselves again and standing upright.

“Ver’ sorry,” screamed Petershin, still anxious to hear what the lost sentence was, but feeling the fault lay with himself. “Awf’ly sorry, but I didn’t qui’ hear.” He glanced up at the same time, and the red face he saw, plastered with wet snow, the hat crooked and the end of a necktie sticking up through the coat collar towards the mouth, made such a funny picture that he burst suddenly into a spasm of uncontrollable laughter.

“Woshthematter, you idjiut?” cried Mr. Snide, suddenly angry. “I only said that was an”—he articulated very clearly, roaring his syllables against the storm—“orspishush’cashun. What the devil—” Petershin’s laughter died away on the instant. “Oh,” he yelled back. “Pardon me, Mr. Snide. Awspishush ’casion, yes. So it is. Qui’ right, of course.” It cost him a prodigious effort, but the words, despite the wicked wind, rang true and clear.

“Tha’s woshIsaid,” came back the angry roar. “Why don’ you liss’n?”

Petershin, crestfallen and ashamed, tried to pull himself together, and as the mental effort involved also the physical effort of standing erect, he was surprised to find that there was something the matter with his feet. With one foot, that is. The left foot refused to follow the right. Mr. Snide, he became aware, was standing on it. It was an awkward moment. He did not quite like to mention it, but neither did he quite like to push Mr. Snide away. He wriggled. Nothing happened. Again he wriggled—furiously. It was no good. Mr. Snide was firmly planted apparently on his left foot. Petershin, still wriggling, was in the act of losing his balance altogether, when suddenly his companion stepped aside with a curiously unnatural movement. A clear space of two feet now lay between the two men; Mr. Snide could not possibly still be standing on his companion’s left foot and yet that left foot would not budge.

Petershin struggled. Mr. Snide, he perceived, was struggling too. Each man, apparently, was making violent efforts to extricate his foot from the clutch of deep snow that somehow held it. Each had one leg stretched out stiff and straight at an awkward angle that provided leverage. But Petershin was the first to realise what had happened. He was the first to put it into words at any rate:

“Me foo’s cau’,” he gasped.

At the same moment both men lost their balance and fell sideways into a deep white drift.

Petershin, again, was the first to pick himself up—into a sitting position. He brushed the snow violently from his person. Immediately opposite to him, about three feet away, he stared into a red face with glaring, bloodshot eyes, cheeks, moustache and eyebrows caked with white, necktie askew, and one arm gesticulating vehemently in the air. For a second the impulse to burst out laughing was very strong, for Mr. Snide’s appearance was grotesque beyond description. The same instant, however, the laughter died away in his throat. His friend was bawling something at him. The words were thick—with snow and wind. They horrified him:

“Me foo’s cau’ too! We’re on the ra’way track God shave us!”

The dreadful situation produced one immediate effort—both men found their mother tongue and were able to use it without difficulty, and simultaneously. They recovered their lost distinctness of utterance. Mr. Snide in particular, having the louder voice of the two, dropped his pose of quoting from better minds than his own, and became at once natural and sincere:

“You damned idjiut,” he roared. “What possessed you to ta’ the shor’ cu’ on a night like this?” He stood upright again, after a tremendous struggle. He shook his fist, lost his balance in doing so, and collapsed again into the snow, still shouting as he floundered.

“You led me into this,” Petershin was shouting simultaneously. “It was your damfool s’gesstion.”

Then he collapsed beside him and, like two violent turkeys beating furious wings, or two veterans in a three-legged race with ankles fastened together, they made the snow fly in all directions, pulling vainly at each other in their attempts to rise, roaring imprecations while they did so. It was a grotesque and painful sight. Breathless at last, with right hands clasped for a final pull, arms taut and shoulders braced, there came a pause.

“Now,” cried Mr. Snide. “Are you ready? One, two, and—away!”

They rose together as though a spring released them. Facing each other in a standing position, as if they were shaking hands, Petershin then turned his head sideways a moment and listened. A sound came to him that was not the wind.

“Snide!” he screamed. “It’s the ni’ express!” “And me foo’sstill cau’!” both roared in the same breath.

In the distance was a faint glimmer of reddish light just visible through the driving flakes. It was growing larger, brighter. There was a deep sound like thunder. It was growing every second louder. And, without a word at first, both figures stooped, bent double, fumbling at their feet with frozen fingers that were all thumbs.

“Lend me yo’ penknife,” both shouted frantically together.

“Lef’ it at home,” bawled two minds with but a single thought.

“Got a match?” yelled Snide. “Li’ it at once. Li’ a bit o’ paper, can’t you?” Petershin did not answer. Not even an oilcan could have burned in such a wind.

“Cut the laces!” It was Petershin’s generous idea. He suddenly shoved an open penknife at his friend, as though he wished to stab him.

“Good man!” Snide seized it and made frantic slashes at his imprisoned boot.

“Hurry up, for God’s sake! Haven’t done me own yet!” from Petershin.

The red light had come much closer, the roar of the approaching train already shook the ground and made the metals tremble.

“Lemme do it for you,” bawled Snide. “I’m free!” He leant over, he bent himself double, his arm was stretched towards his friend’s boot, but in the attempt he lost his balance and fell—outwards, away from the track. At the same instant, when the awful engine was not ten yards from where he had been standing, Petershin, making a desperate wrench of final, superhuman, almost acrobatic violence, extricated his own foot too. The wind from the engine flung him with violence against Mr. Snide’s prostrate body. His foot had torn loose, leaving the boot tight in the rails beneath the thundering wheels. It was an effort that would have surprised an osteopath.

The night express, oblivious of two human hearts within an inch of its flying mass, roared past into the darkness and, light, thunder, rattle, bulk and all, was lost in the storm. The wind and flakes resumed their unchallenged occupancy of the night.

“Get orf of me, you lout!” was the first sound audible, after the bang and clatter were gone. It was Mr. Snide’s voice, muffled by something that impeded clear utterance. A big, white, shapeless substance rolled slowly to one side—and Petershin stood up. “It passed right over us—I do believe,” he gasped.

“Are we alive?” He felt himself over. A second shapeless white mass rose gradually beside him. “I am,” it shouted. “But no thanks to you!”

From the path of a slow-moving luggage train on the other track where they were now standing, they moved shakily aside. The great, endless thing went lumbering past them with convulsions, jolting and shuddering, the enormous tarpaulins over the piled-up freight looking like white mammoths galloping on short legs and with hidden heads, back to the shelter of their primeval forests.

The two men watched it slowly vanish. For a long time neither spoke a word. The appalling fate they had escaped left them half-stunned.

“Have you done with my penknife—Mr. Snide?” Petershin enquired presently, shouting as usual to make himself heard. Mr. Snide replied that he had and added “Thank you” while a search for the knife began, ending some minutes later by its being discovered still tightly clasped in the right hand of the man whose life it had undoubtedly saved.

“With many thanks,” repeated Mr. Snide, more composedly now. He handed over the object with a mixture of carelessness and empressement in his manner.

“Don’t mention it, please,” said Petershin. Both men were very shaky still. Indeed, they were trembling. But recovery was on the way.

The search for two boots then followed. Of these, however, little remained beyond the soles and some scraps of frayed laces. Wearing these sandal-wise, and complaining bitterly of the cold, the two friends eventually resumed their journey arm-in-arm. They spoke little.

“I—er—should like to say thank you,” repeated Mr. Snide, as they presently reached the comparative shelter of the houses. “Your knife—the loan of it—was a great help to me. So small a thing can change the waysh of fate! Indeed, I might say—”

“Oh, please. It’s nothing, Mr. Snide,” interrupted Petershin. “Only too glad I had it with me—after all.”

“I might say,” continued the other, ignoring the interruption, “that it saved my life.” He pressed his friend’s hand, as they reached the door. A lump rose in Petershin’s throat. He was not far from tears. The proximity of the forbidden door, however, exercised a sobering effect. Mrs. Snide, of course, might have returned, he reflected. He paused inside the iron garden gate, then made a move as though to go.

“One minute,” enjoined Mr. Snide, observing his hesitation, but sympathetically. “Allow me,” he added in the tone of a host, as he passed in front and inserted his latchkey with some difficulty. The proprietor pushed open his faded blue door and turned up the light in the little hall. His sandal had slipped off, but he did not notice it perhaps, as he moved on tiptoe to the table below the hat-rack where a telegram was visible.

Petershin, watching him from the snowy step with anxlous eyes, was not even aware that his left foot was freezing in the icy slush. He picked up his friend’s lost sandal and laid it cautiously inside the passage.

“One minute,” enjoined Mr. Snide, glancing back over his shoulder as a man who hesitates between authority and subservience. He opened the telegram. “Ah!” he ejaculated, tapping it like an actor then reading it again a little closer to the light. “It’s or’ ri’,” he added, a happy smile spreading across his red face.

“I beg your pardon?” offered Petershin, choosing the longer form to gain time. Usually he was content with “pardon.” He wished to make quite sure,

“It’s or’ ri’, I said,” repeated Mr. Snide briefly, “Come in, Pe’shin, come in, lad.” He hung his hat up with an air.

Petershin advanced slowly into the forbidden hall. “Vour wife, I trust—?” He meant to ask after the wife’s mother, but his mind was a trifle confused, it seems. “Everything’s s’asfactry, I hope?” he faltered.

His host turned round and gazed at him, an expression of false gravity unable to mask the smile of genial hospitality that overpowered it.

“Qui’ or’ ri’, thank you,” he replied. “Hang yer hat up!” He moved past and closed the door with a bang that echoed through the house and made Petershin jump. “It’s an inclement night. I’ll get some shlippers.” “Thank you, thank you,” murmured Petershin, shaking the snow from his hat, but still hesitating before he hung it up as bidden. “And your mother-in-law,” he hastened to correct his little mistake. “I trust—?”

“It’s or’ ri’, I’ve told you once,” was the reply, given with some impatience. “She’s dead. And my wife returns in the morning. Now, please make yourself at home, Pe’shin, my lad.”

Petershin attempted a hasty calculation in his mind, but failed to arrive at a conclusion. Times, trains and distances were too involved for him at the moment. All he knew was that it was now somewhere about 3 o’clock in the morning. “Come in and have a spot,” Mr. Snide was saying pleasantly. “The mills of the godsh grind surely, but they grind uncommon slow. Those whom the godsh love die sooner or later. It’s all ri’. I’ll put the kettle on and find the slippers. … We’ll have it hot.”

And Petershin followed his friend into the dining-room. It was at this moment that a new sound became audible behind him. It was a sound that froze his blood. His host, Mr. Snide, had evidently not heard it, for he was just then occupied in pouring out whisky with a generous air into two glasses, and he continued the operation steadily enough. He did not jump, at any rate. But neither did Petershin jump—for the simple reason that he could not jump. He could not move at all. He experienced a total paralysis of all his muscles. Tongue, legs, arms, head, all were held motionless in a vice of terror. Petershin was petrified, for the sound that thus turned him into stone was a voice—the voice of Mrs. Snide:

“Is that you, Richard Snide?” she asked, as she came slowly down the stairs towards the hall.

No answer was forthcoming; the question, with a slight change in the wording that rendered it doubly awful, was repeated:

“Then it is you, Richard Snide?”

Petershin, still unable to move a muscle, was aware that the speaker now stood close behind him. She could see his celluloid collar. He could not turn his head, even had he dared. An acute anguish twisted his very entrails. His position became suddenly more than he could bear, so that he made an effort of supreme violence, even though he felt it might burst his heart—he tried to run.

The result was suffocating. He could not breathe properly. A second later he could not breathe at all. God! He was going to die! An awful yell for help escaped him, though meant at the same time to warn his companion. Mr. Snide, to his intense relief, looked round.

The red face was tilted back a little, as its owner poured into his mouth the contents of his glass, and a moment or two later rose in an oddly laborious way and remarked solemnly:

“Pe’shin, me lad, you’ve had ’nough—more than ’nough, I might say. You’ve slept past closing time and your cell’loid collar’s choking you. …”

Picking Fir-Cones

A Fragment

I

Among my earliest recollections of any vividness is a voice saying “yes” across the darkness of my winter bedroom. My exact age at the time is difficult to fix, but since I have no memories of anything before I was six, it may be set, perhaps, safely at seven years old. The voice seemed outside myself; it issued apparently from the shadows as a whole, rather than from a particular corner of the fireless room.

I had been lying awake, wondering “frightfully hard” about everything, why so much was forbidden, and how disappointing it was to be blocked by rules and parents and nurses, and so on, when there stole out of the hush this whispered “yes,” as if in answer to my puzzles. It gave me the feeling that life was intended to be lived. All sorts of things were going to happen at once: I would do, accept them all. An exultant happiness burst up in, me. I was alive!

“I’m at it all again,” came to me.

Questions as to goal or origin there were none, but the feeling of “again” was vivid. This idea of resumption was certainly present. I resumed a journey; the train had stopped, but now went on again. … It was to be a long, long business, yet stuffed with interest and excitement to which I looked forward with zest, with positive joy. I had been “at it” for ages already, the journey by no means just begun. I was hungry to live, but to live again, and this hunger was familiar to me. My questions, my wonder, seemed like efforts to remember things just out of reach, yet not impossibly, finally, out of reach. They were recoverable. Meanwhile, I wished “fearfully” to live and experience again, avoiding nothing. “Getting on,” I called it, though growth, quâ development, was certainly not present in my mind at that tender age.

I woke next morning with the excitement to do things in my blood, and to do them as soon as possible. I did them. I turned on all the taps in the bathroom, tried to set fire to a hayrick to see the blaze, and let the pigs out of their pens into the stable-yard and thence into the garden. I remember lifting a broken hop-pole to hit the coachman’s daughter with. I did everything I could, taking the consequences, painful though these were, and puzzling too. For no one really explained to me, but merely said No, and then hurt me physically. It made no difference apparently. I meant to live, to miss no opportunity of doing things and enjoying the experience, pleasant or unpleasant. To avoid and shirk merely because it hurt was to lose an opportunity I was alive to know; whereas to suppress a desire, find no outlet for it, filled me with a choking violence that poisoned my whole being—what my elders meant by wickedness, I suppose.

Keen regret invariably followed such repression: I had missed an opportunity that might never come again. The hunger to live had been denied. To suppress without regret was a stage, of course, I reached much later; to divert this energy into other channels, transmuting it, came later still. If intensity was my native gift, at any rate, I think my energy was merely wasted rather than used for evil. This analysis, moreover, belongs to maturity, when reason loves laborious explanations; at the time I accepted and believed: I only felt and acted.

Evil! It was just this word, so often on father’s lips, that, with its opposite, good, made me feel sure there was some state superior to either, and that this state I had experienced already. I had known it before, but had now forgotten. It was recoverable, however, only I must be jolly quick about recovering it, for once I was grown up it would be too late. It involved an experience of strange, enormous, universal conditions difficult to describe. I wanted to get into everything, to do everything and to do it all at once, to be everywhere and to be everywhere simultaneously. The fir-cone incident was the only practical proof I had that it was possible. It will be described presently.

Here, then, was a definite, though wholly undetailed, memory. Belief, so called, played no part in my attitude towards it. I knew. I was haunted at this very early age by a dim recollection of some state superior to good and evil, and it betrayed itself, briefly, in an intense longing for things to be otherwise than they were—entirely otherwise.

This sounds so ordinary, it was actually so significant. No intellectually-devised Utopia was involved: an absolute change was what I so ardently desired. Hints of it came to me—came back: in fairytales, in poetry, in music, yet most frequently and with a closer sense of validity, from the beauty of Nature, especially in wild and lonely places; though as I grew older I grew, it seemed at the same time, smaller, and the chances of recovery rapidly decreased. I was settling in among conditions that excluded full recollection. Soon I should forget altogether.

The memory, as I have said, was undetailed, but two conditions stood out in the recovery so ardently desired: I wanted goodness to be more good, wickedness more wicked. People of both types were so tame, insipid, colourless, so oppressively alike. The good were only just good by the skin of their teeth, as it were, their goodness managed by an effort that left no energy over; they laboured for goodness, and for happiness, at some future time. Good to me meant positively shining. Yet the good folk had no particular joy. I wanted people who were shining and radiant now. Children had more of the quality I meant than older people, but no one had it properly at all.

With what my parents called “evil” it was similar. Depravity there was in plenty, but that was negative: an open wickedness, strong and unafraid, I did not find. What passed for wickedness was a hole-and-corner, afraid-of-being-caught, a shamefaced business; what passed for goodness, an equally negative state that denied living and kept certain rules grudgingly and with sighs for the sake of safety and some reward in the future. Energy, raised to the intensity where it involved worship—though I did not phrase it so at the time—did not exist at all. It was such a trumpery affair, the way folk lived. I wanted an intenser life that was somewhere within reach, within recovery. Memory played faintly round it like a flame, but a flame that was slowly and surely dying as I grew older. I longed to lift a curtain, to stretch the scale, to open life to some gigantic flood that was brimming just outside, ready to pour through and sweep me into joy and power. This immense tide hung waiting only just beyond the way we lived, but some small personal fear of its depth and extent alarmed us all. The keynote, at any rate, of this superior state I refer to was certainly joy. Joy was the quality that no one had—that joy, as I knew later, which is the essential quality of wisdom. The surprise, the unearthly touch, of wisdom, are mothered always by this towering sense of joy. It was the denial of joy everywhere that chafed and bruised me at a very early stage of my development, since it was, of course, a denial of life itself. The “yes” in the darkness of my bedroom was an affirmation of its accessibility. And memory was an ingredient.

The accessibility of this superior state I dreamed about remained my firm knowledge for a long time. It lay within reach still, here and now; it was really everywhere. Any moment I might pop back into it—at the end of the wet brambly lane, round the bend of the passage in the old house, behind the huge cedars, across the pond, a little further down the river. It was not in the future, but now; it was not away, but here. When least expecting it, I should come upon the exit through which I had slipped down into “this”—this life with parents, brothers, sisters, servants, governesses, gardeners, coachmen and policemen, all saying No from morning till night. And, once I came upon the exit, I could slip in again. But the way of slipping in or out I also had forgotten, and I made no special effort to recover it because it seemed so amazingly easy—a mere question of mood almost—that no effort was really necessary. It would come of its own accord. If people would only stop saying No so loudly, it would surely be upon me any moment.

Yet the actual way and method became more and more uncertain. Some kind of distance shrouded it in haze. It was then that I tried to get it back, but found that no mental effort was of any use, thinking and longing least of all. The conviction of genuine belief alone could manage the desired recovery, and it was this belief precisely that had begun to waver and grow dim in me as I got older. I must keep very still, intensely still, but with an interior stillness that was now escaping me, because no one knew of it, practised it least of all: this stillness within me I must find if I was to recover what I longed for before it was too late.

Then one day, quite suddenly, it came to me of its own accord. I did not discover it, but just knew. I did it. We called it—do you, my brother, as you read these notes, remember?—by a word of our own invention: dipping.

II

On the back lawn you and Val and I (Val just back from his first term at Charterhouse) were picking fir-cones that crackled sharply to the touch and had earwigs crawling between the dark little gaping crevices. A penny a hundred was the rate of payment father made, half in play and half in sermon-earnest, and the cones were burned eventually in the drawing-room fire, with the remark (if we happened to be present): “See how useful your labour was, my boys! No work is lost, nothing in life is wasted!” The sentence always made me feel rude; I wanted to deny it angrily, but never dared to. The actual picking, however, was rather fun. The crinkly cones with their ugly brown inhabitants were mysterious; the pincers of the insects fascinated me. As a rule, too, this collecting seemed important; it made a difference to the world; yet ever with this half-concealed provision, that it was actually a sham, and that one day some person or other would catch us at it and laugh. The humbug of it would be shown up. … One thing that held my interest, perhaps, was the quantity, and the way the cones deceived me. At first they appeared so few upon the lawn, so thinly scattered; yet half an hour’s labour made no difference to the numbers left. The quantity, indeed, increased; the lawn seemed blacker. I could not make it out. And a hundred cones took up so small a space in the gardener’s wooden basket that smelt of leaves and mould.

On this particular occasion we were picking hard, with remarks at intervals about the number, the prospective pennies, and speculations as to which of us had collected the greater quantity, when, quite suddenly, there was a change.

I was kneeling up at the moment, watching Val—Val, who was so clever, who explained things and “knew it all”;—my head swam a little with the rush of blood from stooping; Val had filled his straw hat, but, forgetting the blue cord fastened to his buttonhole, reached out an arm with a careless jerk that upset his entire store. He uttered an exclamation of disgust with a wry grimace, glancing round at me as though he hoped I had not seen tlie accident. I thought for a moment he was going to cry with disappointment. It was just then that a new mood—the change—came on me as with a burst of dazzling light.

The tiny comedy was set upon the big green lawn, the towering cedars behind, the vast summer sky of blue above. Such was the background to the trivial accident—an insignificant human miscalculation of time and distance framed by the steady, unalterable immensities. The contrast made me catch my breath. I did not laugh, I felt no triumph or pity; I felt, indeed, no interest of any kind, but knew suddenly that I was unutterably bored. The occupation was a sham, it was absurd and trumpery. Someone—father perhaps—was laughing at us. This was not living, it was merely making the time go by without being counted. There were better things to do, real things, immense opportunities sliding past unclaimed. Indeed, we were humbugging as well as being humbugged. I, at any rate, could manage things differently, otherwise, quite otherwise. The sense of the superior state I had forgotten and was in danger of losing altogether came breathlessly close to me. I shivered.

I stopped. A huge simple joy stole over my whole being. I had a sense of awe that made me hold my breath and at the same time intensely happy. The thing I so yearningly desired was near to me as air, not in the future, not away, but here and now. I only had to claim it. There was rapture. I trembled, as though interiorly I was a sheaf of fine, taut wires drawn thin as silk, and a wind passed over them.

I waited, kneeling upright on the grass and staring. Nothing happened at first. All my activities, not merely the gathering of the fir-cones, came to rest. My inner being had become intensely still. Of Val I was no longer aware, I hardly saw him; but I saw you, my brother; I stared, watching you in your alpaca suit of overalls, as you stooped and picked and stretched out your arms and legs in the sunshine. You moved slowly; and I marvelled why you continued grubbing so contentedly on one spot of ground. You crawled laboriously over the lawn, a few inches at a time, panting with effort, like some monster-insect badly made, clumsily jointed: even the earwigs moved with more skill and cleverer energy.

It was ludicrous; yet I realised you were doing this on purpose and had not really “forgotten” any more than I had. It was a phantom you I watched; the real you looked on, looked down, from this superior state. You yourself watched the phantom “you” with detachment that was not quite indifference. Sharply then I realised another thing: you picked fir-cones with all your energy, because you knew it was the purpose for which you were here. I was vividly aware in that instant of those two different points of view respectively: neither of us had “forgotten”; but, whereas I revolted and wished to be otherwise, you accepted the present and were content. I felt ashamed of myself while this flashed through me. With its passing, however, my own point of view shot uppermost again. I thought you obstinate, stupid, but knew that I loved you dearly.

“You are my darling little brother,” I thought to myself, “only it’s stupid-silly—(you remember our childhood superlative?)—of you to be satisfied with this., Why in the world don’t you … ?”

But the actual word escaped me; there was a gap where the right word should have been. The swift, fluttering effort to find it bore fruit afterwards only with the invention of “dip” and “dipping.”

“Let’s go!” I cried instead. “Let’s get on!” It was the nearest I could come to the meaning of what I felt, but could not say. There was an abrupt and passionate vehemence in my voice; in my heart there was absolute conviction. Quietly, without looking up, you replied, “There are more over here,” and continued to fill your basket. The rattle of the cones, as you tossed them in, came to me already from a distance.

“Yes, yes,” I exclaimed excitedly, for I had the horror that you were missing an amazing opportunity, “but why stick in one place like this? It’s awful. We can be anywhere—everywhere at once—doing everything!” I remember the frantic impossibility of finding words to express what I felt so sure of—“Come on, Dick! Come with me!”

Caught by something in my voice, perhaps, you stopped picking and looked up; there was a steady expression in your big blue eyes. You said nothing. I felt that you knew more than I did after all. You wished to restrain me, though at the same time you would have liked to “go.”

I sprang up quickly, lest forgetfulness of the way should catch me.

“Anyhow,” I cried, “I’m going—!”

And then I heard your solemn whisper: “Look out!” you said softly, “it’s not allowed, you know. You mayn’t be able to get back. They’ll cry about you. Mother’ll be in a state. Besides, you’ll only miss all this—” There was a catch in your voice and breath as you said it; you were eager and ready; you knew the way; but, for some wiser reason than I guessed, you thought it a mistake to go. I confused, I think, the real you and the other that picked fir-cones and objected. I hesitated for a fraction of a second, the merest fraction. At the same moment I saw Val watching us—watching me in particular—and the startled expression on his face decided me. For he was afraid. I realised his vanity, his self-importance, his ignorance; either he had never known, or had entirely forgotten; remembering nothing of this “other” state, he was a sham, unreal, supremely satisfied with himself and with his condition. “Oh, dear,” I thought, “almost everybody’s like that!” And I cried at the top of my voice, bursting with joy and confidence, “I’m off!”

Val gave a gasp, and shouted “Where?” And I wanted to reply, but had no time to get the words out; besides, the right words would not come.

“Look, Dickie! Look!” I cried happily. You smiled into my eyes, but said no word. And I went.

The effort, if effort there was at all, was of some interior and delicious kind that was familiar. It was not muscular, though it was accompanied by a certain tautening of the muscles about the heart and abdomen—a sensation of heat in the pit of the body—followed instantly by a complete and comforting relaxation. It seemed a species of inner determination; perfect assurance, absolute conviction made it possible and even easy. I had no doubt that I could “go.” I knew. And there was joy in me beyond anything my words can possibly explain.

I went. It was a change of condition really, but the terms of physical motion describe it best. I went out gliding, as in those flying-dreams so many know, and the slight effort was due to the fact that I had forgotten how to exercise the power properly. As in the flying-dream, I now recovered this half-forgotten power. “I can do this again when I wake,” thinks the dreamer. “I’ve remembered at last,” I thought; “how jolly!” Had I then known Bergson’s suggestion that the flying-dream is due to the feet being deprived of their customary support, I could have given him the lie. The flying-dream is a racial, but also an individual, memory of the means of transition to this other “state.” It is supremely easy; only it must be recovered young, before Reason and excess of physical sensation obliterate instinctive knowledge of the method.

I went out gliding, gliding over the summer lawn. I looked down—down upon the fir-cones and the baskets, the cedar tops, the crescent flowerbeds, the bushy horse-chestnut and its bulging shadow, the gravel drive, the squat, foreshortened Manor House. All lay beneath me, curiously flat. You I saw clearly, I saw Val in a haze; and while you increased for me somehow, there was about Val that flat and meaningless quality, as of an empty shell almost, which touched the other objects also with unreality.

And the expression in his face I cannot forget: the staring eyes, the mouth wide open, the perspiration on the puckered forehead, the coat pulled out where the hat-cord tugged at it, and then the look of sheer amazement passing into terror, as he stretched his bare arms out, turned jerkily, as though the power of coordinating his movements were impaired, and ran headlong towards the house. He had no breath to scream, or possibly the sound did not reach me; for his attitude was a scream materialised. He disappeared. Yet not by going into the building; it was more a fading out, a dying away, as a reflection fades from a pool when the sun is hidden or a puff of wind obliterates it. He vanished into a depth. He was withdrawn from my consciousness. The phantom Val was all I knew. He was unreal.

With you, however, precisely the opposite took place: you became instantly more real. It seemed I knew you for the first time fully, and understood the reason for the deep tie between us. We both shared another, bigger state. The little figure in alpaca overalls picking fir-cones was not really you at all. It was a phantom you. We now came together for the first time properly, or, as I felt it then, “we were together again—at last.” There was union and the full, rapturous joy of union. The idea of being everywhere at once, of sharing everything, seemed amazingly justified.

I cannot say that you joined in my actual physical motion, that you definitely came with me on my gliding, sliding change. It was rather that when I arrived I found you already there; and “there” was a state we had both left temporarily, come down from, as it were, in order to pick fir-cones and do other little necessary things—little things, trivial and unimportant in themselves, yet the doing of which increased our value, our reality. Everybody in the world had similarly “come down,” but the majority became so absorbed in the “little, trivial things” that they forgot. Father, for instance, though he went to church as regularly as to the Treasury where he worked, had not the least idea—he denied that there could be a way back at all. And this was why everyone said No so often and so loudly. The important thing was to continue picking fir-cones as long as possible and as many as possible. Whatever enfeebled or endangered the picking faculties must be prevented. Picking to fill one’s basket, and to fill it first before anybody else, was the sole criterion of reality and a useful life. Church and the Treasury were both, to father, a form of picking fir-cones, and any suggestion that reality lay in a bigger state was merely stupid-silly. This flashed into me as clearly as the meaning of cake and jam at teatime. …

We were properly together, anyhow, you and I, and the joy was wonderful; but not only was I properly with you, for I was in everything everywhere, not stuck in one spot any more, but able to do anything everywhere at once. I had this power, this rapture … At the same time, you understood, apparently, that picking cones on a single spot, and so forth, was worth doing, and worth doing well. It was not to be shirked by any means. We picked experience while we did so, experience that was carried over and stored up in our “other” state, making us more real, and our eventual happiness even more complete. This, too, was very clear to me, simple, easy, and overwhelmingly convincing.

“We mustn’t stay too long,” you said at once. “They’ll be frightened, you see. Besides”—and you laughed happily, as though you referred to a brief, almost an instantaneous interlude—“we want to finish, don’t we? Let’s get it done. Then we can be together …”

There was more I cannot remember; but what I do remember with vividness is the feeling of deep, lasting joy that accompanied your phrase, “then we can be together.” For it involved everything that those who love, yet fear separation, most ardently desire—complete and permanent union. I was too young, of course, in those days to have realised death, yet I saw clearly as in brilliant sunshine that death, where love is, meant only the transition into this other “state” where separation was not even a possibility. It was, I suppose, my first experience of a spiritual value. The meaning of Now was shown to me.

But another thing was also clear: Val had looked on death, or on what he thought was death. For him the only reality was picking fir-cones, and the Val that picked them was the only Val he knew. He had “forgotten” everything. Thinking I was dead, he experienced the nameless terror that is the bogey of his kind—of those who have forgotten.

III

I found myself in bed. There was a darkened room full of soft rustling and whispering. Busy figures moved to and fro on tiptoe like ghosts amid a general sense of hush. Mother and nurse were bending over me. There was a cold sponge and a feeling of anxiety and awe. I felt this anxiety, this awe, this fear, but I wanted to laugh; I could not understand this peculiar atmosphere of dread. It was unnecessary humbug. I could have screamed. A yearning sadness next came over me. Then I laughed. And the laughter brought relief, although it frightened the others. Afterwards—long afterwards—it was reported that I hung between life and death. Isn’t that delicious? A comic statement—the sort of thing a grub might say about a chrysalis: it hung between life and death before it emerged and flew as a butterfly! … A hand stroked my forehead. I knew half-sensations.

Of these half-sensations I was uncomfortably aware. With an effort I had come back, I was shut in again, enclosed, confined in something that had the pain of limitation, yet of limitation that was somewhere valuable. The truth was I had forgotten again, or was beginning to forget, and hence the half-sensations. … They explained presently that I had fainted in the sun; “a touch of sun,” they called it; and when I laughed at this the cold sponge descended on my neck and forehead and the whispers multiplied.

“Lie quite still, my darling, quite, quite still. Do not excite yourself. You’re safe at home, and Mummie’s looking after you!”

It never occurred to them that I might have looked after Mummie.

It was marvellously sweet and tender, but O, how futile and how ignorant! I knew so much; I could tell so little—nothing and less than nothing. I had come back. I was caught again. They could not know, because they had “forgotten.” At last the cold sponge ceased descending on my neck and forehead; I fell asleep; and when I woke again the curtains were drawn back and the sun poured over the room. “That’s real, at any rate,” I remember thinking, as I felt the warmth upon my skin. The light made me happy, though I knew not exactly why.

I recovered very quickly. It had been something of a false alarm apparently. There were no ill results, although hourly warnings about the sun continued for a long time, and Val was afraid of me for the rest of the holidays. “I thought you were dead,” was all he said; “I saw you tumble down flat, you know.” He was white as he spoke of it. “Once I saw a chap fall on his head from the parallel bars and kill himself,” he added. “By Jove, you know—it’s awful.” Having looked on death, he was afraid of life.

What you thought and felt you never said. You were a solemn little owl. Our love seemed more near and understanding than before. I date our realisation of it from that time, at any rate. But, also, from that moment I knew another thing that lay at the back of my bram; I knew it subconsciously perhaps without explanation or analysis. What one knows and believes subconsciously affects all one does in a natural, instinctive way, whereas what one reasons out is a matter of calculation—one is forever persuading oneself that it is true. This thing I now knew was, perhaps, that daily life was but an interlude of no real duration in a bigger matter, and that death simply closed the interlude—if a state without duration can be said to have an end. My intense desire for things to be “quite otherwise” was actually a memory therefore, true and deep, yet hidden with extraordinary care behind my brain. My true self was not involved with this fir-cone picking business except to watch it and be wise; it dwelt apart, detached from good and evil, so-called; it was everywhere and forever. It was my “otherwise.” To be identified with it meant to know peace and joy and those indescribable states which are of the spirit and of eternity, but to know them Now. To forget—as Val forgot it—meant to be unreal. As a dream of ten seconds may seem indefinitely prolonged, so it was with daily life. At the close of the dream the sleeper wakes and says: “Is that all?” The dream has been an interlude without duration.

Although I can give no further details of what I experienced after I went out gliding, I remembered it for a long time with happy wonder. The tang of its unforgettable ecstasy came back with me. I had known power, sweetness, joy; it was complete and satisfying; I had been everywhere, dipped and merged in everything; and you were with me. Young as I was, I realised this great completeness. “It was all right,” as I said to you; and the phrase seems to me now significant: all and right. … My yearning to be “otherwise” had been justified. I had been otherwise. I had been dipped, then come up to the surface again. And I remember saying this to you, wondering at your owl-like silence, although you knew far more about it all than I did, and then your remark at the end: “Yes. It’s all right, but I vote we stay down for a bit all the same. I think we’ve got to—don’t you see?”

Then, gradually, as we grew older, the memory of the experience faded and grew dim. At school it became heavily obscured, at Sandhurst I forgot it. I did not forget the experience, that is, but I forgot the feelings that accompanied it. I could not reconstruct those feelings; I did not even wish to. … Only much later, with the thrill and the opening of the heart by beauty, did the feelings partially return to me. …

I know now, of course, that it is possible to pick fir-cones on the surface, yet to dip and be otherwise, simultaneously; that this, in fact, is really living. Picking fir-cones helps to build empires, but builds the empire of oneself as well; it is human and necessary, whereas “dipping” is exceptional and divine. Everybody wants to be dipped, yet knows not how to achieve it. Being afraid of death, they are afraid of life—afraid to live. They think that picking fir-cones is the way. They have “forgotten.” For, instead, it is the way they pick fir-cones that is the Way!

Pines

All trees, doubtless, appeal in some measure to the sense of poetry, even in those who are not strictly speaking lovers of nature; but the pine, for many, seems to have a message more vivid, more vital than the rest: as though it possessed some occult quality that speaks not merely to the imagination, or to the general love of nature per se, but directly to the soul. The oak for strength, the ash for mystery, the birch for her feminine grace and so forth; but the pine, like a sharp sword, pierces straight through to that inner sense of beauty which accepts or rejects beyond all question of analysis. The personality of this “common” tree touches the same sense of wonder that is stirred by the presence of a human personality, strong beyond ordinary; and worship is ever subtly linked with wonder.

The analogy is interesting. The pine plants its roots where more showy trees faint and die; straight, strong, and sweet to the winds, it flourishes where only gorse, heather, and toughly obstinate things can live. Out of the rock, where there seems not earth enough to feed a violet, it lifts its sombre head undaunted; scorched by the sun, torn by the blast, peering into dreadful abysses, yet utterly fearless, and yielding so little that the elements must pluck it up by the roots before they can destroy it. Only lightning can break it. At a height above the sea that means death to other trees, it climbs singing, “rockrooted, stretched athwart the vacancy”; and even when the main army halts, stragglers are always to be seen, leading forlorn hopes into the heart of desolation beyond. And if, amid the stress of conditions, it cannot look well, it is content to look ill, showing a dwarfed and stunted figure to the skies. Only then, ye elemental powers! What strength in the gnarled roots, what iron resistance in the twisted trunk, what dour endurance in the short, thick limbs! It assumes the attitude of the fighting animal, back to the wall.

High mountains are full of vivid pictures of this courage against Titanic odds. For the pine tree has the courage of its convictions—fine, simple, tenacious—as it has also that other quality of the strong soul: the power to stand alone. “Some say there is a precipice where one vast pine is frozen to ruin o’er piles of snow and chasms of ice ’mid Alpine mountains.” No one who has canoed on Canadian lakes and seen those frequent rocky islets, each with its solitary pine, can have ignored that there is something strangely significant in the sight of that slender spire rising out of the heart of loneliness—something that thrills, and thrills deeply, into the region beyond words. Unsheltered, beneath wide skies, remote from its own kind, the tree stands there, splendid in its isolation, straight as a temple column and prepared for any shock. “Ein Fichtenbaum steht einsam,” of course—but there is more than the pathos of Heine’s poem in its unapproachable loneliness: there is the spiritual suggestion of personality—this upright, self-sufficing tree upon a rock, buffeted by winds and waves, asking no sympathy and dreading no possible fate. The picture, symbolic of the strong soul, conveys the inevitable parable. Compared with other trees, too, the pine does not change. One knows, of course, the tips of tender green that come with May and turn a pine wood into a sea of bewildering beauty. But, though deciduous, one is never aware that anything is lost; its branches never thin; it puts out, properly speaking, no buds. And the monotony of a pine forest is merely a defect of its great quality of constancy. In summer its shade is deeper, its recesses more cool than those of other woods; and in winter, just when most trees are leafless and unable to fight, it bears the full weight of the snow and meets the whole force of the destroying winds. It stands to face disaster when others faint or run. The analogy with man is again striking and complete. Yet its qualities are not merely negative. More than most, it gives out—without reward, often without recognition; for the great forests that sweeten the world with their balsam, and their life-giving odours, stand most often in the deserted regions of the earth, unseen, unknown. And, by their death, they become more useful still, journeying over all the seas. In the true sense, most ascetic of trees, accepting discipline that good may come for others, not for themselves!

Like the vital human personality, too, what “atmosphere” it has! What it lends of suggestiveness to the commonest landscape—a few pines clustered on the hill; a sombre group among the green trees in the plain! In the suburban garden even, or rearing its dark crest against the hoardings of the street, how its picturesqueness spreads about it! It is the gipsy among trees, and its perfume, like the wood fire, sets the blood aflame for wandering and for the lonely places of the world. At the sight of it one thinks, perhaps, of the stone pine “into which the forest has whispered its gravest and sweetest thought,” and at the same instant is caught away to that other revelation where it stands by the sea. For, by the shore of southern seas, it betrays a scarcely suspected touch of melancholy, gentle and pathetic in its essence, feminine almost, that makes the heart yearn for lovely and impossible things. One sees it there, rooted among golden sands, and gazing across a waste of purple sea, the wash of whose waves is hardly to be distinguished from the wash of wind through its own branches …

The mystery of the pines, too, seems to hold a peculiar quality unapproached elsewhere in Nature: it subdues without terrifying, inspires awe without distress, and is more human than the mystery which belongs to mountains, sea, or desert. The fairies come out from the pine woods; for no other woods conceal so gently, yet hold within their velvety recesses such possibilities of revelation. To meet them unexpectedly is to experience a thrill of subtle suggestion. Among tamer trees, suddenly to come upon these black, vigorous things, contemptuous of soil, independent of sympathy, thriving where others droop or die, is to know a leap of the imagination, an increase of vitality—, as when, among a crowd of common souls, one finds a man—strong, radiating confidence and hope. Their very darkness stimulates. One cannot conceive such trees stooping to any kind of show. “Lowland trees,” says the author of Modern Painters, may “show themselves gay with blossoms and glad with pretty charities of fruitfulness,” but the pines “have harder work to do for man and must do it in close-set troops.” While other trees “may turn their paleness to the sky if but a rush of rain passes them by, the pines must live carelessly amidst the wrath of clouds,” and “only wave their branches to and fro when a storm pleads with them, as men toss their arms in a dream … You cannot reach them, cannot cry to them; these trees never heard human voice,” he says, speaking of their inaccessible multitudes among the precipices; “they are far above all sound but of the winds. No foot ever stirred fallen leaf of theirs. All comfortless they stand, between the two eternities of Vacancy and the Rock; yet with such iron will that the rock itself looks bent and shattered beside them—fragile, weak, inconsistent, compared to their dark energy of delicate life, and monotony of enchanted pride—unnumbered, unconquerable.”

And there is no sound in Nature quite so wonderful as that faint spiritual singing of pine trees, that gentle whirring of a forest when soft airs are moving—that säuseln, susurrement, whispering. Midway in the wood, of course, a pine forest shouting in a free wind is simply the sea shouting on a sandy shore; close the eyes, and it is impossible to tell the difference; it is tumbling surf, mellowed by distance, tossing, instead of spray, the flying odours of their needles’ frankincense. But when only stray puffs come a-wandering, and other trees are silent, listen at the skirts of a pine grove, and hear those ghosts of sound that fall from nowhere, that thin away to a mere ghost of sighing, and then come running back to you over the motionless crests. For pines can answer the wind apparently without moving. No other sound can faint as this does—or sing alone; among the stragglers at the edge of the wood you may hear distinct solos. Isolated pines respond to a wind you cannot feel; and a tree at your side will sigh and murmur, while another six feet away keeps silent. Almost as though the wind can consciously pick and choose when and where it shall shake “the clinging music from their boughs,” so that “low, sweet sounds, like the farewell of ghosts,” are heard.

Wherever they are found, whether they “fledge the wild ridgéd mountain steep by steep,” or gather in greater concourse like “fallen flakes and fragments of the night, stayed in their solemn squares,” these trees, for some imaginations at least, seem charged with a potent symbolism. And, from the particular, they sweep the mind across continents to the general. Their shadows rest upon a nation, as Ruskin puts it, and absorb and mould the life of a race. “The Northern people, century after century, lived under one or another of the two great powers of the Pine and the Sea, both infinite … Whatever elements of imagination, or of warrior strength, or of domestic justice, were brought down by the Norwegian and the Goth against the dissoluteness or degradation of the South of Europe, were taught them under the green roofs and wild penetralia of the pine.”

Playing Catch

Mr. Anthony, a widower, was deeply interested in the big questions of life and death, and in philosophy generally. He liked to wonder where his wife was, what she was doing if she had survived the destruction of her pretty body, and how her spirit was engaged. Was she, for instance, in any way aware of him? … Mabel, he remembered, had not been imaginative. Though sympathetic, she had contributed nothing to his mental life. When he referred any of his big questions to her, she would fix her patient eyes upon his own, and say: “ ‘I wonder! What do you think, dear? ” Her disposition was gentle, but uninspiring.

Mabel apart, however, he pondered over many other things, being distinctly speculative: Why there was anything at all, and what—since there was a beginning—had existed before that beginning?What there might be on the other side of the moon, and whether the other planets were inhabited?The vast number of the heavenly bodies in particular perplexed him—a thousand million suns in the Milky Way alone!—it all seemed so unnecessarily enormous. He often wondered, again, about angels. Were there such beings, and, if so, what was their habit and nature?All races, all religions, all cosmogonies mentioned angels. Were they an invention of primitive imagining, Or were they actual?

Dreams, too, interested him immensely. He declared all such enquiries stimulated him.

His speculations, it is seen, were sometimes grandiose, sometimes trivial. He read much, he brooded, he dwelt in an atmosphere of unanswerable questions. It argued, perhaps, a strain of futility in the blood, but his love of the marvellous was ineradicable. That Mabel had not shared his divine curiosity had always been a secret grievance, rather shaking his belief in feminine intuition. She had never answered—anything. Could she answer anything now? By force of habit he still referred all his big questions to her mentally: Did Mabel know?

It was the advent of Mr. Einstein that dragged his anchor and set him sailing upon uncharted seas. Space, Time, Relativity, absorbed his entire thought. The mass of all his reading, knowledge, thinking, converged on this bewildering subject. No sympathy for a discredited Euclid troubled him. Time, as a fourth dimension, delighted him. He mastered the matter as well as any layman could. Though out of his depth, he was not afraid. …

Meanwhile, he had no settled home, feeling himself a wanderer physically as well as mentally. He occupied lodgings in Dymchurch at the moment. Large foreign seashells stood, echoless and dismal, on the plush mantelpiece, and a yellow-faced clock, with hands always pointing to 4.20, reposed under a domed glass cover. There was brilliant gas, a horsehair sofa, and a painted fan before the grate. Long green bell-ropes hung against the walls, with two oil-paintings of violent Swiss scenery beside them. A framed photograph of a fat-faced man, wearing Masonic regalia, was perched above the door, The broad windowsills were littered with his books, volumes straggled over the sofa, and an atmosphere of relativity, of astronomy, of the marvellous generally, pervaded the false brightness of the sordid seaside lodgings out of the season.

One warm February evening, when the days were pleasantly lengthening, Mr. Anthony was coming home along the seafront just after sunset, when a thing happened that enthralled him because it proved, as he had long suspected, that there were Beings in the Universe compared to whom the greatest human was the merest microbe. Were they, perhaps, angels?he asked himself. He was uncommonly intrigued.

The afternoon had been strangely warm. He had sat down under a breakwater to rest. The something that happened was as follows:

The moon, clean, bright and tender, and just off the full, stood well above the sea, when, from the western horizon, there rose without the slightest warning a gigantic arm, whose huge hand seized her, as a man might seize a tennis ball, and flung her away into space with a stupendous but quite effortless throw. The vast hand then dropped, as a man’s hand drops after throwing, and the colossal arm, one instant level with the horizon, sank swiftly out of sight below the rim of the sea. The arm, Mr. Anthony noticed, was visible from the elbow only. The figure it belonged to, therefore, was standing in space at least one thousand miles below the spinning earth.

The grandeur of the gesture, magnificent, even godlike, left him breathless, but exhilarated. Yet it caused him no alarm, nor was he conscious of surprise. Such immense proportions, he reflected, must be angelic, surely. Why no head and shoulders were visible puzzled him—for his mind began to work at once—until he realised that, being of the same colour as the golden sunset, they merged into its background, so that the sky revealed no outline. Moreover, the arm, he observed, was slightly richer in red and gold than the tint of the air, and thus showed up nicely. The hand, of a splendid crimson, was fiery rather, and the colossal fingers that gripped the moon in their great curving clutch, stood out, dark-ridged like mountains, against the silver. It was an impressive and inspiring sight.

Mr. Anthony stood spellbound, watching the moon as she flew plunging away into space. Such headlong speed enthralled him. It was thrilling, too, to remember that this outer space, being of ether only, was completely black. Had he been out there himself, he would have appeared as a solitary bright figure amid Egyptian darkness. This reflection, certainly, occurred to him. He would be a shining figure. Mabel, too, occurred to him. Did Mabel, he asked himself, witness what he witnessed? Was his strange privilege shared? ..

He watched the flying moon. Already she was half her usual size. In fifteen seconds, she was no larger than a tangerine orange; in thirty, she resembled a sparkling marble; in forty, a shining pea; in sixty, a glittering bead; in seventy-five, a pinhead; and in ninety, a mere starry point that was barely visible at all against the sunset afterglow. The speed, the distance, the power behind the throw, the possible immediate effect upon the tide, the terror of any human beings who were looking on—all these details filled him with a high sense of happiness that was elation. He felt, to use his own favourite word, stimulated.

Then other points of view began to occur to him, modifying his first emotion of pure enjoyment. The human standpoint struck him. He noticed that the sky looked bare, undressed, naked somewhere, even—he used poetic license—a little lonely. He felt sorry that the moon had gone. He found that he missed her. He experienced regret. He was glad, therefore, to see that the point of light she had now become held stationary, and that no further dwindling occurred. The moon, then, had not completely vanished. Had she done so he would have felt bereft. Only a few days before he had told his landlady’s child that he knew of no reason why the earth should have a moon at all, since not all planets had these pretty, faithful satellites, and the child had asked at once:

“ But what would happen at night, then?”

It was this simple human point of view that now modified his first emotion somewhat. He felt precisely as the child felt: ‘‘ What would happen at night without a moon?”

It was with sincere relief and pleasure, therefore, after the minute and a half had passed, that he noted she was now growing bigger again. She was returning. She was on her way back. He watched her rapidly grow larger, as she approached at appalling speed. The point, bead, pea, marble and orange sizes were reached and passed successively, and ninety seconds later she had almost resumed her normal size and appearance again. Mr. Anthony’s fear that she would grow larger still and come crashing down upon the earth, obliterating perhaps Dymchurch, was hardly born before it was allayed. He watched with beating heart and straining eyes. He saw the gigantic arm and hand again shoot forth. The enormous fingers caught her, clutched her, then placed her with easy accuracy exactly where she would have moved to in these three minutes had her course not been interrupted. The same side as before shone placidly down. She was not a fraction turned. The stupendous arm and hand at once withdrew and sank below the sea. The sky was as it had been. Mr. Anthony, tears of joy in his eyes and wonder in his heart, but outwardly quite calm, resumed his walk home along the seafront towards his lodgings. …

The awful occurrence, for most, must have been dislocating, yet Mr. Anthony faced it with equilibrium. His joy was not hysterical. Accustomed to speculations concerning the unknown and unexpected, he maintained his poise quite admirably. He did not, so to speak, fall flat upon his face, prostrate in worship, although both awe and reverence were touched. The experience, he argued, was not merely a vision which could be analysed away next morning, for his mind retained its logical, observant processes, his reason worked as usual. Memory, judgment, imagination, the three great faculties, functioned properly. It was, therefore, no hallucination, in which these faculties are notoriously in abeyance. It was an honest, a genuine phenomenon.

He considered what he had seen, he made justifiable inferences, he drew sound conclusions. It pleased him particularly to find that these held water, as he called it. Thus he was delighted to establish—since the moon had been thrown away and then thrown back again—that two great figures were tossing her to and fro together across outer space, and that a spirit of amusement, even of sheer happy fun, evidently inspired the majestic spectacle. It was, perhaps, a game, a match possibly, a trial of skill at any rate, since one hand only was employed. The two gorgeous players were enjoying themselves. They were playing catch.

It made him happy to think that he had witnessed at least one mighty stroke in their magnificent game, and still more happy—comforted as well—to realise that, at long last, the intolerable quantity of the heavenly bodies, together with their overwhelming speeds and distances, were thus reasonably explained. He weighed his inferences cautiously, he examined his deductions; his logic and premises were sound, he could find no flaw in his reasoning. It was obvious to him that all the heavenly bodies, whose numbers had long dismayed him, as their raison d’être had thwarted him, that all of these—stars, suns, planets, comets—were being similarly thrown from hand to hand, most of them, with century-long, some with age-long tosses, and that the purpose of the colossal Universe was at last made clear.

He wondered if Mabel also knew; he hoped she did. To his boldest speculations her contribution had been invariably ‘‘ But why bother, dear? What can it matter to ws? ’ ” Did she now share the relief and wonder of his superb discovery that all the heavenly bodies were used by angels for the purposes of—happy play?

His mind, it is seen, worked admirably, his faculties retained their normal sharpness, the clarity of his thought was unimpaired. How, why, by what happy chance, he had witnessed only one stroke in the game, this, too, was quite clear to him at the moment, though he had difficulty in setting it down later in his written account of the occurrence. Relativity, of course, helped in the first easy stages of the explanation. Four measurements, he remembered, one of which is Time, are necessary to locate a point in space; and until that point is thus located and in position, it has not become an event—it has not “ happened.” Clearly, then, he had witnessed an occurrence in four-dimensional space. It was an event, it had happened, though not necessarily now.

This fourth measurement of Time troubled him for a moment, but fora moment only. He looked at his watch, he began to make elaborate calculations at the back of his head, and then confusion overtook him. … What remained, however, was the positive assurance that this playing catch with the moon filled him with the joy of a comfortable understanding. One of his big questions, at least, was satisfactorily answered.

He resumed his walk along the seafront, therefore, at a steady gait, stimulated, though not unduly so, and by no means shaken. That his mental balance held true is proved by the fact that, as he turned homewards, his mind dealt with commonplace things quite naturally. He thought of his lodgings, remembering that he liked them because baths were included in the terms, that early morning tea was only three pence, and that he could turn the light out from his bed. Also, he once more remembered Mabel. And again he asked himself: was she aware of him in this magnificent moment?For Mabel, he suddenly realised with a qualm of peculiar distress, was involved somewhere in the entire business. This realisation, coming abruptly, caused an odd uneasiness, and the uneasiness spread, till it was established in his whole being. Mabel, it flashed through him, though involved, was not involved—quite openly. There was an unpleasant touch of subterfuge, a hint of plan, of purpose, almost of plot: his original idea of Mabel, his fond, admiring, yet rather stupid wife, had undergone a disagreeable change. It was as though she now stood mysteriously behind the scenes, unpleasantly concealed—secreted.

The confused conviction that Mabel played this hidden réle began to trouble him. …

Meanwhile, the splendour he had witnessed brought a touch of soberness in its train. The aftereffect of splendour is invariably of a sedative description, and this reaction now set in, accompanied by a feeling of disappointment that just stopped short of distress and yet held the seed of faint alarm. The breath of uneasiness blew through him. It was slight, impossible to seize. He noticed it, no more than that, yet its presence lurked, if not definite enough yet to cause acute disturbance. It remained a vague sinking of the heart, due to something that was not fully explained. Mabel, however, he felt sure, would explain it—if she could. Here, at last, was something Mabel really knew. Here was a contribution she could make—if she would.

Confusion grew upon him. He had after all been privileged, perhaps, beyond what a man can bear with equanimity—this occurred to him as a solution of his distress. Being wise, therefore, he turned his thoughts deliberately upon more familiar things. He felt hungry. He hoped there might be a fried Dover sole for supper. Mabel, too, he remembered, was fond of that dish. He felt happier again. The wind had grown chilly, and he drew his light-blue dressing-gown more closely about him. The dark blue bathing-suit underneath looked a trifle tight, he thought, but there was no need to bother about that at the moment. The thought did not detain him. He must get home quickly now and change. He hurried.

In this frame of mind, therefore, Mr. Anthony made his way along the deserted front, and in so doing had to pass the row of bathing-sheds that stood high and dry upon the sandy ridge. The coarse grass went ruffled and whistling in the wind. It was too early in the year for bathers, and the sheds were unoccupied. Rather dreary and melancholy it appeared, but this was all exactly as it should be, and his mind observed the fact, offering no comment on it. At the same time something about those whitewashed bathing-sheds began to draw his attention. His mind was first arrested, then startled. There was a difference somewhere. Why, for instance, did it take so long to pass them?Why did they stretch into such an interminable distance?Why did the endless row of familiar ugliness now seem queer and ominous? … He found himself counting them automatically. And his interest, on a sudden, became intense. He had discovered where the difference lay; there was an increase in their number. Multiplied by thousands, the row of sheds stretched horribly, hundreds upon hundreds, into a dim infinity …

His alarm deepened at once. There was something here he ought by rights to have known, but did not know; yet something, it occurred to him painfully, that Mabel knew already and had always known; something, again, that she was concealing from him deliberately.

He paused to consider the matter. It was, he realised, of immense importance—not so much the horrible increase in the sheds, as her reason for the deliberate concealment. A singular new dread invaded, clutched him. What precisely was it that Mabel knew, yet kept so mysteriously hidden from him?A dreadful curiosity attached itself to the interminable row of bathing-sheds. Their number, certainly, was sinister. But her reason for concealment was far worse. Terror touched him with an icy finger. He faced, with shrinking, a portentous and appalling thing.

In this predicament his native habit of philosophical enquiry amid unanswerable questions proved of some assistance. His mind switched automatically elsewhere. Turning his attention in another direction altogether, he glanced up at the sky, perceived the moon safely in her accustomed place, and noted, not without a faint annoyance, that he had mistaken her light a few moments before for sunshine. The bathing-suit he wore was out of place now. He had evidently lingered somewhere; he must hasten home and change. He therefore hurried. He passed the row of sheds without the slightest difficulty, intent only upon finding Mabel so that she might explain properly to him what she had so long been hiding. He reached and entered his lodgings, forgetting entirely that he had ever felt uneasy, and quite happy that everything was now all right again. Passing through the hall he saw his landlady very quickly close the kitchen door. She spoke to him, but he did not catch the words. Very quickly she closed that door, He caught but a glimpse of her vanishing face.

Things, however, were only fairly “all right,” it seemed. For instance, he at once missed Mabel. There was no sign of her anywhere. A feeling came to him—it was in the very air—that she had never been in this particular house at all. For a second he felt sure it was the wrong house altogether. A wild bewilderment came on him. Mabel was lost, hopelessly, irrecoverably lost; and it was due to some stupid carelessness of his own that she was thus irretrievably mislaid. Somehow he had blundered: he had neglected some obvious precaution, had been somewhere he ought not to have been, had missed or overlooked a prearranged instruction of very simple kind—with the result that his wife was now finally and completely lost.

A realisation of his deep guilt overwhelmed him. A sense of hideous, imminent danger at once hung in the air. He had stolen upon the threshold of a mystery none but Mabel could possibly unravel—and she was lost. He felt it with capital letters: LOST. A sense of frantic hurry rushed upon him. It was tremendous, overmastering He knew himself hideously caught by the thing that all men dread—the panic sense.

He hurried, he rushed, he tore headlong. …

In the confused and frenzied search that followed, Mr. Anthony experienced such acute anguish, such poignant, heartfelt sadness, such aching misery and distress of mind, that he realised it was altogether impossible to continue looking. It was a hopeless, an intolerable search: the strain was unbearable; the pain was more than he could support without a collapse that involved the awful disaster of some terrible extinction. He, therefore, gave up the search, and turned his thoughts to other things. … The power of detachment pertaining to a mind that dealt with unanswerable questions asserted itself once again, At the back of his head, moreover, was a feeling that really he knew all the time exactly where Mabel was, what she was concealing from him, and why she was concealing it; yet, further, that when she did reveal her secret it would prove to be something he had known all along quite well. What puzzled him a little, indeed, was why he hid this knowledge from himself?Why did he shrink from facing it? Why did he deliberately avoid it? Whence came this elaborate and artificial pretence? He raged, he shrank, he trembled. …

Then, suddenly, the reason for his attitude flashed clearly. He understood the monstrous thing: if he faced it, his terror would be too appalling to contemplate and live. He must go mad, or die.

That Mabel grasped this and, out of love for him, still consented to remain Lost, brought a measure of comfort to his anguished soul, though it was in vain he tried to grasp its full significance. The full meaning of the whole episode continued to evade him. That her remaining lost bore some subtle relation to the throwing of the moon, he perceived vaguely, but what that relation precisely was he could not, for the life of him, determine. The effort to understand at length exhausted him. He dripped with perspiration. …

With sharp, dreadful clarity, his intelligence then strangely opened, and—he knew.

Transfixed with terror, he could scarcely breathe. His voice failed him. He called out wildly, but no sound was audible. He screamed and shrieked for help, but no whisper left his lips. He was alone, entirely alone, lost in an infinity of emptiness. And—he was shining: a figure of light amid the Egyptian blackness of outer space.

He himself had been thrown away. He was falling, falling … and Mabel was aware of it. …

In those awful seconds before he crashed upon some point in ultimate space, the full significance of the moon’s return became at last quite clear. The revelation came with a final certainty there was no resisting. It was appalling beyond words. The Other Player, he realised, had held the catch—this time. But one day that catch would not be held. It would be missed. Another heavenly body would then be seized and flung, a constellation, perhaps the Pleiades, perhaps—the Earth herself!

“One day soon, we, too, shall be flung away!” he roared aloud, incoherent with the horror of his dizzy falling. But no sound left his lips. He heard instead—where, oh where, had she said this dreadful thing?>—the voice of his landlady:

“The Pleiades would scatter in a handful of golden dust!”

His terrified thought could not grapple with such fearful words. Meanwhile, he rushed and tore and fell. …

‘ ““Mabel!’’ he screamed, finding a strangled voice that hurt his throat in the effort to get out. ‘‘ Mabel! Look out, dear! Look out! He’s going to—miss!”

The odd thing—the first detail in the whole experience that occurred to him as really strange—the odd thing was that Mabel seemed quite unfrightened. She was not even interested, much less disturbed. She paid no attention to his frenzied warning, as she passed, prettily smiling, through the room. The sunlight fell on her smooth, comely body in its becoming bathing-suit that was dripping wet and clung tightly to her. She went very quickly towards the inner room to dry herself and put her clothes on. She came, evidently, straight from her dip in the sea, and it annoyed him that she had gone to bathe alone, without even letting him know that she was going.

This annoyance, however, lay far below his terror, barely recognisable at all. His terror usurped all other fecling. Even the frightful descent through empty space was quite forgotten. It was the smile on her placid, patient face that petrified him. The ghastly horror of it, its indifference, its gentle sweetness, its fatuous imperturbability, froze his blood.

He understood at last—everything.

The tossed moon, the stupendous arm and hand that clutched her, the horrible increase of the bathing-sheds, his own fierce fling through blackness towards some final crash of extinction—all, all had a reason, an explanation, which had been concealed from him with cunning and diabolical success by—Mabel, by his own stupid, loving, faithful, yet knowing wife.

Mabel knew. She knew everything. Also—she had always known.

Yet his understanding, even now, was not complete. God! Would he never understand anything completely?

He slowly turned his head. Mabel, in the act of passing out of the room, was looking back at him over her wet, shapely shoulder. The line of her delicious body enticed him. Her lips were moving. She was mentioning something—by the way, as it were:

“He has missed, dear! But, why bother … ?”

Mr. Anthony, shivering with cold, opened his eyes, rose from his indifferent shelter below the breakwater, and walked home rapidly to his cheerless lodgings. …

Railway Travelling in the Caucasus

Very practical some of the arrangements of this Caucasian train—some, not all, for in a first-class carriage the only light was a fag-end of a candle that barely enabled one to tell the time when standing up!

At the larger (!) stations the buffets are excellent and the time is ample to prove it. Hot bortsch, omelettes, various steaming meats, and delicious tea, cheese, and cakes, prices plainly marked, stood all ready on a counter. You helped yourself, carried your plate to a table, and were happy. A bell rings three times by way of warning—one stroke first, a few minutes after two strokes, about three minutes afterwards three strokes, and then the train moves out.

Moreover, the guard, in whose Mingrelian breast my Russian phrase-book and my struggles with the names of the stations stirred pity and amusement, lent me his timetable, giving time of arrival and departure at every little station, with the exact number of minutes the train stopped there.

Nor shall I ever forget the kindness of another Georgian, whom I discovered in the third-class as I walked through, who suddenly addressed me in French. Six feet high, bearded, Ills tcherkeska a perfect armory of weapon, his long nose suggesting more than Semitic sympathy, he strode up and informed me that he had once been guide, interpreter, and friend for an Englishman (Lord Somebody, whose name I never discovered, for he pronounced it like a sneeze) In Daghestan, but who knew no French. (“And why was that?” ho asked, “when France is at the door of London?”)

This warrior, without molesting me in any way, insisted on steering me through the bewilderment of Tiflis Station, finding cab and luggage, telling me exactly what to pay porter and coachman, and then strode off and disappeared In the darkness with the bow of an ambassador and a gentle haughtiness that made a tip an impossible offence.—

The Other Woman

Not that it was so particularly lovely, but that it was so astonishingly real, perplexed him. This reality, the conviction that he knew it intimately, were the reasons why its appearance troubled him, though trouble is perhaps too strong a word, since it woke a yearning sweetness too. The root of the strange emotion doubtless lay in this: that the face, while curiously familiar, was not known to him. He did not recognise it.

It would rise before his inmost vision as in a cloud of silvery mist ; memory would leap to claim it, pause, hesitate, and finally draw back in failure. ‘I know you intimately,” he would whisper, deep inside himself. I have always known you. But, for the life of me, I can’t remember who you are!’’ Comforted, blessed, contented, he would give up the puzzle with a sigh.

Where had he seen this face before? When had he met the original? Under what conditions of time and space had he known in the flesh this woman whose eyes gazed with such sweet, haunting invitation into his own? It was not a memory he could trace, try as he would ; it was not a dream— in his dreams he never saw her; she belonged to everyday working life and sunlight. Moreover, she was ever young. She matured, but did not age. In every true artist-soul lies something which is unageing. She kept pace in him with that.

She first appeared quite early in his life, in boyhood almost, but certainly when the boy slipped into the man: and he soon established the fact that it was invariably a girl or woman who evoked her. It was sufficient for a girl or woman to engage, OF threaten to engage, his heart, for this other woman to rise inwardly and take possession of him, with the result that the attraction of the moment faded, then wholly died away. The exquisite invasion brimmed his entire being, leaving nothing over or unsatisfied. Her seductive power was so great that against her mere silent appearance, before the gaze of those inviting, gentle eyes, no other charm, no passing fancy, at any rate, could stand a moment. His soul soared upwards towards her. She seemed to offer a perfection which became for him a test and standard for all lesser beauty.... Did she, then, resent intrusion of such lesser beauty ? Certainly she nipped in the bud each of his early love affairs, prevented serious attachment too. Absurd as it must sound, absurd as it was indeed, the Face forbade his marrying. His soul loved and yearned towards her alone. She became his faultless guide.

Having humour in his composition, he called her the Other Woman, and tried, but without success, to paint her. His skill, already famous, failed with each attempt. On the canvas she became too common- place to finish, much less to frame. She eluded him completely. Thus he was unable to convince his friends, who flocked to the studio, that she possessed the qualities, above all the reality, he saw and felt in her. Moreover, she prevented other pictures too, landscapes even, or imaginative renderings of his inmost being that were not absolutely true—born of his highest inspiration. She resented, in a word, he came to realise, any aspect of Beauty not of the purest, sweetest, that threatened possession of him to her own exclusion. She insisted upon a standard he could not always reach. He made his name among the few. He made no money.

The relationship, thus established and accepted, ruled his life. He loved, he worshipped, he obeyed this Other Woman who so elusively filled the imagined réles of comrade, wife, and guide. Yet she troubled, even alarmed, him sometimes. It was not the conviction of precious intimacy, but the puzzling failure to recognise, that alarmed him, suggesting some grave dislocation of memory. Somewhere he must have seen her original, perhaps in a picture, perhaps fugitive in the street, or at another’s house.

“You see, I know her," he told his friend, ‘‘ know her as well as I know my own mother. Yet I cannot recall her name, or who she is, or where we met, or anything about her. And that’s amazing—like for- getting all about the wife you love except that you know her, love her, and belong to her. Now—lI ask you!”

“But you’re a painter,’ the friend explained. ‘This is some ideal or other you visualise pictorially. It’s probably some childhood memory suppressed years ago. Find the original and it will cease to haunt you.”’

‘But she knows me, too, I tell you,” insisted the artist, already regretting the confidence given. ‘‘ That’s the uncanny part of it.’”” The other stared a moment with embarrassment. ‘‘ It is,’’ he repeated, as with a mental shrug of the shoulders. “It is a bit uncanny, as you say.” He changed the subject, and presently made an excuse to go.

The painter passed through many love affairs ; they had no result ; they interfered with his work ; they dimmed his sweetest vision as they passed; but each time, with the appearance of the haunting eyes that gazed so yearningly into his own, power was restored to him. Each frustration added to his power; he wasenriched. He wanted wife and children ... their lovely ghosts walked through his canvases. The artist soul is notoriously passionate and fickle, exacting too; the Other Woman led him victoriously, clean, unsoiled, through all adventure. To be false to her was to be faithless to the highest, deepest, truest, in his life. He suffered, but he did not fail her. He saw then in her dear eyes a new expression—majesty. His genius knew fulfilment.

“You say you have already tried to paint her? ”’ asked a wise woman who loved him for himself, but loved his genius more. ‘‘ Her expression would interest me enormously--?

“ Tried till I’m tired,” he interrupted. ‘‘ She fades instantly. Elusive beyond capture. That’s just it, you see.’’ There was a note of reverence in his voice.

“And pain--?’’ she asked softly, the sympathy of real understanding dangerously in her eyes.

He signified assent. “I yearn towards her,” he confessed, gazing at his companion as though he begged forgiveness, then gazing suddenly past her. “Tm beginning to think ” He paused; the sentence remained unfinished. Ineffable yearning filled his heart as the Other Woman rose in that instant before his inmost sight, exquisite, majestic, with her final, unquestionable power. The love offered him seemed tawdry by comparison. The full confidence was not given.

From his earthly eyes she remained concealed until the very end. It was at the very end only that he knew and recognised her. At the moment of death she gave herself into his full keeping, because she had already been in his full keeping always, and because he had proved faithful to her through all his minor faithlessness.

“ Forgive me,” he murmured, in the confused ramb- ling they mistook for incoherence ; “‘ forgive my times of doubt and question.... O my Great Loveli- NESS... « a)”

Beside the bed they listened to his whisperings : “Tt is worn thin with words.... I heard them discuss it often... the artist.... I see now it’s true.... Alone of men the artist has within himself the perfect mate. He needs no other. The feminine lies divinely in his being, his own perfect soul-mate....”

He held out his hands, raising his head a moment from the pillow.

“Tt was you, and only you, I really loved. I have been true.... O my Great Loveliness!’’ And, with a smile of joy upon his face, he went to meet her.

Sambo and Snitch

I

It was boiling hot in the garden and the twelve o’clock bell had been ringing for a whole minute when Sambo, aged six, popped his head out of the cowshed door and said, “Oh, bother!”

The bell meant that it was time for him to go indoors and rest till lunch. Topsy, his younger sister, had already heard it and gone in; he could see her fat, round figure waddling past the drawing-room windows in the distance. She liked going in to lie down, he remembered. That was because she was so round and fat probably; it was easier for her to lie down than stand up. Anyhow, he didn’t want to flop on a bed and rest. He wanted to stay and watch the calf, to stroke its head, give it hay, talk to it. He loved all animals. He understood what they felt and thought. And he was sure they understood him, too, when he talked to them.

The bell had stopped ringing now. Nannie’s voice was shouting for him instead.

Sambo sighed—oh, such a deep sigh. Then he said goodbye to the young calf, who blinked back at him understandingly, and walked slowly down the path towards the house. He heard Nannie shouting and shouting, but he did not answer. He just mopped his face.

“Why ever does Nannie go on shouting like that?” he said to himself. “I heard the bell long ago!”

And at that instant a large brown lizard darted across the path in front of him, so close to his feet that he almost stepped on it. There were pretty black spots on its back. Sambo loved these lizards, but he could never catch one. They went such an awful pace.

He stood still with excitement.

“Oh, I say!” he cried. “Here’s a lizard! Look at it, just!”

Now, as a rule, these lizards flickered down a crack in the stones as quick as light and vanished. But this one didn’t. It stopped. It might have been made of stone. It made no movement. Its brown back shimmered in the heat. One brilliant eye peeped up at him. He had never seen such behaviour before. There was something unusual about this lizard.

“If only I could catch it!” thought Sambo, and began to bend down very cautiously—then stopped in amazement and stared. For at this moment the lizard spoke.

“Something’s pricked my tail,” said the squeaky voice like a slate-pencil.

Sambo felt such a thrill run over his body that, in spite of the hot sun, he shivered. He didn’t know what to do or say. He kept perfectly still and waited.

“A hawk dropped on me,” continued the tiny thin voice. “I was down a crack in a twinkle, but I didn’t twinkle fast enough.” The voice became indignant. “Its beak pricked my tail!”

Sambo just stared and stared. Nannie and bells were all forgotten. His whole life was centred on the lizard. He felt an enormous surprise, yet at the same time it seemed quite natural that a lizard should talk—talk to him, at least.

“Well, why don’t you say something?” squeaked the lizard. “I opened the conversation. It’s your turn now.”

But Sambo’s tongue refused to move. The only things he could think of to say were? “How do you do?” or “Did it hurt?” and neither of these seemed quite right, he felt. Besides, the lizard sounded a bit angry now, and that rather frightened him. Lizards couldn’t bite, could they? He wasn’t quite sure.

“Pricked my tail, I told you,” repeated the lizard, its body still motionless, its bright eyes still peeping up at him. “The hawk did.”

Then suddenly he found his voice. His surprise left him.

“It didn’t,” he said, rather bluntly.

“It did,” said the lizard fiercely.

“It didn’t,” repeated the boy, and straightened up to his full height.

“How do you know?” squeaked the other. “You can’t see up there anyhow!”

“It didn’t,” Sambo said again, trying not to be rude.

“Prove it,” the lizard snapped in a voice of keen annoyance.

“Because you haven’t got one!” said Sambo flatly.

This seemed to upset the lizard dreadfully. Its voice rose to a still shriller note.

“What d’you mean?” it screamed.

“It’s gone!” was the answer.

At this the lizard moved for the first time. An extraordinary expression came into its pointed face. It turned its head to see. As its head turned, its body turned too, and of course the tail turned with the rest of it. It went faster and faster, till it looked like a brown wheel whirling. But it couldn’t catch up. It couldn’t see its own tail.

“I can’t see my own tail,” it panted presently, pausing a moment in its whirl. Its voice sounded rather disappointed, almost sad.

“Because it isn’t there,” explained Sambo sympathetically. “I told you once.” He was getting cross with it. “You’ve only got a stump left.”

Now, hardly had Sambo said this when he realized he had said an awful thing. He had. But it was too late to change it now.

“That’s rude,” said the lizard quietly. It was not angry, only hurt. “Worse than rude, it’s unkind. It’s like telling your mother she’s lost her looks, or her hair, or that she squints—something unpleasant that she knows, but doesn’t want to be told about.”

Sambo felt unhappy. Already he liked this lizard immensely. “I’m awfully, awfully sorry,” he said, mopping his perspiring forehead.

“Thanks!” squeaked the other instantly. “Now we’re friends again.”

It was the way his own mother forgave him always. He liked it.

“Are you a mother then?” he asked politely.

“Of course. I’m a female. All females with us are mothers.”

“Oh,” he exclaimed, remembering his Natural History lessons. “And you’re a reptile, aren’t you, too?”

“That’s our family, yes,” replied the lizard proudly. “I belong to the great reptile family, like the snakes and crocodiles. Oh, rather! I’m glad you know that at least.”

“—You lay eggs, don’t you?”

“—I should think I do. Little beauties!”

“—And may I have one, please, for my collection?”

“When I’ve got any,” was the reply, “you certainly may.”

The lizard kept silent then for a bit. It didn’t move. The boy kept silent too. He just watched it. It was still panting from its violent whirling after its own tail. He could see its little sides puffing in and out like tiny bellows. The brown skin rose and fell, the black spots with it. How amazingly still it kept! It might have been a stuffed one, except for its heaving sides.

Sambo waited for it to speak again, but as it said nothing, he presently made a remark himself.

“The hawk took it,” he explained kindly, referring to the lost tail.

“I didn’t twinkle fast enough down the crack, I suppose,” came the reply in a gentle voice.

“That part of you didn’t,” Sambo suggested. “The rest of you was like lightning. It always is.”

He heard the lizard laugh. It was like the queer sounds Father got on the wireless machine and called “Berlin” or “Madrid.”

“Oh, I know,” it said, when it had finished laughing. “You’ve often tried to catch me, haven’t you? But you can’t. I can always twinkle fast enough to get away from you. A hawk’s different. You don’t hear it coming, for one thing. It drops like a cannon ball, for another. Hawks like us very much, you see.”

“I see,” agreed Sambo politely.

The lizard thought for a moment.

“Now, will you please show me where I end?” it asked.

“There,” said Sambo, pointing. He was delighted to be of use to his new friend.

“Oh, you may touch me. Pointing’s no good. Touch the end of my body, please.”

It was exactly what Sambo had been longing to do. He bent down and put his hand out cautiously. He touched the dry little body on the stump of the tail. It felt like the ginger he got from dessert sometimes, only smoother and more slippery.

“Thank you,” said the lizard, with evident pleasure. “Now I know exactly where I end. Where I begin is easy, of course, but where I end is more important. My head may be safe down a crack, but my tail still in danger outside. Now I can twinkle again properly.”

“I’m awfully sorry it happened,” remarked Sambo, who now began really to love the little creature, “for you look all wrong without a tail.”

The same instant he felt he had said something rude again, but the lizard wasn’t angry.

“I look what I am,” it said cheerily. “And I feel all right. Besides, I can grow another. Only it takes time, and I haven’t been very well lately. You can see that for yourself, can’t you?”

Sambo couldn’t see, but he didn’t say so. He asked instead what was the matter with it.

“I’ve felt cold,” announced the lizard in a weaker voice, as though that proved it.

Sambo, who was perspiring in the blazing heat, gave a gasp. Was it pretending, he wondered?

“Cold!” he exclaimed. “Why, it’s simply hotter than anything. I’m boiling. I’m all wet!”

“Snitch!” said the lizard. “Snitch! Snitch!” it repeated, keeping one bright eye fixed upon the boy’s face.

He jumped. It was a most peculiar sound. It startled him.

“What does ‘snitch’ mean?” he asked politely.

“—It means nothing,” was the reply. “Just nothing at all.”

“Then why did you say it?” the boy insisted pluckily.

“I didn’t,” observed the lizard with a touch of impatience.

This was really too much. He wasn’t going to be humbugged like that. “But—I heard you!” he exclaimed with vigour.

“Look out!” squeaked the little reptile. “I’m going to do it again in a second!” It lifted its sharp head a quarter of an inch into the air, paused, shut both its eyes tight, and then suddenly repeated the peculiar sound twice over very rapidly: “Snitch! Snitch!” it went.

It gave a little laugh and looked up into his face. “That’s a sneeze,” it explained. “I told you I was cold.”

What Sambo might have said, will never be known, for at this moment his attention was distracted. Something fell with a click onto the path between them. The lizard remained motionless as a bit of stone, but Sambo lowered his head to find out what it was that had fallen from the sky. At first he thought it might have been a drop of perspiration from his face, but he soon saw his mistake. It was a little brown pointed thing. He stooped and picked it up.

II

“I say,” cried Sambo in amazement. “It’s your tail, I do believe!” He looked up quickly into the sky. “And there’s the hawk that dropped it!” The added. “Well, I never did!”

A big hawk, sure enough, was circling slowly in the air far above his head as if nothing had happened.

“Didn’t like the taste, I suppose,” he went on, his head still turned upwards.

“It’s the best part of me really,” said the lizard down at his feet. Its voice sounded rather faint and muffled. But Sambo was too excited to look down. He was a wee bit frightened too. What if the hawk suddenly dropped like a cannon ball on his head? He could never twinkle as fast as the lizard did! He watched it for a minute or two, holding the tail in his perspiring hand, and thinking of the sharp claws and dreadful beak far up in the blue sky. But the great fierce bird showed no signs of dropping on him. It just circled round and round lazily, hardly moving its big wings at all.

“Can’t you do something to frighten it away?” inquired the muffled little voice below.

Sambo bravely clapped his hands.

“Has it gone?” squeaked the faint voice.

“It’s going,” Sambo said, encouragingly.

“One of us must go, you see,” came the rather nervous comment.

“Yes,” agreed Sambo, “but please not you! There, it’s gone now—gone away over the woods by the Church. You’re quite safe again!”

He looked down to give the tail back to its owner. But the path was empty. He looked everywhere. The lizard was gone!

Oh, dear! This was very disappointing. Wherever had it gone? He looked and looked, but there was no sign of it. He missed it dreadfully. Already he was tremendously fond of this strange, friendly little lizard. He really loved it. He could have cried—when suddenly he caught its little voice again close beside him somewhere. It was faint and muffled.

Where on earth was it?

“Is that you, Snitch?” he called out. The name came naturally.

“Of course. I’m down here. Why don’t you use your eyes?”

It sounded offended rather, he fancied. The squeak seemed between his feet.

“Bend down,” it went on, “and you’ll see. I told you one of us had to go.”

Sambo knelt down and put his face close to the flat stones that paved the middle of the path. Something in the crack glittered, reflecting the sunlight like a tiny mirror. It was the lizard’s brilliant peeping eye.

“—Hooray!” he cried. “Hooray! I was afraid I’d lost you!”

“That’s what the hawk would say if he could see me. But he can’t.”

“The hawk’s quite gone now,” whispered Sambo. “There are only a few swallows about. You can come up again. Anyhow,” he added proudly, “with me here, it would never dare to drop!”

“I thank you,” squeaked the faint voice. “It’s cold as a cellar down here, anyhow.”

Sambo bent lower, formed his hands into a cup, and put them against the crack. “Crawl in here,” he whispered. “Please do.”

“I wish you wouldn’t whisper,” mentioned the reptile. “It sounds like running water. And I don’t like water.”

“Crawl in,” repeated Sambo in his ordinary voice. “It’s quite safe. Warm too.” He put his hands in the easiest position he could, leaving a tiny opening between his thumbs. “I’ve got the tail in my pocket all right,” he added.

Would the lizard trust him?

He waited a few moments. Nothing happened.

“Oh, but I say, do squiggle in, dear Snitch,” he urged. “My back’s aching so!”

“All right,” came the squeak. “You needn’t cry about it. I’m coming. I thought I was going to sneeze, that’s all. Now—one—two—three—Go!”

Sambo felt a warm, tickly sensation on his palms. Four tiny feet clutched his hot skin.

“I’m in. Thank you!” piped the little voice happily …

And at that minute the bell began again. It was ringing furiously. It rang as though the house was on fire.

“My gracious!” exclaimed Sambo. “I forgot all about it! Oh, what a row there’ll be!” He straightened up as though he had been shot up by a spring. “I’m awfully late,” he explained. “I’ve got to go indoors and rest, you see. Topsy went ages ago. I must run. Ill take you to my room.” And he ran as hard as ever he could towards the back door, keeping his hands tightly closed in front of him. “Hold tight!” he whispered as he ran. “Hold on. I won’t drop you.”

The lizard laughed inside his hands. “That’s nothing,” it squeaked. “I can hold on to anything! The faster the better! But I’d like a little more air, please. I’m suffocating. Besides, I’m going to sneeze in a second!”

Sambo opened his fingers a tiny bit.

“Snitch! Snitch!” went the lizard, as the boy kicked open the back door and ran panting up the back stairs into his bedroom.

Now, at first, Sambo had meant to tell all about the lizard. He meant to tell everybody that a lizard could talk. It was such a very wonderful thing to happen. It was far too marvellous to keep to himself. Nannie and Topsy must hear all about it at once.

But when he entered the room, he changed his mind. He was hot and breathless. The green blinds were drawn. It was rather dark. Topsy, he saw, lay on her bed in the corner, looking like a boiled pudding in its cloth. She was asleep. There was an unpleasant silence. He heard nothing but a fly buzzing up and down the windowpane behind the green blind. And—he saw Nannie!

Nannie stood in the middle of the room, staring at him. Her arms were akimbo, and he knew what that meant. She was going to scold. She was waiting for him with what he called “a string of words.” And Sambo, knowing quite well he had been disobedient, felt afraid. He decided to say nothing. He would keep it all a secret. He held his hands in front of him as naturally is he could. If only the lizard wouldn’t sneeze!

Would Nannie ask him for an explanation? Would she want to know why he was so late? What in the world should he say? He never told lies.

“Didn’t you hear the bell, Master Sambo?” Nannie began at once. “It rang loud enough. Where were you? What have you been doing all this time?”

He just stood and gazed at her. He said nothing. He kept his hands pressed against his “tummy,” hoping it looked natural. The lizard never moved foot.

“The cowshed,” he mumbled. “I’m sorry, Nannie.” But he knew by Nannie’s tone that she did not really expect an answer to her questions. She was just scolding. He was really very fond of her. She was talking in a whisper too, and that meant she wasn’t frightfully cross. He felt tremendously relieved.

“Well, another time you must come quicker—the moment you hear the bell,” her whisper continued across the still room. “It’s very naughty of you. Your sister came in long ago. Now, be quiet. Don’t wake her. And lie down at once and get your rest. You naughty little boy, you!”

She hadn’t noticed his hands then after all! The perspiration was trickling down his nose, but he couldn’t wipe it away. It trickled cold against his back as well, but he couldn’t scratch there either. Oh, dear! If only Nannie would go out of the room for a moment. He couldn’t possibly lie down with his hands held like that in front of him. Nannie would discover everything. He stood without moving, waiting for an inspiration.

Then a terrible thing happened.

The lizard sneezed.

“Snitch! Snitch! Snitch!” it went inside his hot hands. Sambo remained stock still. He thought the end of the world would come. But the next instant he saw that Nannie hadn’t heard. His heart had stopped beating; it now began to bang against his ribs. And with the sneeze came a brilliant inspiration!

“Nannie,” he whispered, “I wonder—if I’ve got a cold. Can I have some of that sweet medicine, please? I’m shivery. I feel shivery.”

It was quite true. He did feel shivery.

“A cold!” exclaimed Nannie, still whispering. “However can you have a cold on a broiling hot day like this?”

“I believe I have,” repeated Sambo. He sniffled as well as he could. Nannie stared at him. He sniffled louder. Oh, if only he could have sneezed! But he didn’t know how to. He knew anyhow what a fuss Nannie made when there was any sign of a cold, or even when there wasn’t. He also knew that the sweet medicine was kept on a shelf in the bathroom—across the passage!

He sat down on the edge of his bed. There was a moment or two of terrible uncertainty. To his immense relief, then, Nannie moved slowly towards the door.

She was going to fetch the medicine!

“Oh, you’d better have a dose, perhaps,” she whispered impatiently. “It can’t do you any harm, I suppose. But mind I find you in bed when I get back.”

And she went out.

Quick as a flash Sambo whispered to his four-legged friend: “I’ll slip you into my tumbler, Snitch,” and he was across the room in a jiffy, opened his hands, and saw the lizard dart into the empty tumbler on the washhand-stand.

“Put my tail in with me,” it squeaked nervously.

And Sambo just had time to find the little fragment in his pocket and obey, when he heard Nannie’s footstep outside the door again. He gave an enormous sigh of relief—but for an instant only. A new horror seized him. Nannie might want his tumbler for the medicine! Oh, it was awful! He stood hesitating for a second. If Nannie found him still out of bed, she would scold. But if she found the lizard—she would throw it away … !

What was he to do? Oh, how difficult life was when you had secrets!

“Take me with you—quick!” he heard a faint, hurried squeak. And a second later he was lying on his bed, with the tumbler just below the edge of his pillow, and well out of sight.

Snitch had saved the situation just in the nick of time. Oh, he loved his lizard more than ever now. Faithful, clever little reptile!

Then Nannie came in. She brought another tumbler with her after all! He drank the sweet medicine, nearly choking in his excitement, so that some of it ran down his neck and onto the pillow. But Nannie didn’t notice this. The room was too dark.

“—Now go to sleep at once,” she ordered, and tiptoed out of the room.

III

Sambo pretended to sleep. The only sound for some minutes was that tiresome fly buzzing up and down the windowpane. …

The room lay dark and warm, for the green blinds only let in a narrow line of sunlight round the edges. Topsy lay sound asleep, more like a boiled pudding, he thought, than ever. The fly buzzed on and on. From the garden, sizzling in the midday heat, came the murmur of bees. The leaves were still. The whole house lay silent.

Sambo presently sat up on his bed and listened. Nannie’s footsteps had now died away down the passage. There was no sound. The servants had strict orders to keep quiet in this part of the old house while the children slept. Sambo gave a sigh of relief.

He glanced over at Topsy. He always told her everything; they shared all their adventures; and he had meant to tell her this. But now he hesitated. At any rate, he couldn’t wake her at the moment. She’d make such an awful noise, for one thing. Yet, if she didn’t see the lizard herself, and hear it talk, she never would believe him. What should he do?

The familiar squeak interrupted his thoughts:

“More air, please, Mithter!”

It sounded rather thick. He lifted the pillow’s edge and took out the tumbler. The lizard, he saw, held the bit of broken tail in its mouth. That explained the indistinctness.

“Thank you,” it said, dropping the tail and running swiftly along the edge of the sheet to where the sweet medicine had been spilled. Its tiny tongue shot out and licked it.

“What’s good for your cold is good for mine,” it said, evidently enjoying the taste.

Sambo watched it. “You are a funny lizard,” he said in a low voice.

“—And you are a funny boy,” remarked the lizard.

The same instant it picked up the tail and wriggled with great swiftness over the bolster and dropped onto the floor. “I mutht be off,” it squeaked.

“Oh, oh!” cried Sambo, bitterly disappointed, “you’re not going, are you? Please don’t go!”

“Yeth, Mithter, I mutht,” it said thickly. “Thank you all the thame!”

“But I was going to stick the tail on,” pleaded the boy. “I’ve got secotine, you know.”

The lizard evidently dropped the tail from its mouth, for its next words were clear again.

“I’ve got something better still. I can grow a new one. And I want the broken bit as a model.”

Sambo leaned over and tried to see it, but against the dark carpet it was invisible. He only knew by its voice whereabouts it was. The disappointment was more than he could bear. He simply couldn’t let his wonderful little new friend go out of his life like that. It would be too dreadful!

“But you’re not going for good, are you?” he asked, and there were almost tears in his voice.

“Do you like me as much as all that?” inquired the voice from the carpet.

“I like you more than that. I love you,” Sambo implored. “I do really.”

“Oh, all right,” piped the lizard, with a happy little laugh. “I like you too. So I’ll come back.”

Sambo felt happier. Only he still had so many questions he wanted to ask that he didn’t know which to begin with.

“—Where are you going to?” he began quickly.

“Out,” was the short reply. The voice was farther away now.

“The door’s shut—” said the boy.

“The window isn’t,” came the answer. And the squeak was still farther away this time, quite near the window in fact, where the fly went on buzzing up and down still. “I can run down any wall that was ever built. Up it too, for that matter.”

“Then you’ll come back that way. I’ll always keep it open for you,” Sambo said quickly. The time was short, he felt.

“Can’t promise,” came the answer from a new position now. It was climbing up to the windowsill already. “Down the chimney’s just as good a way—in summer. In winter, of course, I hardly come out at all.”

“How shall I know, please?” the boy asked next.

“Oh, I’ll make a sign. And I shall call you Mister. I’m carrying my tail in my paw now,” it added. “That’s why I’m going so slowly.”

Sambo felt dreadfully sorry it was going, but there was nothing he could do to stop it. It had promised to come back. He liked the name of “Mister” too.

“Well, dear Snitch, goodbye,” he said in rather a sad voice. “I’m awfully glad I saved your”—he nearly said “life,” but changed it in the nick of time to “tail,” It was true anyhow. He had saved its tail.

“Though am I,” piped the tiny voice, much farther away now. “I thall never forget that.” Ah, it had picked up its tail again.

Sambo had been just going to ask for something in return, but was too proud. The next thing the lizard said made him glad he hadn’t shown that he expected a reward.

“And I’ll do thomething for you thome day,” it added gratefully. “Goodbye, Mithter!”

Sambo just had time to call quickly, “What sign will you give?” and to hear its answer “Snitch!” when he caught a flash of shimmering brown across the narrow line of dazzling sunlight beneath the blind—and the lizard was gone.

Now Sambo was a very observant little boy. As the lizard twinkled out, he noticed two things. First, that it had pronounced the S in its name distinctly, and therefore had opened its mouth; and, secondly, that the buzzing fly no longer buzzed!

That meant, he felt sure, that the buzzing fly had gone out with it—but inside it—gobbled up with a lightning thrust of the pointed little mouth.

The broken bit of tail, therefore, might be now lying on the windowsill. He crawled off his bed to look. Yes, there it lay. He picked it up and put it carefully away in an empty box of tooth-powder. Then he put the box away in a drawer where he kept his treasures. Then he crept back on tiptoe to bed. Then, in due course, he fell asleep.

Sambo woke up next morning expecting to see Snitch looking at him from the windowsill. Not a bit of it. There was no sign of the dear little lizard. It was probably having its breakfast somewhere, he decided. What did it eat for breakfast? He didn’t know. Not porridge and eggs and marmalade anyhow. It drank water and ate a fly most likely. Sambo kept his eyes and ears wide open all that morning, but Snitch did not appear. In his pocket was the little box with the tip of its tail. He often took it out and looked at it when nobody was about. Sometimes he rattled it, thinking it might hear and answer. But nothing happened. The whole day passed without a sign of it.

But Snitch had promised to come back. Sambo knew it would keep its promise. “It’s gone hunting perhaps,” he decided. But female lizards didn’t hunt. “Or having some babies,” he changed his explanation. Anyhow it was busy. Meanwhile, he kept his secret to himself. He told no one, not even Topsy. “Females divulge,” he once heard a man saying to his father. He didn’t know quite what it meant, but it had something to do with telling. Topsy, being a female, might divulge. It meant telling secrets anyhow.

The next day it rained, and lizards stayed at home when it rained, Nannie told him. She also answered lots of other questions he asked, though she had to look at a big book first. Lizards, she read out, were reptiles; they belonged to the great family of crocodiles, snakes and that sort of creature, and snakes were simply lizards that had lost their legs. A slowworm, which they sometimes found on the road, was a legless lizard. They laid eggs, lived on insects, and slept through the winter in some little hole or crack, because in the winter there were no insects for them to eat. There were only two kinds of lizards in England, one called the Sand Lizard, because it lived in sandpits; the other called—but Nannie couldn’t pronounce the name, so she stopped reading out a minute from the big book. “It’s about seven inches long,” she went on presently …

“That’s mine!” he exclaimed excitedly.

Sambo seized his opportunity at once. “Thank you very much, Nannie,” he added. “I’ve heard enough.” And he was out of the room like a flash, for the rain had stopped, the sun was blazing, and he had a feeling that Snitch might be about.

IV

Sambo stood in the hot paved sunken garden, where the flowers smelt sweet after the rain, and there were lots of cracks between the stones. He stared about him.

“Snitch!” he called softly. “Snitch, dear, where are you? I’m all alone. Which way have you gone?”

No answer came, but the words ran on in his mind into a little rhyme. He began to sing this little rhyme to himself in a low voice:

“Dear little Snitch,
I’m all alone!
I wonder which
Way you have gone?”

He sang it over again, and only stopped because a fly kept settling on his neck and tickling him. Once he thought he heard a tiny laugh. But nothing stirred: he saw no movement on the stones. Besides, Snitch had promised to give a sign. He would hear it say “Snitch!” when it was there. Was it angry with him because he had asked so many questions? He had been rather rude, he remembered, and it was certainly a little annoyed. But he had a thousand more questions to ask now.

Bother! There was that fly tickling him again! He smacked his hand down on the back of his neck, but instead of catching the fly, he only hurt himself. Now, if Snitch had been there it would have caught that fly in a second, thought Sambo. Snitch was quicker than lightning. The fly tickled him again, and he smacked his hand down again.

“Snitch!” he heard suddenly. “It isn’t a fly at all! It’s me!”

Sambo turned round so sharply that he nearly fell down. He was so excited he could hardly believe his ears.

“Where are you?” he cried. “Quick! Tell me!” For at the same instant he heard Nannie’s voice coming round the corner of the house. And Topsy was with her. “Oh, let me see you! Where are you? Please, please!”

“Here!” was the reply in a tiny squeak. “On your shoulder, of course. I’ve been tickling your neck with my nose for a long time.”

“You were the fly!” gasped Sambo. “I might have hit you!”

He twisted his head and neck, and there, sure enough, was his little friend perched on his shoulder, his pointed face peeping up with tiny sparkling eyes.

“I was the lizard,” it snapped. “Please be accurate. And another thing—you couldn’t hit me if you tried all day. Even the hawk only nipped my tail. You’re not a quarter as fast as a hawk.” It giggled close beside his ear.

“Oh, you are a little beauty!” exclaimed Sambo. “I knew you’d turn up. You promised, didn’t you?”

Nannie and Topsy came into view as he spoke, round the corner of the house.

“Oh, be quick, be quick! Hide, or they’ll see you!”

Snitch giggled, as he gave the boy a tiny nip with his little mouth in the neck, but so gently, it was almost like a kiss.

“I am a beauty,” it squeaked. “I did promise. I have turned up. And I am quick—so quick that you’ll never hit me, and they’ll never see me!” And the same instant, quick as a lightning flash, it darted down his shoulder, scuttled along his back, ran with the speed of flight along his arm, and settled finally into the hollow of his hot hand, where Sambo felt at once the queer little tickle of its tiny paws.

“Close your paw,” Sambo heard, “and remember—no one but you can hear my voice. The others can’t. You hear me because you love me.”

Sambo closed his hand immediately, but only just in time, for Nannie at that moment reached him, stared at him, put on an expression as though he was doing something he had no right to do, and said in a rather cross voice:

“What’s that you’ve got in your hand, Sambo? You’ve been picking up something dirty as usual I suppose, and you’ll make your clothes in a mess. Open your hand. What is it you’ve got there?”

Topsy, who was beside her, leaned forward to see what it was. She wished she had picked it up, whatever it was. Sambo always had all the fun and excitement.

Sambo, always obedient, held out his hand. But at first he didn’t open it. If Nannie saw the lizard, she would make him throw it away. She would probably scream as well. He would never be allowed to touch a lizard again. So, obedient but very cautious, he just held out his hand and did not answer. He felt hot and cold all over. He was fairly caught now. He shut his lips tight.

Then, suddenly, and before Nannie had time to say anything more, he heard a faint squeaky voice that sounded far away and muffled:

“Turn your hand downwards with the palm to the ground. Then, when I sneeze—open it!”

Sambo obeyed, “Sambo,” said Nannie, certain now that he had picked up something horrible, and speaking more sternly, “Sambo, I told you to open your hand. Open it at once and let me see what you’ve got there. Some nastiness, I’ll be bound.”

“Snitch!” came the signal agreed upon, but so faintly that no one heard it except the boy.

His closed hand was held downwards with its back uppermost. He opened his thumb and four fingers and held them spread out for Nannie to see. “Turn your hand over,” Nannie told him. “Show me your palm.”

Sambo did so. His heart sank. But before his hand was round he felt a tiny sensation in his palm, then on his wrist, then along his arm, as far as the elbow, and next over the skin of his back and shoulder till it reached his neck, where it stopped. It took only a second or two to turn his hand over as Nannie told him to do, but when his palm lay open before her eyes—there was nothing in it.

Quicker than a flash of light, the wonderful little lizard had darted up his sleeve and inside his shirt. It had escaped. The open palm Nannie examined was quite empty.

“There’s nothing there,” said Sambo in a faint voice, looking very innocent. Nannie looked rather foolish, and Topsy gurgled disappointedly like an echo of her brother: “But there’s nothing there! Oh, Nannie, what a sell!” They moved off slowly towards the mulberry tree, where Nannie then sat down in a wicker chair, while Topsy went to hunt up the tortoise, Percy. The hot sun had dried the grass. The whole garden steamed. Red Admirals and Peacocks came fluttering over the pinks and roses …

But Sambo, bursting with admiration of his wonderful little friend, stood stock still and waited. Snitch had saved him marvellously. He stood and waited, breathing hard, his hands hanging down beside him. Then, suddenly, his palm tickled. He lifted his hand. Snitch lay there cosily between the thumb and little finger. It was laughing.

“You see, I can always save you,” it squeaked, “if you do what I tell you.”

“Thanks awfully,” the boy stammered. “I always will. But—how on earth could you go at such a rate?”

The lizard ran up his arm, across his shoulder and coat, and settled on his blue sailor tie: “That’s not the only question you want to ask,” it said, peeping up into his face over his chin. “You’ve got a hundred others, I know, because I heard Nannie reading out from the book about my family. I was in the chimney all the time. I like the chimney when it’s raining. Well now, get along with it. Hurry up and ask your questions.”

“You were in the chimney!” gasped Sambo, too surprised at first to ask the hundreds of questions that seethed inside his brain.

“I’ve been watching you,” went on the lizard, “ever since we first met. I wanted to be sure you were worth knowing. I’ve never been far away. I heard you singing. I’ve watched you awake and asleep. I had to make sure, you see, that you were worth it—worth being my friend, I mean.”

Sambo felt very uncomfortable. He was usually naughty, he knew.

“And—am I?” he asked faintly.

By way of answer, Snitch darted up over his chin, reached his lips, and gave him a tiny kiss. The next second it was back again on his blue tie, as though it had never moved. “Let’s sit down now and talk,” it squeaked, as though nothing had happened. “Then Nannie won’t think you’re up to mischief—eh?”

V

Sambo was too pleased and surprised to argue; he was too excited as well; he ran over to the wooden bench in front of the morning-room window and sat down. On the iron table, where his father and mother had drunk their coffee after lunch, lay the newspapers. Snitch shot down upon the page giving the theatrical news. Having settled itself, it glanced up at him sideways: “Now,” it piped, “go ahead. I’m ready.”

But Sambo, wanting to ask a hundred things, found himself suddenly dumb. He remembered all that Nannie had read out, and he wanted to ask what time lizards got up in the morning, what they ate and drank, how they lived together and what their houses were like, what sort of eggs they laid, how they managed all the winter without food, how they made their tails grow again—oh, and a thousand other things as well. But the only thing he could think of at this moment was the funny bit Nannie had read out about lizards losing their legs and turning eventually into snakes. Snakes, she had read out, were simply lizards that had decided they could get on better in life without legs, and so had given up using them till they finally disappeared. This was the only thing in his mind at the moment, but somehow he didn’t quite like to ask it. He hesitated.

“It’s quite right to think before you speak,” snapped Snitch, “but time is passing, you know. Nannie’ll be yelling for you in a minute. Hurry up!” Sambo took a deep breath and clenched his hands. “I only wanted to ask,” he said in a low voice, “whether you—that is if you expect—to lose your legs—someday?”

There! He had said it! He wondered what would happen. Would Snitch be offended, perhaps hurt as well? Would it snap at him … ?

Instead it burst out laughing. Oh, how it laughed! Its laughter rang out like the tinkling of silver bells. Its music floated across the sunlit garden like tiny falling drops of water, so that the swallows hovered a moment to listen, and even the Red Admirals and Peacocks looked up a moment where they were drinking honey from the clematis and seemed to wink at one another.

“Bless the boy!” cried the lizard in its highest squeak, “what a question!” Its sides were panting with its merriment. It was not a bit offended. “Yes, yes,” it went on jerkily, wriggling from side to side on the newspaper paragraph about Shakespeare and Bernard Shaw. “Yes, yes, of course I shall—in time. Only, not today or tomorrow. It takes thousands of years to make a change like that. The slowworm you saw last week in the road—the poor little thing that frightened you because you thought it was a snake and would poison you—that old harmless slowworm, a hundred thousand years ago, was a lizard, just as I am now. Then it found it could manage better without legs, and so gradually its legs, from want of use, disappeared, you see. Only it took a hundred thousand years for that to happen. I shan’t lose my legs today or tomorrow!”

It laughed so that Sambo thought it was going to burst. He began to laugh with it, though he hardly knew exactly why he laughed.

“Why, a million years ago,” piped the lizard between its bursts of laughter, “you men—you human beings—all had tails! You lived in trees. Yes, you did really. Then, gradually, you began to live on the ground more. So you didn’t need your tails to hang from the branches by. You learned to walk upright. And your tails, slowly, after thousands of years, disappeared!” The lizard stopped. It had laughed so hard that tears had run from its eyes, tiny little drops of silver that smudged the print of the theatrical paragraph about Bernard Shaw and Shakespeare. It raised a paw and quickly dried each eye. Then it glanced up and said: “So there! Now you know something you didn’t know before, eh?”

But Sambo was not a silly little boy. He liked being told things he didn’t know. It all puzzled him a bit, but still he felt it was probably quite true. His father had told him that animals and plants were always changing, only he didn’t know they took so long to change. But the idea that men had once lived in trees appealed to him. He wished he still had a tail.

“So that’s why I like climbing trees, Snitch, is it?” he asked.

“You still just remember the old days, yes,” came the answer, “when you lived like monkeys. You wear clothes now instead of hair, and you cook your dinner instead of eating it raw, and you live in an expensive house with ten rooms instead of in a cosy little hole or crack with one room—but—” it began to laugh again like a shower of silver bells—“but your human world isn’t so very far apart from ours, you know, after all,” it went on, “and you needn’t feel so superior about it—”

Sambo could think of nothing to say. He felt bursting with ideas. His mind seemed splitting. Then, not quite knowing why, he suddenly asked: “Snitch, dear, why do you tell me all this?”

In a flash the lizard left the newspaper and seemed to disappear. The same second almost it was across his shoulder and perched beside his ear. It was half inside his ear. He felt its breath tickling his skin. “I’ll tell you,” it whispered, “because I like you and trust you, and because I know you like me.”

“I do, indeed, dear Snitch,” the boy said quickly. “I really love you.”

“Exactly,” replied the lizard in its tickly whisper. “Well, the truth is that I’ve always wanted to know more about the world you humans live in, only I never found anybody I could trust enough to ask. You’re the first that hasn’t thrown stones at me, or tried to hit me with a stick, or wanted to put me in a cage. So, if you’ll let me, I’ll come with you sometimes into your funny human world, and see how you all behave, and what you do. And I’ll tell you about my world in return. Is that a bargain?”

“Yes, rather,” began Sambo—but before he could say any more, he felt that tickling sensation down his neck, then along his bare leg, then—well, he just heard a tiny squeak somewhere on the ground, but when he looked down there was nothing to be seen. Snitch had vanished like lightning. He was alone. And Nannie was calling to him across the lawn.

The lizard came a great deal into the house during that summer. It was full of tricks. Sambo never knew what it would do next. One day it would wake him up early by biting his toe in bed, another it would pop its muzzle over the edge of the blackboard and say “Hallo, Mister!” while the children were making their letters with the chalk. Once it lay along a black note on the piano when Sambo’s mother was teaching him his notes, and there was a wet afternoon in the Nursery when he heard it saying “Here I am, Mister!” dozens of times before he discovered it finally on the top of the brown clock, looking exactly like an ornament—a metal lizard. It had been there for half an hour without moving.

No one ever saw it but Sambo.

“That’s the way to hide,” it explained. “Keep quite still and no one notices you. Choose a background of the same colour as your clothes and you’re very hard to see—almost invisible.”

“But I’m rather big for that,” the boy objected.

“All human beings are too big,” grumbled the lizard. “If you were the same size as us you’d be much happier. There’s no sense in being so big. If you were small like me you’d need less food, you could live in smaller houses, use much less stuff to clothe you, and life would be much easier altogether—”

Instead of finishing its remarks, it suddenly shot up the curtain by the window and hung motionless. It was some minutes before even Sambo could pick it out, for the curtain was brown and the lizard’s body did not show against it.

“What’s up?” the boy asked in surprise.

“I am,” replied Snitch. “Just in time too!”

Before Sambo could say anything else, the door opened and his sister, Topsy, came in. But it wasn’t Topsy that had frightened the lizard. It was something else that came in with her—Mrs. Tompkyns, the yellow cat.

Snitch had heard the cat’s soft tread in the passage!

Topsy had come to fetch something. She blundered about the room a moment, upset a pile of books, knocked a chair over, banged against the fender and made the tongs fall down with a clatter, tripped over the carpet and fell down herself, found the pencil she was looking for under the table, picked herself up again and went out, slamming the door behind her.

“That’s that!” remarked the lizard from its perch, looking down sideways at the cat. For Mrs. Tompkyns had not gone out. It sat licking itself in front of the fireplace, one leg stuck in the air like a ship’s mast. Apparently it was interested in nothing except cleaning itself. But the lizard knew better.

“And that’s you!” added Snitch, keeping its keen eyes fixed on the great yellow Mrs. Tompkyns. “I see you! And—you see me!”

“You can’t fool a hawk or a cat,” it went on, talking to Sambo in its slate-pencil little squeak. “They see everything. Dogs are slower, and you human beings slowest of all. But hawks and cats—” it gave a shiver, “are almost as sharp as we are. So I take no chances. It can see me up here, but it can’t get at me—she, I mean—and she’ll never make a sign. She’ll just go on washing, and pretend she doesn’t see me. But the instant I come down—pop! she’ll make a dart and a pounce—and goodbye Snitch!”

At this moment Mrs. Tompkyns turned her head sideways. She had heard something. She left her leg sticking up in the air, but she was listening. She seemed to be admiring the wallpaper. “You can hear me, and you can see me,” piped Snitch, “but you can’t get at me.”

Mrs. Tompkyns turned her head towards the door, her back to the curtain. Apparently it was the closed door she found so interesting.

“That’s all humbug,” piped the lizard from its safe place. “You’re just pretending. I know your little game.”

The cat’s whiskers twitched, but she made no other sign.

“Little tiger, that’s what you are,” went on Snitch. “I heard your step in the passage in spite of Topsy’s thumping feet. So I popped up here for a change of air. Now, I tell you what you’d better do—go and catch that mouse I hear nibbling in Nannie’s room across the landing. Because you’ll never catch me, you know.”

Sambo, who loved Mrs. Tompkyns, had crossed over to stroke her yellow back. She was purring. She looked as innocent as a baby.

“Open the door and put her out,” went on Snitch. “You’ll see I’m right. I can hear the mouse.”

Sambo obeyed. He opened the door, lifted the big cat with an effort and put it in the passage. Mrs. Tompkyns, pretending this was just what she wanted, paused a moment, then walked majestically down the passage towards Nannie’s door which stood ajar. There she sat down and began to wash her cheeks with a wet paw, as though nothing else in the whole world concerned her.

“Just pretending again,” piped Snitch against the boy’s ear, for the lizard had darted across the floor and climbed up him. Sambo turned his head in amazement. “Now, look again!” whispered Snitch. And, sure enough, in that instant while he turned his head, Mrs. Tompkyns had vanished. Carrying the lizard safely on his shoulder, he peeped into Nannie’s room. There was the great yellow Mrs. Tompkyns crouched down over a tiny hole in the boards where a mouse had been nibbling, no doubt, a moment before!

“Now we’ll go back, thank you,” said Snitch, “and don’t forget to shut the door, please.”

VI

Sambo shut the door tight and then went back to the Nursery, Snitch still perched safely on his shoulder.

“Well, I never … !” he exclaimed, full of wonder and admiration, for the lizard’s skill amazed him.

“What d’you mean?” inquired Snitch. “You never what? But shut the door first, please,” Sambo banged it. “Now you can tell me what you mean,” Snitch added. It had climbed down his back, run across the carpet, shot up the leg of the table, and was curled round the inkpot on the brown tablecloth, so that he could hardly see it at all. It was quite motionless. “What d’you mean by ‘Well, I never!’?” it asked.

Sambo fidgeted. He tried to collect his thoughts. “I meant,” he mumbled at length, “that I never knew anything like it. …”

“Like what?” snapped Snitch. It seemed annoyed.

“The pace you go, and the way you keep so still, and the way you hear everything, and the way you hide, and—”

“That’s enough,” interrupted the little reptile, now mollified. “But all that only surprises you because you can’t do it yourself. It’s natural to us. My life’s a danger from the moment I’m born. If I wasn’t quick and couldn’t hide, I’d be caught and eaten; but nothing wants to pounce and eat you. You’d taste horrid, anyhow.”

“Lions and tigers would,” objected Sambo, wondering a moment how he would really taste, but not referring to it. “Only, of course, there aren’t any here.”

“And they couldn’t get into houses if there were,” the reptile said, shortly. “You’re safe in houses. Besides, even outside, you’d hear them coming. They roar. But cats and owls and hawks and snakes don’t make much noise before they pounce. If I hadn’t such sharp hearing, I’d be caught before I was a week old.”

Sambo listened with keen attention, deeply interested. “I see,” he put in.

“But I see better still,” went on Snitch, rather annoyed at the interruption. “Thousands of years ago we had a third eye, you know. It was on the top of our heads, so that we could see above us into the sky. It’s gone out of use now because there are very few hawks left—there used to be millions—and we don’t need it. Two eyes are all we want now. Besides, the things that pounce on us are pretty big, and we easily see them coming. Mrs. Tompkyns, remember, seems as huge to me as an elephant does to you.”

“You pounce on things too,” said Sambo suddenly. “To a fly you must seem enormous—”

He stopped dead. He had said something he oughtn’t to have said, evidently, for the lizard suddenly left the inkpot and was behaving in an extraordinary way. He had been watching it with his elbows on the table and his chin in his hands. Snitch now crawled over the cloth and stopped just beneath his face. It then rose slowly on its hind legs, balanced itself carefully with the help of its stumpy tail and began to swing sedately to and fro. Its head turned up, pointing the sharp muzzle into his face. It closed one eye. The tiny mouth opened. A faint sound came out like “Madrid” on the wireless. It was singing:

“To mention size
Is very rude.
I pounce on flies
Because they’re food.”

There was no tune, but just a sort of queer little singsong, and as it swayed to and fro it waved its front paws in the air, it sang the verse over and over again. It was very odd indeed, thought Sambo. It wasn’t really angry, he decided.

“I’ll get you some flies, shall I, Snitch?” he asked, hoping to make up for his mistake, and looking at the window where a bluebottle was buzzing up and down the pane.

The lizard stopped singing. “I wish you wouldn’t interrupt,” it spat at him. “I can get flies myself when I want them. I want one now. That’s why I sing. I always sing when I’m hungry and on the hunt. When you’re hungry, you cry. That’s the difference between us.”

It began its monotonous song again, swaying to and fro rather more violently now. The sight fascinated Sambo. He stared and stared. At the same time he noticed that the big fly had stopped buzzing on the glass.

How many times Snitch sang that verse over and over again, Sambo could not say. It may have been a hundred times. He only knew that it made him feel drowsy as he listened. The queer, swaying dance had the effect of making him heavy in the head. His eyes began to close. Snitch swung and swung like the pendulum of a clock. It never stopped. The boy grew heavier and heavier, drowsier and drowsier. He vaguely realized that the same thing was happening to the fly. … The fly was getting drowsy.

Suddenly there came a pop, a bang, a splash! The sound stopped dead, the singing ended. There was silence in the room. For a second Sambo couldn’t make out what had happened. He rubbed his eyes. Then he felt that his nose and forehead were sore. His cheeks were wet too. He passed his hand quickly over his face—black! He had dropped asleep and his face had fallen forwards into the inkpot. The ink was spilt all over the table, over his shirt and cheeks and nose and forehead. It was on his lips and in his mouth. He was a sight!

He wiped the ink out of his eyes and stared about him in a state of fright and bewilderment. The lizard, he noticed, had gone. The fly had also gone. The room was empty. He was quite alone. He was covered with ink. What could he do? To upset the inkpot was an awful crime and Nannie would be very angry. He would be punished. He wanted to cry. But instead of crying he suddenly thought he would try and sing, as the lizard had done. So he stood in the middle of the floor and began to pipe up:

“Dear little Snitch,
I wonder which
Way you have gone?
I’m all alone … !”

He sang the verse over and over again, but just as he was singing “I’m all alone” for the fifth time, he heard a noise behind him. The door had opened. The room seemed full of people. First of all he saw Topsy, standing against Nannie’s skirts and giggling. Then he saw his mother. Last of all, he saw Mrs. Tompkyns, rubbing against his mother’s dress. He wasn’t “all alone” after all!

Covered with ink, he stood in the middle of the room, while all these people stared at him in amazement with their mouths wide open. There was going to be an awful row. He knew that. He could think of nothing to say. He just stood there and stared back at them all. If only he knew how to hide as the lizard did! But he was too big. Also it was too late.

“Sambo!” said his mother in a solemn voice, “What is the meaning of this? How did you get all over ink like that?”

At this moment, while Sambo was wondering what in the world he was going to say, a tiny voice piped in his ear: “Don’t be frightened. Just tell the truth and you’ll make them all laugh. You needn’t mention me, of course.”

“I fell asleep,” mumbled Sambo, “and my head banged down against the inkpot and upset it.”

There was a moment’s silence. Then Topsy’s giggle became audible. Nannie, too, was grinning, her handkerchief stuffed into her mouth. The next moment his mother began to smile. It was really impossible to be angry. Sambo looked too funny to be scolded. And so the laughter became general, and even Mrs. Tompkyns had a twinkle in her bright green eyes. Sambo laughed too.

“Nannie,” said his mother, “take this Black Sambo away and wash him white, and put the inkpot out of reach for the future.”

But while Sambo was being scrubbed hard in the bathroom by Nannie, who puffed and blew like a grampus as she lathered his black face with soap, he heard a funny little squeaky voice over by the open window. It was the lizard at its tricks again. It had run round outside the house, climbed the wall, and was now perched on the windowsill, looking like a bit of dark wood:

“When you want to cry,
The very best thing
Is to shut one eye
And begin to sing!”

“Oh, Nannie, listen!” cried Sambo, his mouth half full of soap. “That’s Snitch singing to me!”

He said it without thinking in his excitement. He had betrayed his friend. But Nannie, luckily, didn’t understand. Evidently she heard nothing of the tiny little voice.

“Keep your head over the bath,” she cried, laughing, “or I’ll never get you white. And don’t talk nonsense about snitches, or whatever you call ’em!”

This made Sambo laugh so that he swallowed a good deal of soap and water, and nearly choked. He felt very happy anyhow. The lizard evidently felt happy, too, for he heard it piping away while Nannie dried his head:

“She’ll get you white,
Don’t be afraid!
I’ll come tonight
When you’re in bed.
I had my fly,
You had your fun,
You didn’t cry:
Sambo—well done!”

And a couple of hours later when he lay between the sheets, the little box with the broken tail in it under his pillow, he kept his ears wide open for a sign of the voice he expected to hear in the darkness.

VII

To tell the truth, Sambo never understood quite what happened that night. The whole experience was too wonderful. He knew Snitch would come because it promised, but he couldn’t know exactly when it would come. It seemed ages before Nannie left the room, and still more ages before Topsy fell asleep. But at last the door was closed, Nannie was gone, and he was alone with Topsy and the night-light.

Now Topsy was full of questions. She would not go to sleep. She had somehow guessed that something was up. She noticed Sambo’s excitement, probably because he could not hide it altogether. She wanted to share it with him. “What’s on, Sambo? You’re waiting for something, I know. Can’t I do it with you?”

Sambo was very fond of his fat little sister. They always played together. The lizard was the first thing he hadn’t shared with her. And tonight he suddenly wanted her to know it all. It would be twice as much fun if Topsy knew. Only Snitch, he felt, didn’t want her. She was a female, and females, Snitch had warned him, divulge. He did not dare to tell his sister without first asking permission. So he decided, the moment Snitch appeared, he would ask if Topsy could be in the secret too.

Meanwhile the minutes passed, the house grew stiller and stiller, the night darker and darker, the candle burned lower and lower, and Topsy got sleepier and sleepier. Nannie opened the door softly once and peeped in, but hearing no voices, thought the children were safely asleep. The door closed again. The footsteps died away.

“Won’t you tell me, Sambo?” came Topsy’s last drowsy whisper. And Sambo answered in another whisper, “All right; I’ll try, Topsy. When you’re asleep, I’ll ask about it. Will that do?”

A very faint “Yes” was heard, and the next second Topsy was in the land of dreams. She always went to sleep like that—all of a sudden. The room became quite still now. Nothing stirred. The candle flickered, the shadows danced, the curtains hung motionless. There wasn’t a sound except Topsy’s breathing. She made a noise just like a kettle boiling.

Sambo watched and waited and listened. His eyes were all over the room, his ears were strained to their sharpest. He thought of nothing but the lizard, but as he waited he began to get very sleepy too. The minutes passed.

“I wonder when it will come … ?” he said to himself for the hundredth time, in a very low voice. Then a faint noise startled him, so that he sat bolt upright in bed and stared about him.

“I’m not it. I’m she,” he heard distinctly. “Please be more respectful.” It was Snitch. He knew the jolly little voice at once. But he couldn’t see the speaker, stare as he would.

“Oh, hooray! You’ve come! But where are you, please? I’m very sorry for calling you it. I won’t do it again. And, please, I want to talk about Topsy.”

Sambo said all this in one breath, speaking in a whisper. But before Snitch could answer, he saw her—lying along the dark iron rail at the foot of the bed.

“I’ve been here all the time,” piped the lizard. “I saw you both say your prayers and get into bed. I look just like a bit of the iron rail, don’t I?” she added proudly. “Nannie almost touched me once.”

“Exactly,” said Sambo with admiration. “You’re simply wonderful.”

“Thank you,” replied Snitch, and ran along the counterpane towards him. “It was a bit risky, but I always keep my promise. So here I am.”

There was a pause. Sambo glanced over at his sleeping sister. He longed to get her into the secret, but he was afraid Snitch would refuse. For a moment he said nothing, Snitch said nothing either. Topsy snored, more like a boiling kettle than ever.

“Get on with it,” remarked the lizard presently. “I heard your conversation, remember.”

Sambo drew a deep breath, but still was a little afraid to ask. Then he made a great effort: “Please, Mrs. Snitch, may I tell Topsy that I know you? We usually do everything together, you see. I feel such a pig, leaving her out.” There! It was done.

Snitch hesitated and cocked an eye. “I like you for asking,” she observed. “Most little boys, of course, are pigs,” she added.

“Oh, I’d love it so if Topsy knew,” put in Sambo quickly. He didn’t mind being called a little pig a bit, for he felt it was rather true.

“She’s a female,” objected Snitch, cautiously turning a sharp muzzle towards the other bed.

“But so are you,” said Sambo, sticking up for his sister. “Aren’t you?”

“Yes, but I can balance,” came the odd reply, not a bit offended.

“Balance!” repeated Sambo. He didn’t understand.

“You see, tonight I’m taking you on an adventure. We’re going out. And to go out safely, I’ve got to make you my size—as small as I am. I don’t often go out at night, of course, but this is an exception. I feel like an adventure. You do, too. Now, you see—your sister—is—rather round and fat. When I’ve made her small enough she’ll be nothing but a little ball on legs. We shall go in some funny places. She might lose her balance—and roll.”

This information excited Sambo to such a point that he felt he was going to burst. An adventure! Going out! Out into the night, out into funny places! And to be made small first! The same size as Snitch! It sounded all too wonderful to be true. For a moment he could think of nothing to say, though he really wanted to yell with delight and excitement. So many questions came rushing into his head that he asked none of them. All he could manage was: “Oh, Snitch, dear, wonderful Mrs. Snitch!”

“Thank you,” squeaked the lizard, wagging her tiny head with pleasure, for evidently she liked being called “Mrs.” “But the point just now is—your fat little sister. She’ll be rather a risk. She might roll off a wall, or slip into a hole, where we’d never get her out again, or—”

“I’ll look after her,” interrupted Sambo proudly. “Like I always do.” Snitch ran up his sleeve and settled on his elbow. “Now, that’s right,” she piped. “I like you for sticking up for her. Do you mean that you don’t want to come unless she comes too?”

Snitch waited for his answer several minutes. The temptation was very severe. Sambo longed to go out on the adventure with all his might. At the same time he felt he would be really a little pig to leave Topsy behind. And, oh! she would enjoy coming so much! Yet, if he insisted on her coming, Snitch would probably refuse to go at all. “Thank you very much, Mrs. Snitch,” he said at last in a rather faint voice, “but I don’t want to come—unless—Topsy—comes too.”

For a few moments there was silence in the room, broken only by the snoring of Topsy in the corner. Then Snitch popped up suddenly onto Sambo’s shoulder, raised her mouth, gave him a tiny nip in the neck with her wee teeth, and whispered into his ear:

“I hoped you would say that, Sambo. Now I know I can trust you. You’re true to Topsy, so you’ll be true to me. I’ll take her. We’ll go together, all three!”

At this, Sambo felt so happy that he picked up the lizard in his fingers and gave it a kiss.

“Thank you,” piped Snitch, when he put it down on the bed, “but you needn’t waste time doing that. We’ve a lot to do before we’re ready to start. I’ve got to make you both small first. We must all be the same size or we shan’t be able to get into the same places. Besides, you can’t see in the dark as well as I can, and you’d soon lose me. Have you got my tail?” she asked in a whisper.

“Rather!” Sambo hopped out of bed so quickly to get the box that his foot caught in the sheet and he fell full length on the floor.

“There! You might have squashed me!” squeaked the lizard. “Lucky I’m so quick, isn’t it! Now you understand why we’ve got to be the same size!”

“I hope Nannie didn’t hear,” the boy gasped, as he picked himself up and ran to get the box.

“Oh, she’s having her supper in the kitchen,” explained the lizard. “But it’s lucky you didn’t wake your sister. She’s got to be made small after you. And in the dark too. We must put the night-light out first.” And with a sudden whisk of her whole body, Snitch darted up the saucer, raced across the burning little wick and squashed it down into the soft wax before the flame had time to burn her. The room was now in complete darkness.

“There!” she squeaked, running almost the same instant along Sambo’s arm, till she reached his hand that held the box. “Now, open it and I’ll take the tail out. I can’t make you smaller without the bit of my tail, only I must do it in the dark, because it’s a secret, and you mustn’t see how I do it.”

Trembling with excitement, Sambo had now opened the box. He felt the lizard run past his fingers. The same instant he felt it run out again.

“Thank you, Mithter!” he heard.

Snitch already had the bit of broken tail in her mouth.

VIII

For several minutes nothing happened. Oh, how still it was! The blackness of night covered all. Nothing stirred. The deep silence was broken only by the knocking of Sambo’s heart against his ribs. He tried to hold his breath. Bang! Bang! went his beating heart.

Suddenly he became aware that the kettle had stopped boiling. Topsy, that is, no longer snored. She was waking up. Probably she’d make an awful fuss, he thought—bubble and squeak with excitement and ask a hundred questions. As a matter of fact, when the time came, she did nothing of the sort. She took the whole affair as calmly as though it happened every day. And this, Sambo decided next day, when he thought it all over, was very queer.

At the moment, anyhow, he heard the little bubbling grunt she always made in the morning when she opened her eyes. But he heard something else as well that was not his fat, round sister. A tiny voice was speaking—singing rather. He listened intently. He recognised the voice. Mrs. Snitch, the broken tail still in her mouth evidently, was chanting the spell in the darkness that was to make their bodies small. It went to the tune of “Now we go round the Mulberry Bush:”

“Make me though thmall
That I can crawl
Along a wall
Without a fall.

Make me though neat
That hands and feet
May flash along like lightning!”

The words floated through the darkness like the faint buzzing of a bee.

“Thay it after me,” came the order in a whisper close beside his ear. “And touch my tail—the broken bit—at the thame time. Ith in my mouth, ath you can hear.” And Snitch darted up the boy’s finger so that he could feel in the darkness where its mouth was.

Sambo obeyed. His finger ran along the cold scaly back till he felt the pointed head and muzzle. Very gently, using his little finger, he found the broken bit and touched it. At the same time he sang the words:

“Make me so small
That I may crawl
Along a wall
And never fall,” etc.

And as he sang, repeating the verse over and over again, this strange thing happened. He felt himself shrinking, shrinking, shrinking. It was too dark to see anything, of course, but he knew he was shrinking because he presently felt the long hair of the bearskin rug beside the bed tickling his cheeks. The queer bitter smell he noticed too. He had smelt it before, of course, when playing bears with his father, the rug all over his face, but the smell had never been so strong as this. He was, evidently, close to the ground, the long coarse hair about him like a forest.

While all this was happening in the pitch black room, Snitch was attending to his sister. The lizard had long ago left his hand and darted across to Topsy. She was fully awake now. Sambo already heard her gurgling voice, very low but quite distinct, singing the words with him. She, too, was being made small. It was a powerful spell. It worked quickly. The next minute he felt something touch him in the darkness. It was a hand. Topsy was feeling for him. He put out his own. They found each other’s fingers. They shook hands.

“Now, all together,” came the voice of Snitch, close beside them on the ground. “Only, instead of ‘make’ the word is changed to ‘keep.’ ”

Sambo noticed that Snitch pronounced the s. The tail had been dropped. “Take my paws,” added Snitch, “my front paws, and beat time by swinging your hands up and down while we sing.”

There, in the darkness, the three of them holding hands, they sang together, keeping their voices very low, the wonderful spell that was to keep them small:

“Keep me so small
That I may crawl
Along a wall
Without a fall.”

“Keep me so neat
That hands and feet
Along a wall
May flash along like lightning!”

Their hands—and paws—swung up and down to keep time. They sang the little song three times.

“That’s enough,” interrupted Snitch, just as they were beginning it again.

“Each time means an hour. You’re small for three hours now. Hooray!”

“I’m as small as a ball,” announced Topsy, speaking for the first time.

“But I can’t see anything. How small are you, Sambo?”

She felt no surprise, apparently; it was all natural enough. And Sambo felt the same. He saw no reason why he shouldn’t be small like his companions. Everything in the world was either small or big compared with something else. He was big compared to an ant anyhow, occurred to him.

“Oh, I’m all right,” he replied. “Bigger than a beetle anyhow. I feel all darty. I could flash away like lightning—if only I could see.”

“I only hope I shan’t roll,” said Topsy. “I’m awfully round—rather hedge-hoggy—”

A shrill noise stopped her. It was Snitch screaming.

“Hush!” cried the lizard. “You mustn’t use that word. Hedgehogs and snakes eat us—sometimes. We never mention them. It’s bad language. Like swearing with you.”

“Sorry,” said Topsy quickly. “I didn’t mean to be rude.” Then, as the lizard’s front left paw stroked her hand to show forgiveness, she added “Thank you.”

“Forgiven and forgotten,” squeaked the lizard briskly. “And now listen to me, please. Listen carefully. I’ll give you the programme for tonight. We’ve got just three hours for our Adventure, and I think it would be more fun to go out than to stay indoors. Don’t you?”

“Rather!” exclaimed both children in the same breath, while Topsy added: “If you’re sure nothing can catch us and eat us!” Her hand stole into her brother’s and held it tightly.

“And if we can see our way,” put in Sambo, gripping his sister’s fingers to comfort her. “It’s frightfully dark.”

Snitch burst out laughing. “You’re much too fast for anything to catch you,” she explained, “for you can dart away now as quick as I can. You’ll be safe under any stone. I’ve arranged about light too. Wait here a moment while I run and see. I’ll be back in a second. Don’t move, remember.”

And she was gone. They heard her rapid feet across the carpet, but they made more noise than usual. Their ears picked up all sorts of sounds—sounds they never could have heard three feet up in the air.

They lay among the thick hair of the bearskin rug, waiting in the darkness for the lizard’s return. They could see nothing.

“Sambo,” whispered Topsy, “I’m awfully excited. Aren’t you?”

“Oh, yes,” replied the boy, as though adventures like this were no new thing to him. “I thought you’d like to come too. Mind you don’t say anything to hurt her feelings. You won’t, will you?” he repeated.

“But what ought I to say to a lizard?” Topsy asked, greatly impressed.

“What sort of things?”

Sambo, of course, didn’t really know. Only he mustn’t let her see that he didn’t know. “Oh, just be polite,” he whispered back; “very polite is best.”

“Say I’m sorry, you mean?” she enquired.

Her brother hesitated. “I beg your pardon would be better, I expect,” he told her. “It’s what Mummy says. And you might add R.S.V.P.”

A sound interrupted their whispered conversation, and Topsy snuggled in closer to her brother’s side. But it was only Snitch coming back. They heard the hair on the rug swishing and rustling like leaves of a tree as the creature came darting through it to their side. Snitch felt them over with her front paws to see where they were.

“I wasn’t long, was I?” she said, a little breathlessly. “Well, everything’s ready. I’ve got the Lights. They’re coming. And we’ll go by the window instead of the stairs and hall.”

“Window!” gasped Topsy.

“The window and the wall, yes,” replied Snitch. “It’s safer. The window’s open at the top, and it’s a good wall with lots of cracks and niches. We’ll slip down it. The Lights will follow us. Are you ready? Come along then!”

Sambo was bursting with questions, but he had no time to ask them. He felt Snitch pulling him along through the thick hair of the rug, across the carpet, whose roughness tickled his tummy, then up the leg of the table, which he knew stood close by the window, and next, with a flying leap through the air, onto the windowsill itself.

It was all so swift, so breathless, so extraordinarily light and easy that he simply hadn’t time to think. He had shot and darted along like lightning. Yet all the time he held onto Topsy’s hand. He never for a moment let her go. She came after him like a ball from a ping-pong racquet, rolling, bouncing, tumbling along, her feet twinkling like a fly’s wings, while she grunted, panted, gurgled and puffed. Whew! What a flying race it was! The way they flashed up the table leg, then shot through the air from the table to the windowsill was marvellous. How their feet had clung to the polished surface of the table leg he couldn’t understand. He only knew that there was no difficulty about it. Why, he could have run up a smooth wall, he felt.

“We’ll rest a second now,” he heard Snitch saying. “Then we go up the window, out through the crack at the top, down the wall, and into the garden. The Lights will be here in a moment.”

Sambo and Topsy stood panting and breathless beside their guide. They hadn’t enough breath to speak at first.

“I’d better prepare you,” Snitch went on, “for what you’ll see when the Lights come. You’ll see me, for instance. It needn’t frighten you. I shall look rather—er—big, perhaps.”

But already Sambo had become aware of something beside him with enormous bulk. He just made out this huge shadowy mass, for here on the windowsill the starlight gave a faint glimmer, and the outlines of things were clearer than when he was on the floor. It was as big as himself, as big as—as a crocodile. Yet Snitch’s voice came out of this immense dim outline. It moved then. Good heavens! It was Snitch, but Snitch as big as a—crocodile!

“Don’t be frightened,” the lizard said quickly. “Of course I’m big now. I seem big like this because you’ve grown small. You’ve come down to my size, you see. I’m just the same as I was before, really, only you’ve got smaller. I haven’t changed at all.”

Sambo gasped. He wasn’t frightened, but he was too amazed to speak at first. So this crocodile beside him was Snitch! His own head stood level with its huge scaly back. Its eyes were as big as his own. Its tail ran away into space. Its paws were tremendous. He looked down at himself then. Well, he couldn’t tell how big he was, or whether he was big or small. He only knew that he and Snitch were about the same size. Next he looked at Topsy. She was the same size as himself. She was lying on her back resting after their fierce rush to the window. She looked like an egg with two short legs poking out below and two short arms above. The starlight was too dim to show more than her oval outline. Then, suddenly, she began to grow clearer. Something was happening. The light grew stronger.

“Sit up,” Sambo called to her. “Sit up and look. It’s all right. Nothing to be frightened about.” He stretched his hand out to help her. She took it and began to roll over and over, till finally she found her feet and stood up.

She stared about her in the growing light. Then she gasped too.

But what made Topsy gasp with amazement was not, as with Sambo, the great size of the lizard. This didn’t seem to strike her so much as the size the room had grown to. The furniture, the window, the table and chairs, the height of the ceiling—this was what struck her more than anything else. She realized the changes differently from the way Sambo realized them. She realized, for instance, that she and her brother had become very small, rather than that Snitch had become very large.

She opened her mouth to ask a hundred questions, when Snitch stopped her quickly.

“Don’t ask questions,” the lizard said. “Everything will explain itself as we go along. Besides, here are the glowworms. We can go ahead now, if you’re rested. We’ll go fast this time,” she added, as though the pace before had been nothing.

Glowworms! So that explained the increasing light!

Outside the window gathered a flock of moving lights, faint and beautiful. There were about twenty of them, and they gave out a dim, gentle glow. They danced and hovered in the air outside the glass.

“The glowworms,” explained Snitch. “They’ll come with us—ten in front and ten behind—to light the way. And when there’s danger, they go out.”

“What sort of danger?” whispered Topsy, snuggling closer to her brother and feeling for his hand.

“Oh, the night creatures,” replied the lizard: “owls, nightjars, perhaps a cat that hasn’t gone to sleep, or a wandering rat—anything like that on the look out for food. But there’s nothing to be afraid of. At the least hint of danger I give the sign, and the glowworms put their lights out. In the darkness, of course, we can’t be seen. We’re safe, provided you keep still. Now, watch,” added the lizard. “I’ll give the sign to show you.”

“What is the sign?” asked Topsy.

“A sneeze,” was the reply. And the lizard, raising itself on its front paws, which seemed gigantic now, suddenly sneezed.

“Snitch!” it went. And instantly all the Lights went out. It was so dark that the children couldn’t see each other. Topsy and Sambo held hands very tightly, waiting. Then the lizard repeated the sneeze, doing it twice this time, very rapidly: “Snitch! Snitch!” it went. And instantly the Lights came on again.

“There!” said their guide, “now you see! Only remember that when the Lights go out you must keep still—absolutely still. You mustn’t move a muscle till they come on again. If you do that you’ll be perfectly safe. Understand?”

“Yes,” whispered the children. “We understand.”

“Good,” said Snitch. “Then we can start. Come along!”

It was up the side of the window like a flash, and Sambo, seizing his sister’s hand, was after it. They raced up, darted along the top of the open sash, perched on the dizzy edge a second, then scuttled headfirst down the framework between the panes and landed safely on the stone ledge outside. It was a breathless business. Topsy fairly bounced along. She was very surefooted for a ball!

“Now,” said Snitch in a low voice, “the quicker the better—in case we’ve been seen. Something may be watching us; you never know. The Rule is, When Lights are on, move fast; when Lights are out, keep still. Got it? Better say it after me to make sure.”

The children repeated the Safety Rule together: “When Lights are on, move fast. When Lights are out, keep still.”

“That’s right,” whispered Snitch approvingly. “I’ll go first now, and you follow. Join me on the lawn. The Lights will go down with you.”

There was a flicker of the great tail, a chuckling laugh, a swift rattling scuttle of four marvellous feet—and it was gone into empty space.

Sambo and Topsy peered over the edge into the gulf of darkness. How smooth the wall looked! What a height it seemed! The garden lay below them far away, looking like a dim map spread out. They could smell the earth and flowers.

“Don’t hesitate,” rose up a tiny voice out of the gulf. “Head first. Use hands and feet. Now—one … two … three … go!”

IX

With his heart in his mouth, Sambo moved towards the dizzy edge. The floating Lights moved with him, so that he could see every detail, every crack and niche. The glowworms grouped themselves in the air close about him. He was very frightened, to tell the truth. But he didn’t forget his sister. Even in his moment of fear before the terrible descent, he remembered Topsy. He must help her, if he could. “Give me your hand, Topsy,” he whispered, “or your foot, if that’s easier.”

His sentence was hardly finished when, to his amazement, Topsy slipped past him without a sound, and disappeared over the edge alone. She rolled into space. Ten of the Lights instantly detached themselves and followed her down.

“I’m all right, young Sambo!” her voice floated up to him with a gurgle. “It’s quite easy. Come on!”

She was already halfway down, and Sambo was ashamed to hesitate any longer. He crawled to the edge, put a leg over, found a crack for his foot—and was off. The Lights floated down with him, helping him to find the niches and rough bits he could cling to. It seemed a long way, but he got down at last and felt his feet on the gravel path that skirted the lawn. He drew a deep breath, thanked his stars he hadn’t slipped, and looked about him to find his sister and the lizard.

A few feet beyond him he saw the group of glowworms that had accompanied Topsy down the wall, and he was in the act of running across to join them, when there came a sound that set every nerve tingling in his body.

“Snitch!” he heard, close in the grass beside him.

It was the warning, and it rang out sharp and clear. There was danger somewhere. The same instant every Light went out, as though an electric switch had turned them off.

Sambo stood stock still in the darkness, holding his breath. He remembered the Rule: When Lights are on, move fast; when Lights are out, keep still! He kept as still as a mouse. What was the danger, he wondered, and how had the lizard discovered it? Where was it? From what side would it come? Was it an owl, a snake, a rat?

He stared as hard as he could. He could see nothing but the gigantic house, the towering cedars on the lawn, the huge rhododendron bushes. All these, of course, now seemed enormous compared with his own tiny body. The blades of grass all round him rose to his shoulder, for he could feel them touching his cheeks, but the house and trees looked like mountains reaching to the sky. He saw the house clearest, because its walls were painted pale yellow, and glimmered through the darkness. Against this pale yellow wall he now became aware that something was moving. Its bulk was great. It seemed as large as a cow. It was alive. It moved slowly, stealthily. What in the world was it?

Sambo was frightened. Shivers ran down his back. Although the big thing moved so delicately, he could just hear the soft thud of its feet on the gravel path by the wall. It stalked along. No stone was disturbed. It planted its feet most carefully.

Frightened though he was, however, he again remembered his sister, for if he was frightened, she must be simply terrified. And though the Rule warned him not to move, he could not help trying to see if he could find her with his hand and comfort her.

Very cautiously he stretched an arm out between the blades of grass surrounding him. Against his hand he could feel the rough edges of a dandelion leaf. He could actually hear the sound as it scraped along his skin. He trembled as he heard it. Tiny though it was, it seemed quite loud now that he was so close to the ground. At the same moment he felt a warm soft thing clutching his fingers. Only by a miracle did he keep back a scream.

And then he knew—it was Topsy’s hand. She, too, had been groping for him in the darkness. The two hands clasped one another tightly, and Sambo heaved a deep sigh of relief. His hand, he knew, would comfort her.

But that sigh, quiet as it was, had been heard. The scraping of the dandelion leaf had probably been heard too. For the Stalking Outline stopped instantly. For a second it kept as still as though it were a stone. Then the great mass moved forwards. The whole black bulk of it moved towards him—slowly, stealthily, silently—nearer and nearer, till it stood within a foot of Sambo and his sister. Large as a cow, it towered over them, and in the upper part of its great body were two large round discs that flashed with a queer greenish light. These great discs were turned straight upon the two cowering children. They were discovered. The monster stood glaring down at them.

Then, suddenly, Sambo knew. The discs were eyes. The monster, of course, was Mrs. Tompkyns.

Now, both children were brave. Topsy was brave, because she had no imagination and never dreamed anything would hurt her; and Sambo was braver still, because he had imagination—he realised how a thing might hurt him, yet faced it just the same. Anyhow, it was Topsy now, in this terrible moment, who acted first. Any moment, of course, the great cat might pounce on them, thinking they were mice because of their size. But Topsy never thought of that. She loved and trusted Mrs. Tompkyns. The cat’s gigantic body didn’t frighten her.

“It’s old Mrs. Tompkyns,” she whispered with a gurgling little laugh. “Let’s get on her back, Sambo! We’ll climb up by the tail—”

She never finished her sentence. What happened, happened so quickly, and with such appalling noise, that Sambo hardly knew what it was. Afterwards he knew, but at the moment it just seemed as if the house had fallen, or the great cedars had come crashing down about them. One thing he heard clearly, but only one—the voice of the lizard. Its shrill squeak penetrated in that instant above all else:

“Run for your lives! Go in opposite directions. Hide under different stones!”

Immediately following the words came a queer whistling sort of sound, a great shaking movement among the blades of grass, a scuttling of flying feet—and the lizard had darted past the children towards the cat.

It was all like a hurricane that strikes a forest of trees, for the blades of grass bent this way and that, scraping their rough edges noisily together, while the thud of feet on the lawn was like thunder. There was a tremendous roar and scuffle, and the only thing Sambo knew was that, while he seized Topsy’s hand more tightly than before, and tore away with her to hide in the darkness beneath a stone on the path, he caught sight of Mrs. Tompkyns flying through the air above his head. He could see the whole black mass of her rushing past against the stars. It was followed by a crash that shook the ground. Then came silence again, a silence of the grave.

Sambo felt about for his sister, for he had lost hold of her hand in that wild dash for safety. The big stone now covered them nicely. No one could see them.

“Here I am,” whispered Topsy. “Old Tompkyns made a bad shot, didn’t she?” And she giggled happily beside her brother. She snuggled up close to him again. “I’m glad we came to the same stone,” she added. “Aren’t you, Sambo?”

Sambo was still too excited to think clearly, or realize quite what had happened. He was still panting.

“Has she disappeared?” he asked breathlessly. “The cat, I mean.”

“Rather,” Topsy told him. “Snitch did it on purpose, I think.”

“Of course,” Sambo agreed, though he didn’t quite know what she meant yet, nor what the explanation of everything was. “She’s in the middle of the rhododendron clump, where old Tompkyns can’t follow her,” added Topsy, gurgling her delight.

And then at last it dawned upon Sambo what had happened. Snitch had realized their danger, had guessed that the cat might take them for mice and pounce upon them, and so had deliberately drawn attention upon herself. She had made a noise on purpose. Mrs. Tompkyns had suddenly caught sight of her—and jumped to catch her. The cat, of course, had jumped right over their heads, clearing them easily. The crash and noise and scuffle were now explained. But Snitch, laughing in her sleeve, had flashed away like lightning, and Mrs. Tompkyns had just landed upon an empty patch of grass where there was no lizard at all!

“Snitch risked her life for us,” declared Sambo, proud and pleased that at last he understood the whole business properly. “We should have been a bit squashed, you know, if the cat had fallen on us. You would, at least,” he added.

“Hark! What’s that!” Topsy interrupted him.

They listened. A queer, wailing noise was audible in the distance. It came from the direction of the stables behind the house. It sounded at first, they thought, like a human voice, but the next moment they recognised it for what it was—a cat. It was caterwauling.

“It’s old Tompkyns cat-a-walling on the stable walls,” announced Sambo, using the long word as he believed it was really meant. “She’s given up. We’re safe again. Snitch will be back any minute now.”

“I hope so,” replied Topsy, crawling out from beneath their stone.

Sambo followed her. “Look!” he cried. “Look, Topsy! The Lights are on again!”

Topsy clapped her tiny hands with delight when she saw the group of floating pale green Lights dancing about over their heads.

“That means the lizard will be back any minute now,” she laughed, as she rolled her way towards the lawn again, Sambo leading the way. “The old thing’s as quick as lightning—”

“Quicker, you mean,” snapped a shrill voice. “And if you speak of me again like that, I shall make you bigger and send you back to bed!”

It was Snitch, who had darted up across the lawn. She was, of course, offended. For a moment an awkward silence fell on them all. Sambo was horrified at the way his sister had spoken. He felt ashamed of her. Naturally the lizard’s feelings were hurt at hearing herself called “old thing.” And he was just going to talk severely to Topsy, when he saw her rolling quickly up to Snitch’s side and holding out her two hands.

“I’m very sorry, Mrs. Snitch,” she said in a whisper. “I beg your pardon.” Then she added “R.S.V.P., R.S.V.P.,” twice over.

“Forgiven and forgotten,” Snitch answered at once, to Sambo’s great surprise and happiness. He had expected a row. “You’re a female. All females have sharp tongues. I’m one myself.”

“Thank you, Mrs. Snitch,” whispered Topsy, “and I won’t do it again.”

Snitch laughed. “Perhaps not,” she snapped. “But you’ll do something worse. Anyhow, forgiven and forgotten. So let’s get on. The Lights are burning again. We’ll move fast.”

“Thank you for saving our lives,” put in Sambo quickly. “You did save them, you know. It was wonderful.”

“Oh, that’s nothing,” said the lizard. “I can always fool a cat.”

“If that was nothing,” exclaimed Sambo, “what’ll something be like, I wonder?”

“You’ll see,” was the reply. “Now give the ball a push, and let’s move fast.”

Sambo caught Topsy by the hand, knowing she was the ball referred to, and that Snitch was making fun of his sister by way of a little revenge, and followed Snitch across the lawn. The dew was heavy. The big drops on the grass half soused them. But they puffed and panted along, following Snitch’s ever-vanishing tail, and so presently reached the gate into the field.

Here Snitch paused. The two children paused beside her, trying to recover their breath. They looked about them. The Lights had scattered, so as to be less noticeable. In a group they might draw the attention of some hunting owl, but separate like this there was nothing to attract any night-creatures that might be on the prowl.

Beyond them, in the field, Sambo saw that the grass was much thicker and taller than on the lawn. It looked so high, indeed, that he felt sure he would never be able to get through it, much less help Topsy rolling at his heels. The lawn was tiring enough, but this huge grass, rising like a forest, alarmed him.

“Mrs. Snitch,” he whispered, “we—we feel rather small, I think, to—to go fast through that.”

Snitch, motionless beside them, made no sign that she had heard. There was no reply, at any rate. Sambo nudged his sister. “You say something too,” he whispered in her ear. “Something polite—very polite, mind.”

The ball rolled over, for Sambo had nudged her harder than he knew. Topsy, now lying on her back, rose to the occasion and did her best. “Please, Mrs. Snitch,” she gurgled, “I beg your pardon, but couldn’t you make us a little bigger? R.S.V.P.”

Still there was no reply, nor did Snitch stir a muscle. Her great back lay like a log in the deep grass; her tail stretched away into the gloom of the thick stems; her eyes stared straight in front of her. Holding hands, the children waited for what seemed a long time. Then the lizard slowly turned her great head and looked at them.

They saw that the bit of broken tail stuck in her big jaws.

“Thay after me,” she said, “thith verth. And touch my broken tail at the thame time:

“Pleathe make my figure
A little bigger—
About enough
To clear the rough.”

Sambo and Topsy obeyed at once. Raising their hands, they touched the bit of tail and repeated the words of the spell.

But nothing happened.

“Thut your eyeth,” said Snitch severely.

They shut their eyes tightly. Everything was black.

“—Now try again,” they heard.

Again they repeated the spell:

“Please make my figure
A little bigger—
Just big enough
To clear the rough!”

There was a curious swelling sensation inside them. Sambo felt his sister pushing against him as she expanded. He felt his own head scraping past the grass-stems as he rose. He seemed to be rising in the air.

“Open your eyes,” ordered Snitch.

And when they obeyed, they found that they were just tall enough to look over the tops of the rough grass. They had doubled their size and height. Snitch, too, had grown bigger with them. They now looked across the surface of what seemed a gigantic hayfield, and in the distance they could just make out dark masses that looked like hills.

“Cows,” said the lizard briefly. “If you’re ready, we’ll climb up one. The Lights are on. Follow me!”

X

Climb up a sleeping cow! What an adventure!

The lizard’s body made a trail through the thick grass, but in spite of this the children had difficulty in keeping up. Topsy was puffing and grunting, while Sambo, holding her hand, dragged her along behind him. Great drops of dew splashed their faces. The grass was stiff. They stumbled and tripped as they went. Beetles and insects watched them pass but did not interfere. There was only the starry sky to light them, for Snitch had dismissed the glowworms for safety’s sake.

As they drew nearer, the body of the cow grew bigger. Like a little hill it loomed before them, blocking half the stars. It looked enormous. It did not move. But they could hear a curious deep sound coming from it.

A few feet from the monster Snitch stopped. “We must find the best way up,” she whispered. “I’ll go and scout, while you wait here.” And, without a sound, she vanished.

Alone in this forest of grass beneath the stars, the crouching monster only a few feet away, Sambo felt less comfortable. Whether his legs trembled or not is hard to say, but at any rate he suddenly sat down. “We’re safer out of sight,” he whispered, pulling Topsy down beside him, “and remember the Rule: ‘When lights are out, keep still!’ ”

Topsy, landing beside him with a bump, snuggled in close. Sambo could feel her heart beating against his ribs. His own heart was going like a drum, but he knew it was a man’s business to protect a female.

“Don’t be frightened,” he whispered. “I’m here, Topsy.”

“I’m not frightened,” she whispered back. “But I don’t like that noise so near us. What is it?” She drew in closer still.

There was this curious roaring sound that came at regular intervals like a gust of wind, making the grass shake and rattle. It was very close. Trees in a storm made that kind of roar.

But Sambo had guessed what it was. “It’s only the cow breathing,” he said below a whisper. “She’s asleep. We mustn’t wake her—”

“In front of her mouth we should be blown away,” began Topsy—when suddenly the danger signal sounded.

“Snitch! Snitch!”

The warning sneeze made them jump, for it was in their very ears. The lizard had come back. She had made no sound, but was just suddenly there.

“There’s a mole on the other side,” came her squeaky voice. “I’ve been all round. The cow’s asleep. But a mole came up to the surface against her ribs. And it tickled her. She may wake. We must wait a moment. When the breathing gets quiet again it’ll mean she’s safely asleep.”

They waited some time till the roaring noise grew less and less, and presently the lizard began to stir again.

“Now,” she whispered. “Are you ready for the climb? Come on!”

“Which end?” asked Topsy breathlessly.

“The far end, of course,” snapped the reply. “Away from the mouth and horns.”

“By the tail?” exclaimed Topsy, bursting with curiosity and excitement.

“Hind leg,” Snitch answered. “It’s less steep than the ribs.” And she led the way through the tangled grass towards the sleeping monster.

It was a creepy, stealthy business, stalking round the great sleeping cow whose body rose like a small hill against the stars. They kept close to her huge bulk where the shadow was deepest. Stretching out their hands, the children could feel her thick stiff hair, the warmth of her body too. If the animal rolled over, they would be squashed flat. But she didn’t roll over. Only the gentle rise and fall of her great sloping sides was visible as they crawled along. Mrs. Snitch knew a thing or two about cows, asleep or awake. No danger signal sounded.

“Here’s the hind hoof!” she warned them, stopping at last in front of a dark object as large as a football. “Now, follow me! Take a running jump!” And she scuttled up the hard smooth hoof, leaving her tail dangling for the children to climb up by. “It’s a bit slippery,” she called from the top. There was a good deal of puffing and blowing, but a moment later Sambo and Topsy stood beside her.

“My!” exclaimed Sambo, who still held his sister by the hand. “It’s a risky business, this being a man!” He puffed himself out.

“Follow me,” replied Snitch, “and don’t boast. It’ll get steeper and steeper as we go.” And she began to scuttle swiftly up the great hind leg. The children followed more slowly, Sambo first, pulling his fat sister after him with his left hand. His right hand clutched the long hair of the great flank.

They mounted slowly; it was a laborious business; the body lay soft and warm beneath their feet. Higher and higher they rose towards the stars, and steeper and steeper grew the slope.

“Tread lightly,” came the lizard’s warning from above, “and if you feel the body move, catch hold of the hair and stop dead. The tail may come flicking round. You never know! She may think flies are tickling her in her dream.”

This was an awful thought. The children had often watched the long tail flicking and lashing about. If it caught them it would sweep them off into space. They moved as softly as they could, and at last they felt the slope become less steep, the hair less thick and matted, and harder ground beneath their feet. They stood on a kind of solid ridge. Snitch had stopped and was waiting for them.

“We’re on the spine,” she explained in a whisper. “We go on the level now for a bit, till we reach the neck.”

“Where do we go after that?” asked Sambo, as soon as he had got his breath, Topsy being too winded to speak at all.

The lizard did not answer for a moment. She was thinking, evidently. “Between the flicking ears and up the horns would be the most interesting,” she said presently. “They’re slippery, and you could slide down them like banisters. You’d like that, wouldn’t you?”

Sambo felt his sister’s hand tighten on his own. He remembered that he was a man. “Are they easy to get up?” he asked in a faint little voice.

“Not very,” answered Snitch, “but I’ll help you. Sliding down is the real difficulty. If you slide the wrong side you may land on the nose and mouth and the cow might snort. And that’s risky rather. A good snort would blow you halfway across the field!”

Sambo wasn’t quite sure he liked cows when he heard that. It was Topsy, finding her breath at last and speaking for the first time, who brought his courage back. “I’ll race you, Sambo,” she said with a thick gurgle, “and I’ll give you choice of horns.” She was actually laughing! The boy conquered his nervousness. “I’ll give you a start,” he answered loudly. “You can have half a horn, and I’ll beat you easily.”

The lizard interrupted them. “Come on, now,” she told them. “We’ve only got two hours, remember, and it’s a longish way down the spine. You’ll feel the body moving probably, but that’s nothing. It rises and falls with the breath, of course, just like your bodies.”

She led the way again at a fair speed, and the children wriggled along behind her. The hair was shorter and less plentiful on the spine. There was not so much to cling to, but it was harder under foot, and they made good speed. On either side the great sides sloped down and away into the darkness of the field far below, but the ridge was broad and nearly level, and Sambo felt very brave until suddenly the upward slope of the neck was reached and the hair became much longer and thicker, entangling their feet in matted, twisted patches.

Here Snitch stopped dead. Beyond her, in the air, rose the broad flat plateau of the head. The twitching ears, fringed with great webs of hair, spread sideways. Farther, again, the long curve of the slippery horns swept up to the stars like immense toboggan runs.

“The ears,” observed Snitch calmly, “aren’t flicking much. She’s too sound asleep. But the horns look extra slippery tonight. That’s the dew, you see.”

She turned her head down to examine the two children. “How do you feel?” she inquired kindly.

Sambo was the first to find his voice. “Quite well, thanks,” he said faintly. “Only—my legs ache a bit.”

“And you, Topsy? All right, eh?” asked Snitch.

“Same as Sambo,” came the answer, brief for want of breath.

“Then choose your horns quickly,” said the lizard. “I think the cow’s going to wake in a minute. She’s rumbling a bit inside. It’s probably a cough coming.”

The noise was like the rumbling of an underground train, but though the great body shook and trembled a bit, the cough did not come, and presently the rumbling and the shaking ceased.

“Now, choose your horns and shin up them,” squeaked Snitch. “There’s no time to lose.”

“Ladies first,” suggested Sambo, relieved that it was the correct thing for a man to say.

“I’ll take the left one,” whispered Topsy, without a sign of nervousness, and almost before her sentence was finished, the lizard had scuttled up to the top and hung her tail down for the children to climb up by. How Topsy managed it was a mystery, but while Sambo pushed and heaved her from below, the fat little body somehow found a footing on the smooth horn and swarmed slowly up it, and a few minutes later her gurgling laughter was heard high up in the air.

“I’m up!” she cried, waving an arm. “On the very top. Hurry up, Sambo! You give me half a horn’s start, remember, for the race!”

It was now Sambo’s turn. But Snitch did not come down to help him. She stayed by Topsy. “You’ll do it easily,” she piped. “You’re a man.”

He had to do it alone. Sambo examined the gleaming slippery horn that curved so steeply upwards. He knew the difficulties. He clenched his fists and faced them. He was not a coward, but all the same his heart was quaking as he began the perilous swarm. It was a terrible job. His muscles ached, the perspiration poured down his face, his breath gave out, but he clasped the horn with arms and legs, and after a tremendous struggle he reached the top. Holding tightly to the tip of the horn, he looked about him, while the others shouted “Well done, Sambo!” at him across the gulf between them. It was wonderful, but giddy. The stars were nearer; the field far, far below; he was perched high up in the air, and the great body of the cow lay beneath him like a cliff running out into the sea. The wind blew past him sharply.

He glanced down nervously into the empty space below. Would he find the courage to slide full speed down that awful slope? It was so narrow! If he swung round too much he would land on the nose and be blown off into the night! He shuddered.

“Are you ready?” Topsy’s call floated across to him. “I’ll count One, Two, Three—and away.” She slid down a little way for her promised start.

“Ready!” he answered, his voice trembling rather.

“One—two—three—” he heard.

But before the “Away” was uttered, something happened—the last thing in the world he expected. It was the warning sneeze.

“Snitch! Snitch!” came the sharp danger signal. “An owl! We’ve been seen!”

XI

Sambo, balanced precariously on his narrow tip, had a sort of convulsion. His first instinct, to protect Topsy, was useless, because he couldn’t reach her. His second instinct, to protect himself, was also useless, because he didn’t know what to do. He remembered the rule and kept still. It was the only possible thing to do, anyhow. Perhaps he wouldn’t be noticed. He clung as tight and still as ivy to the horn—while the swooping owl shot past him through the air. He saw the big dark body, he heard the wings, he felt the wind they made, and the shrill hunting cry shrieked in his very ears. It was an awful moment, though it seemed more like ten minutes.

“It’s missed me!” he heard Topsy call.

“It’s missed me, too!” he shouted back. And the next moment he heard the owl’s wild scream far away among the trees across the road. They were saved.

But someone else besides themselves had heard that owl’s loud shriek. The cow had heard it. It had disturbed her slumbers. The cow began to wake up. She stirred in her sleep. She moved. Slowly—her body rose. She began to get up, rolling to one side as she gathered her legs under her, then to the other side, as she found her feet and prepared for the final effort.

“Hold tight!” cried Snitch. “You’re quite safe if you just hold on!”

Sambo held on for grim life, as the vast body heaved itself up into the air. Mercifully, no tail came slashing round, but the twitching ears made a wind that blew him sideways, and the cow’s final effort, as she found her four feet, swung him first down, then up, then sideways at such a pace that he almost lost his hold altogether. How he still kept his hold was a mystery. The cow at last was fully up. She stood motionless.

“Hold tight!” piped Snitch. “She’s going to shake her head, I think. They usually do when they’re up.”

And this cow did. Sambo shut his eyes. Why he wasn’t shaken off into the stars he never knew. It was an appalling shake. The whole earth seemed to shake. Every bone in his body rattled. His head nearly fell off. He bit his tongue. His teeth clicked. But, at last, the shaking grew less and stopped—and the cow began to walk across the field.

Sambo found his breath and opened his eyes. “Are you all right, Topsy?” he called out.

“R.S.V.P.,” she cried back in a shaky voice.

“S.O.S.” yelled Sambo.

“A.B.C.,” his sister answered.

It seemed all they could think of to say in this amazing moment, as the cow, carrying a child perched on the tip of each horn, went walking beneath the stars across the field.

“I’ll guide her to the gate,” piped the lizard, and then did a wonderful and clever thing. She slid down the horn, scuttled over the head between the twitching ears, slipped along the wet nose and muzzle, and by tickling the cow’s mouth first on one side and then on the other, she persuaded the animal to turn right or left as she wanted.

In this way, after a long time, they reached the gate in the hedge. The road, with the house just across it, lay below them. The cow stopped dead.

“Now, get ready,” called the lizard. “I’ll tickle her between the eyes and she’ll lower her head. Then you must slide down and land on the top bar of the gate. Watch me!”

This happened, too. Snitch flicked her tail about between the cow’s eyes, making the great animal lower her head, till it almost rested on the wooden bar.

“—Slide!” piped the lizard.

Sambo shut his eyes, flung legs and arms round the slippery horn, and—slid. He landed head over heels among the thick, soft hair of the head, ran forward towards the nose and, just avoiding the dangerous puffs of breath from the great mouth, he found himself at last standing on the top bar of the gate. Beside him stood Topsy. “I won,” she chuckled happily, not one bit upset or frightened. “I got down first!”

“Moo! Moo!” boomed the cow, drowning their voices with a roar like thunder, and making them scuttle down into the road as quick as lightning.

They found the lizard waiting for them. “Well,” she squeaked, “we’ve had our adventure, and you both came through it very well. You know now what sort of life we lizards lead. Day and night we live with adventure, risk and danger. So you’ve learned something! You’ve learned to move quickly too! The way you scuttled off the gate was very good. Also you’ve learned to keep still. I hope you’ve enjoyed yourselves, anyhow!” she added finally.

“Thank you very much, Mrs. Snitch,” murmured Sambo with respectful and admiring gratitude.

“X.Y.Z.,” whispered Topsy, using her politest voice, for she, too, was filled with admiration.

Snitch uttered a peculiar squeak, and the glowworms came flocking round them with their pleasant light. The cow, the children saw, had moved away.

“The three hours are up,” mentioned Snitch, “You must get small again and climb up the wall into your beds:

Make me though thmall
That I can crawl
Thtraight up the wall
And never fall!”

There was a dwindling sensation; the ground came nearer; both children became as small as they had been when they started on the adventure.

Accompanied by the Lights, they climbed easily up the wall and through the open window. The glowworms faded out. Sambo tumbled down onto the carpet. Somehow or other, he lost sight of Topsy, but when he picked himself up he saw that she was already in bed. He could see the lump of her round body beneath the clothes. He climbed into his own bed.

“Good night!” he heard Snitch call from the windowsill outside.

“Good night, Mrs. Snitch,” he called back sleepily as he turned over beneath the bedclothes, buried his nose in the pillow, and went off into another dreamland.

It was late when he opened his eyes again. Topsy’s bed, he saw, was already empty; the sun was pouring into the room. He had overslept.

Nannie poked her head in at the door: “I’ve called you four times,” she said crossly. “If I have to call again you’ll have no honey for your breakfast. The bath water’s nearly cold!”

He crawled out of bed, wondering why he was his natural size again. Snitch hadn’t made him bigger; the last thing he remembered was the difficulty of climbing onto the mattress. He rubbed his eyes as he trotted into the bathroom. His head still felt sleepy.

“Have you seen a lizard about anywhere, Nannie?” he asked.

“Lizard!” exclaimed Nannie, astonished at the question. “I should hope not, indeed! What’s the boy talking about! You’ve been dreaming.” And she popped him bodily into the bath and began to sponge him vigorously.

The cool water chased the sleep from his head, and he remembered that he must not say anything to Nannie about the adventure. He would wait for Topsy. Topsy would be able to explain what had happened. When at last he was dressed and ready, he went in to breakfast and saw his sister with a large plate of bread and honey, already eating hard. He caught her eye. She looked at him innocently, as though honey was the only thing she knew about in the whole world. “You’re late, Sambo,” she said cheekily.

He winked hard at her. “R.S.V.P.,” he whispered, splashing in his plate of porridge. Then, as Topsy made no answering wink, he added: “S.O.S.” But Topsy said nothing to this either and looked as though she didn’t understand what he was talking about. Her face was as blank as a cushion. “P.T.O. and X.Y.Z.,” Sambo tried again, winking with both eyes this time, then adding under his breath: “Did Snitch make you big again? What happened after she left us—?”

Topsy stared at him with her mouth wide open.

“Don’t eat with your mouth open, Topsy,” Nannie pounced on her at once. “And you get on with your porridge, Sambo. I can’t think why you’re so naughty this morning.”

Recognizing from her voice that she was serious, the children glanced sideways at her, and went on with their breakfast; but as soon as Nannie was out of the room again, Topsy began full blast: “Sambo, why were you so sleepy this morning? And what did you mean by all those letters you said to me? And who’s Snitch, or whatever you called it? And how can I be made big again? You are naughty, you know. I believe Nannie’ll smack you or something if you go on.”

She stopped for breath and Sambo stared at her. A queer feeling came over him. Was his sister joking, or had she really forgotten?

“Topsy,” he asked solemnly, “don’t you remember a lizard and a cow and an owl and a tremendous cat and a lot of glowworms flying about to light us—?”

“Glowworms don’t fly,” exclaimed Nannie, bursting into the room, “they crawl on the ground, for one thing. And, for another, you’d better finish your breakfast instead of talking nonsense. I spoke to you once.”

It was quite clear that Topsy remembered nothing of the adventure, nothing at all. Sambo could tell from her face now. It was full of questions, but not of memory. He felt dreadfully puzzled, but he gobbled up his bread and honey before Nannie could tell him he wasn’t to have any. Topsy, he saw, was now busy with a picture book. She had forgotten all about the things she asked. She changed from one interest to another very quickly always.

“I say, Nannie,” the boy asked a few minutes later when he was alone with her, “is that really true about glowworms?”

“That they can’t fly?” replied Nannie. “Of course it is. I read all about them in a book. They’re beetles. The female gives the light and it crawls on the ground. Now, run and get your boots on.” She said a lot of other things about going for a walk, what he was to wear, and where they were going, but Sambo heard none of it. He was more puzzled than ever. Had the whole Adventure been a dream then, he wondered? It had been grand and marvellous anyhow, and the world was a finer place because of it, and far more exciting than before. Whether Topsy remembered or not made no difference really. He would ask the lizard.

The lizard, however, remained in hiding. She was resting after her wild night, Sambo decided. He also decided that he would not ask his sister any more direct questions. He would just test her instead with a few remarks to see how she would answer. So, when they started for their walk, and Mrs. Tompkyns accompanied them down the drive with her tail in the air like a ramrod, he said: “If you were as small as a mouse, Topsy, Mrs. Tompkyns would look as big as an elephant.” To which Topsy replied: “But I’m not”—with nothing more. And when they passed the field where the cows were lying down, he said: “If you wanted to climb up that cow and ride on her back, which leg would you get up by?” To which Topsy replied: “But I don’t,”—with nothing more. Once again he tested her: “If you had to climb out of a window and down the wall, would you go head first or feet first, Topsy?” To which the answer came: “Neither. I’d stay inside,”—with nothing more.

“Then I don’t believe you really came at all!” Sambo blurted out—to which his sister made no reply of any kind, because clearly she had no idea what he was talking about. Then he added under his breath, saying it to himself: “It doesn’t matter a bit. I went anyhow! And that’s certain!”

“I went, too,” squeaked a tiny voice close to his ear.

It was Snitch’s voice. It startled him. “I’ve been on your coat collar ever since you left the house,” the voice went on. It ran up and tickled his neck to prove it, then ran back again into hiding. “Drop behind,” added the lizard, “so that we can talk without being heard.”

Sambo instantly stooped down to tie his bootlace, while Nannie and Topsy walked on ahead.

“Dear Snitch,” he began at once, “I want to ask you something very important, please.”

“Unimportant things, anyhow, aren’t worth asking,” mentioned the lizard. “Quick, now, for I want my dinner.”

“Did Topsy come with us last night?” asked the boy.

Snitch laughed. “If she did,” came the answer, “she’d never stop talking about it. She’d tell everybody in the house. Females always divulge, as I’ve already warned you.”

“Oh!” cried Sambo, “then you’ve made her forget it on purpose!”

Snitch made no comment.

“But I went, didn’t I?” he went on excitedly. “I didn’t just dream it all, I mean?”

For a moment there was no reply. He felt Snitch run up over his neck and wriggle into the hollow of his ear. The tiny feet and forked tongue tickled him.

“You enjoyed yourself, didn’t you?” the little creature whispered.

“Rather!” shouted the boy—so loud that Nannie turned and came towards him.

“Then just remember it and be glad,” Snitch told him. “That’s quite enough. Never bother happiness with questions. Now, goodbye, I’m off to catch my dinner.”

And a second later, when Nannie came up, the lizard had vanished into thin air.

XII

One result of Sambo’s strange friendship with his little saurian was that he showed signs of changing. He began to notice things for himself. Topsy was still too young to alter. Balls may look rounder some days than others, but they’re really always the same until someone pricks them, when they become just pieces of flattened india-rubber. No one pricked Topsy, however, so she remained the tight round little ball she always had been. With Sambo it was different.

His parents sat in the garden one day and talked about him. They little guessed that all they said was overheard.

“The boy’s developing fast,” remarked Father in a pleased voice, as though the improvement were due to himself. “He’s beginning to notice things out of doors—”

“What sort of things?” interrupted Mother, a little alarmed.

“Oh, insects and things—bees, spiders, flies and all that. He’s always asking me questions I can’t answer, especially about lizards. He knows a lot about lizards already. I can’t think where he picks it up.”

“Probably he just makes it up,” suggested Mother. But Father disagreed. “No,” he said emphatically, “because it’s accurate. Besides, he never wants to kill a thing now the moment he sees it. He’d rather watch it.”

“Yes,” agreed Mother, “that is queer. So unlike a boy. I hope Nannie isn’t filling his head with nonsense!”

“No fear,” laughed Father. “Why, Nannie doesn’t know the difference between a tortoise and a turtle. She certainly knows nothing about lizards.”

“She understands children,” Mother defended her.

“Children, my dear, are not insects or reptiles—at least, our children aren’t.” And then he added: “I’m glad to see this in the boy. It may mean he’s going to be a naturalist. And that’s a healthy out-of-door life, I always think.”

This conversation took place on the seat in the rose-garden, and Snitch, who was always where you least expected her, was lying comfortably along the leg of Father’s chair. She knew quite well that the improvement in Sambo was due largely to herself, so she felt flattered and thought it might be nice to show herself. Dropping down, she shot across the ground in front of the speakers, as much as to say, “Here I am! Now look at me!” And very nice indeed she certainly looked, so neatly dressed, her new tail nearly grown, her bright eyes shining.

But instead of the cry of admiration she expected, there came a shrill squeal of fear.

“Oh! Oh!” screamed Mother. “There’s a snake! Or a mouse! Or something horrid! It’ll run up my skirts and bite me!” And, quick as a flash, she climbed upon the garden seat, jiggling her feet about as if she were trying to dance.

“It’s only a lizard,” Father calmed her. “It won’t hurt you. Nice, friendly little things, lizards. Look, it’s got a forked tongue, and it’s moving its eyelids,” he went on. “Snakes haven’t got movable eyelids, you know, like lizards.” But Mother, having climbed still higher, had all she could do to balance and wasn’t listening. “And, by Jove, it’s growing a new tip to its tail. It’s a little beauty,” he cried. “I’ll pick it up and show it to you.”

“Will you, indeed!” squeaked Snitch, though the big man couldn’t hear the voice as Sambo could have heard it had he been there.

Father stepped forward very cautiously; he stooped; he slowly advanced his hand; then suddenly darted out a finger and thumb and grabbed—nothing!

“Why, I do declare—it’s gone!” he cried in amazement. “And yet I never saw it move! It’s disappeared completely.” And he stood up straight again and helped Mother down from her dangerous perch. “Gone into its hole, I suppose. I never knew anything so fast in my life!”

Snitch had certainly disappeared, but as a matter of fact she had hardly moved at all. She had merely shifted her body at incredible speed an inch or two, so that she now lay against a dry twig. She lay absolutely still, looking like a bit of wood herself. The big man’s eye could not distinguish her from the ground. He no longer saw her.

“I do believe it’s the very lizard Sambo’s been watching,” Father remarked. “The boy told me it moved like lightning. Come along, dear,” he added, taking Mother’s arm and walking away. “You’ve nothing to fear. It’s gone.”

“I only hope he doesn’t touch it,” replied Mother nervously, giving a little shiver. “I’m sure it bites. And I hope it doesn’t mean we’re going to have thousands of them about. They have enormous families, I believe, like rabbits. …” and their voices died away as they went into the house, so that Father’s comment was not heard.

Snitch, smiling to herself, also went into the house just behind them. She flashed up the banisters and along the corridor into the schoolroom, where Sambo sat alone poring over a book about Insects and Animals that Live in your Garden—a present from his father. She ran onto the open page, cocked an eye, and told him what had happened. “I could play with your Father,” she observed, when the tale was ended, “because he’s friendly and likes me. But your Mother’s afraid of me and thinks I bite.” She flicked her tail and laughed. “I could never do anything with her. Besides,” she added in a hurt tone, “I eat the flies that tickle her face, so she ought to feel grateful. And we don’t have enormous families either. Twelve eggs is the most I’ve ever had, and usually it’s only six or seven.”

Sambo, however, was not listening very attentively. He was more interested in the way Snitch had made herself invisible to his father. “I wish you’d teach me how to do that,” he begged, adding quickly “Thank you very much indeed.” It was a good plan to give thanks beforehand, he had discovered.

Snitch cocked both eyes this time. There was a pause. The lizard was thinking it over. “It’s not easy,” she announced at last. “You humans are so big and lumpy. I’m only seven inches long. You’re over sixty. Besides, we lizards have been practising it for millions of years. Have to, you see. Otherwise we should be seen and eaten.”

“I see,” remarked Sambo sympathetically.

“Do you?” piped the little voice with a chuckle. But its owner had vanished. The slim body which a moment before had sprawled over the page of the open book was no longer there. “You hear me, but you can’t see me,” the voice continued. “Now, if you were a hawk or a hedgehog or a snake, I’d be safe here where I am; but as you’re only a little boy, and rather a slow one too, I’ll show you my hiding-place. Look closely now!” And Sambo saw a pointed muzzle pushed suddenly into view over the edge of the white page. Two bright eyes winked at him. Snitch lay along the binding of the book, her colour merging with the colour of the binding so that she was practically invisible. Unless she moved, it was impossible to see her. Her outline was lost against the dark background.

“Another thing you can’t do as we do it,” she went on to explain, darting back upon the white page again, “is—keep absolutely still. Boys—grownups too for that matter—make unnecessary movements all the time. No human can keep quite still for more than a few seconds: you flick your eyelids, bite your lips, twitch your fingers, wiggle your toes, wrinkle your nose, twist your neck, and breathe so heavily that your ribs heave up and down like a storm at sea. Your eyes, too, are never still. All those silly movements betray you.”

“Yes,” replied the boy, “that’s true, I expect. But the people looking for me wouldn’t notice most of those movements, would they? A hawk or a snake might, but a person—”

“Sambo!” cried the lizard, with a shrill squeak of pleasure, “you’re worth teaching. People only see big movements. I’m delighted with you! You might almost be one of us. So I’ll show you how to do it. Quick, now! Your father’s coming. Get ready!”

Sambo just stared. “How do you know?” he asked in amazement.

“I hear his step on the stairs,” explained Snitch. “He’s coming up from the hall and I know his tread. Besides, the boards of the floor are shaking. I can feel the table trembling. You forget he’s seventy-two inches long and weighs nearly 200 pounds.”

“But I hear nothing,” objected Sambo. “I can’t feel anything shaking.’ Do what I tell you,” squeaked the lizard sharply, “if you want to learn. Quick, or you’ll be too late, and he’ll catch you.” And hardly had she spoken when Father’s voice, calling “Sambo! Sambo!” was heard booming in the passage. The thump of his feet was heard too, striding down towards the room.

“Take that brown and red tablecloth,” ordered Snitch, “and wrap it round your shoulders. That’s right,” she added, as the boy obeyed. “Now sit down on the floor against the bookshelves, bend your head forwards as if you were looking at the books. Hide your white hands and tuck your feet under you. Quick! Now, don’t move. Don’t stir a muscle. The tablecloth and the browny-green covers of the books melt into the colours of the cloth. You are difficult to see. There’s no outline visible. Keep quite still and you’re safe!”

“Sambo! Sambo, boy! Where are you?” called his Father’s voice just outside the door. The next minute he was in the room. “Sambo!” he shouted, “are you here? Topsy told me you were reading in the schoolroom. I don’t see you anywhere!” And he began to search with his eyes. Then he moved forward and picked up the book. Next he looked under the table, behind the folded curtains, at the back of the sofa, and even in the cupboard.

“Bother the boy!” he exclaimed to himself. “Why, he’s disappeared just as that little lizard did! My wig! What a streak of lightning he is!” And he passed so close to the bookshelves that his leg brushed Sambo’s shoulder. But the big man never saw him, though more than once he must have looked straight at him. The colours were too perfectly matched. No outline of his crouching body was visible to an unpractised human eye. He marched heavily over to the open window and looked out into the garden. “Sambo!” he bawled at the top of his voice, “are you out there?”

“Now show yourself,” whispered the lizard, perched on a brown bookbinding beneath his nose. “You kept still grandly—for a first time. Now, get up and show yourself.”

Sambo obeyed. “Here I am, Father,” he announced himself, standing just behind his parent’s back and pulling his coat-sleeve.

The big man turned. “Bless the boy, I never heard you come in!” he exclaimed, picking him up in his arms. “Wherever were you all the time?”

“Here,” answered Sambo. “Why, you touched me once. I was down there,” he explained, pointing to the floor beside the bookshelves. “I had the tablecloth over me, you see.”

His father stared, tremendously surprised. “Show me how you did it,” he exclaimed. And Sambo repeated his performance. He crouched down, covered with the cloth, so that it was very difficult indeed to see him. Knowing exactly where to look this time, however, his father of course could distinguish the outline of his body.

“Well, I never!” he cried. “That’s what they call camouflage! And who taught you that, I should like to know!”

“Promise you won’t tell anyone?” the boy made his condition.

“Yes, I promise,” agreed the man, picking him up bodily.

“A lizard,” Sambo whispered into his ear.

XIII

Sambo had now learned a lesson the lizard perhaps had intended him to learn. He realised that Topsy didn’t need Adventures as he needed them. That was why she had forgotten all about the Night Out, even if she had ever taken part in it at all. Their natures were different. He also realised, after the talk with his father, that if he talked too much, he would have to grow up into a Naturalist, whereas what he meant to grow up into was an engineer—a man who drove tremendous engines, built bridges, and dammed up great torrents.

Henceforth, therefore, he kept his Adventures to himself. He enjoyed them in his own way.

For Sambo was a merry lad,
His heart was light as air,
About the things he didn’t know
He really didn’t care!

“That’s very pretty, but rather silly, I think,” squeaked the familiar voice. “It isn’t a good tune, either.”

Sambo turned his head and saw his tiny friend sprawling on a stone in front of him. He was alone in the garden. “You’re always listening,” he objected. “You turn up everywhere. I thought I was alone. Topsy’s gone out with Nannie. I’m supposed to have a headache. Too much cake or something, they said.”

“Because I like you,” replied Snitch. “That’s why I’m here now.” And she wriggled closer. “I’ve got something to propose to you.” Her bright eyes sparkled.

“What is it?” asked the boy, all eagerness at once.

“Oh, just the garden,” said Snitch vaguely, “and how we lizards read it.”

“Oh, the garden,” repeated Sambo, disappointed a little. “How do you mean—‘read it’?”

“You read books,” replied the lizard. “But books only give what other people have seen. We,” she added proudly, “don’t want secondhand stuff. We read it first.”

“Oh!” remarked the boy, feeling rather stupid. He didn’t understand.

“Your letters and printing,” explained Snitch, “are only signs on paper. You know what they mean because you’ve learned them with a lot of trouble. Well, the whole world is covered with signs that you can read direct, if you know how. I’ll teach you a little, if you like.”

“Thanks awfully,” replied the boy in his politest voice, and he turned his head and stared all over the garden, hoping to see signs he had never noticed before. But he saw nothing new.

“You must learn the alphabet first,” mentioned the lizard, watching him. “How do you think we should know all we do if we couldn’t read the writing all over the fields and sky and trees? D’you think we just guess it?” Her voice turned very scornful. “Bah!” she added, “your book-writing is nothing compared to ours!” And she drew her tail up.

Sambo felt ashamed. “I’m sorry,” he murmured. “I see now what you mean. And you certainly do know an awful lot, I must say.”

“Thank you,” Snitch said, in a forgiving voice. “Now, we’ll begin with the Night Garden.”

“The Night Garden!” exclaimed Sambo. “Do you mean the Garden at Night?”

“It’s easier to read,” explained the lizard. “There’s more going on. You’re all out of the way, for one thing!”

“Oh!” gasped Sambo, beginning to understand.

“You,” went on the lizard rather contemptuously, “think everything goes to sleep when you do and because you do. You think only owls and bats are awake at night.” She twitched her head and gave a little laugh. “Now, be ready tonight when Topsy’s asleep. I’ll come for you.”

“I’ll be ready,” the boy agreed eagerly. “Shall I be made small again?” he asked.

“Bah!” snapped Snitch contemptuously. “We never repeat things. We think of something new. Now, remember, don’t ask questions afterwards, don’t talk to people who can’t understand, and—be ready when I come.” And she disappeared so fast that Sambo never saw her go.

That night Topsy fell asleep, luckily, the moment her head touched the pillow, and Sambo lay staring at the night-light and waiting for the sign. The door, as usual, stood ajar, and Nannie poked her head in once or twice. But no signal came. The minutes passed. The house grew very still. The boy’s eyes grew rather heavy. Then suddenly the familiar little voice sounded behind him: “Dress,” it said. And he was out of bed and dressed faster than ever in his life before. As he buttoned his coat the light was put out. “Take thith,” he heard, “and follow me,” and he felt something put into his fingers in the dark. “I’ve got the other end in my mouth. Itth a pieth of thtring.” Already he felt it tighten. A moment later he was out in the passage, down the deserted stairs, through the empty hall, along the corridor to the pantry—and the side-door clicked behind him. Snitch, by means of the piece of string had led him straight into the garden. He felt the cool night air. He saw the stars. Still feeling the pull of the string, he followed his invisible guide down the long gravel drive, along the path that crossed the Farm Meadow, and so to the edge of the belt of trees that lay between this meadow and the big hayfield. Here, half a mile from the house, they stopped. The lizard spoke for the first time since leaving the room.

“You can’t see me,” she said, “so you must just listen instead. You can’t see anything, for that matter, because you haven’t got our night-eyes. But you can hear and feel. Just hear and feel as keenly as ever you can. Now, which way is the wind? Tell me that first.”

Sambo, eager to obey, listened and felt as hard as ever he could. But there was no wind. Not a tree rustled, the grass lay silent, no air stirred. He wetted his finger and held it up, but with no result. Not a breath!

“There isn’t any,” he said, proud to feel he was right.

“Wrong,” squeaked the lizard. “There’s always some, even on the stillest night. A draught, a current, a movement in the air. Now,” she added, like a teacher giving a lesson to a stupid child, “try again.”

This time, remembering his instructions, Sambo just listened, and after a few minutes, though he had thought it was a dead silence, he began to hear all manner of queer, gentle, little noises creeping upon him from the left. He hadn’t noticed these before. From his right side he heard nothing.

“The wind’s blowing from my left to my right,” he announced, though it was partly a guess, perhaps.

“Right!” exclaimed Snitch, in a pleased voice. “And what do you hear?” she asked him next. “Listen hard a moment, and then tell me.”

Sambo listened so hard that he nearly lost his balance, and leaned against a larch tree to steady himself. The blood made a rumbling noise in his head at first, but presently he began to distinguish other sounds behind this rumble: creakings, rustlings, sharp tiny clicks as though a leaf or small twig snapped, odd little hissing noises too, while other, fainter sounds—and they were deeper, these—seemed to come from underground. There were odd tappings too. And the harder he listened, the louder grew the volume of noises, though this may have been because he already was hearing better.

“They all come from my left,” he whispered, and his whisper seemed like a roar compared to the softness of these other sounds. “Nothing from the right.”

“That proves the wind,” replied Snitch. “Describe what you hear.” And the boy did so, as well as he could.

“Not bad,” remarked the lizard judicially, “not so bad for a boy who has never learned how to listen, and whose ears are full of wax. Now, I’ll tell you what it all is, but first I’ll get on your shoulder.” She ran up and perched below his ear. “I’m safer here. Something might make a dart at me on the ground—from the right side, where we can’t hear. I can whisper too.” She gave him then a rapid analysis of all the jumble of sounds, though he couldn’t distinguish all the differences that she evidently could. He felt rather frightened to know there were so many living creatures all about him, but she explained to him that most of them were friendly, more afraid of him than he was of them, and that only one or two were hostile—“to me, not to you,” she added. “They’d gobble me up if they could. They know I’m here, right enough. That’s why I’m on your shoulder.”

“The whole wood’s alive,” she told him, “for everything moves at night. There’s just as much noise coming from our right, too, only we can’t hear it because the wind’s the other way. The things on our right can hear and smell us, but all those we hear to our left, though they know someone’s about, don’t know exactly what or where.”

“Smell?” asked Sambo, sniffing hard. “Why, I can’t smell anything at all.”

“I’ll tell you about smell later,” replied Snitch. “For the moment let’s deal with hearing. That rustling you hear is made up of a good many things, all moving stealthily. Several field-mice are flitting in and out of the grass, hunting for food; beetles, and all manner of insects, are scratching; and that soft, silken noise like water is something nasty sliding along on a very smooth tummy. It never stops, you notice. It’s ahem! we won’t refer to it again, if you don’t mind—a grass-snake. I have a poor opinion of such things—”

“So have I,” agreed Sambo, “though they’re not poisonous.”

“Things that swallow me can be poisonous or not,” replied Snitch. “I disapprove of them. But, before we leave the hostile things, I’ll mention one other. That clicking, jerky noise—d’you hear it? It goes by fits and starts. Well, that’s—ahem!—a hedgehog. If it saw you, it would just roll up in a ball and pretend to be dead; but if it saw me, it would open its ugly mouth, run at me much faster than you have ever seen a hedgehog run, and—I’ll omit the rest, I think, if you don’t mind.”

Something fell with a little sharp tap beside them onto the ground.

“And that,” Snitch continued more calmly, “is something harmless. A squirrel perched high on a branch above our heads is eating its nuts. It dropped that bit just to let us know it’s seen us. Friendly little things, squirrels, but rather conceited about their sparkling eyes and bushy tails.” Snitch gave a subdued yet shrill squeak, and the squirrel answered with a similar noise. More things dropped.

The lizard gave a sudden start. “That’s a warning,” she whispered. “Something’s moving towards us from the side we can’t hear—the right. Let’s get into the field a bit. It’s safer.” And the boy obeyed as quick as lightning, carrying his friend with him on his shoulder.

“What was the deeper noise we heard?” he asked, as soon as they were safely in the open field. “Underground, it sounded.”

“It was underground,” Snitch told him, “but you’d never guess. In the deep ditch, a dozen yards from where we stood, is a hole that goes down into the soft earth—a badger’s hole. What you heard was old Father Badger moving about among his family. He’s got two young ones. And he was shuffling about and grunting because he heard some rats sniffing at the mouth of his hole as they scampered past towards the farm-buildings in the field beyond. He’s a great friend of mine, but dreadfully shy, and he hates human beings because—well, because they badger him to death whenever they can.”

A dozen questions came into Sambo’s head, but before he could ask one of them, Snitch was talking again. “Now, lean down and put your ear to the ground, and you’ll hear something else, if you keep still enough.” The boy knelt down and put his ear to the earth, while Snitch wriggled round onto his back as he did so. “Listen hard and keep still as a mouse. You must hardly breathe.”

After listening intently for several minutes, Sambo caught a queer faint murmur in the earth, but below the surface. It was a soft, grating sound, rather as if he rubbed sand between finger and thumb close to his ear.

“Earth worms,” Snitch told him. “Hundreds of them. They pass the soft earth through the whole length of their bodies. You see the casts on the lawn in the morning usually. A bird can hear that noise. Then it taps on the lawn with its feet to make the worm come up—and be gobbled for its breakfast. The moles aren’t moving yet; they start about dawn.”

Sambo held his ear to the ground and listened for a long time. It all fascinated him.

“That’s enough now for one night,” exclaimed Snitch presently. “Up you get and back to bed. I want to get some sleep too. You’ve read a few lines of the Night Garden anyhow—just the beginning of a chapter. Next time we’ll try smell, after that trees and flowers and bushes, after that perhaps the sky—oh, and dozens of other chapters as well.”

“It’s most awfully kind of you, Snitch,” the boy thanked her, as he got on his feet again. “I’ve enjoyed it enormously. Next time I’d like to—”

But before he could finish the sentence there came a queer rushing past his ears, he seemed to rise, then drop through space, he turned over and over. … He opened his eyes a little and found he was in bed. The night-light had burned very low, and in the other bed across the room Topsy was snoring and blowing like a small grampus that had somehow got into a kettle on the kitchen stove. He closed his eyes again and remembered no more.

XIV

Sambo was just beginning to learn the Garden-Writing of sound, smell and sign, when something happened to interrupt the fascinating lessons. September had passed and October, with its shortening days, had come. In the early morning mist lay along the fields, and the leaves, turning red and gold, were already fluttering to the ground like gorgeous, tired butterflies. Along one of these golden leaves, dropped from the horse-chestnut tree, lay Snitch one afternoon.

This time she had not chosen a background to hide against. The gold showed the outline of her slender little body very vividly.

“Pick me up, please,” squeaked the lizard. “I don’t feel like darting or scuttling today.” The voice had a rather tired sound.

Sambo obeyed. He picked up the big leaf and laid it on the palm of his hand. Snitch did not move. She lay like a dead twig, motionless.

The boy wondered what was the matter. Her voice, he noticed, was not quite as clear and sharp as usual, her eyes seemed less bright. They had less flash in them. She seemed altogether listless and uninterested in life. Never before had she asked to be picked up, for as a rule she darted up his arm or back before he could think.

He feared his little friend must be out of sorts, or even ill; and this made him feel uncomfortable, because he knew nothing about illness and could not think of anything, to say for some time. He gazed down at the motionless little creature in silence. She made no sound.

“Have you got a headache, or something?” he asked gently, after a long pause.

“Never have headaches,” replied the lizard, still without moving, “because I never overeat.” After a moment she added: “That’s my trouble.”

Sambo was puzzled; he did not understand this mood. “What trouble?” he asked, bending his face down a little closer so as to watch her better.

“Eating,” replied Snitch briefly. “My food’s getting scarce.”

“Oh, if you’re hungry,” cried Sambo, “I’ll get you something from the kitchen in a jiffy!” and he almost turned to go into the house.

The lizard stopped him.

“My food, not yours,” she explained, then fell into silence again.

“I’m awfully sorry,” Sambo put in, and really meant it. “It’s horrid being hungry.” He longed to help, but didn’t know quite what to suggest. He was far too clumsy to catch her food in the way she managed it.

“Insects are getting scarce now,” the small voice went on presently. “And there’s less heat in the sun. You might move out of the shade, please, and put me near a wall, where it’s warmer. I feel cold.”

Sambo quickly ran down the Drive and stood against the old stone wall. The sunlight was reflected here. Flies and bees were buzzing in the ivy.

“That’s better,” said the lizard, and showed signs of reviving a little. Her voice was already brisker. She cocked her head round and looked up into the sky a moment. “The swallows are going too,” she observed. “They can’t get enough insects to eat either. They’ll all be gone to Africa in a week, where there’s lots of food. When they go, I go.”

Sambo felt his heart sink. “You’re not going to leave me!” he cried. “I should miss you terribly. I love you so. We’ve had such fun—”

“Thank you,” Snitch interrupted, and ran slowly off the leaf onto his palm, which she tickled softly with her tiny forefeet by way of showing her affection. “Your hand is nice and warm,” she added, snuggling in against the curve of his thumb. “I feel tired, cold, hungry and sleepy.” Her tail curled round a little as if she were going to sleep. “So, when the swallows go, I go too,” she said again, half closing her eyes.

“But you’ll feel ever so much better after something to eat and a good sleep,” said the boy eagerly. “I wish you wouldn’t talk about going. I hate it.”

“When the swallows go, I go too,” repeated the lizard gently. “I must.”

“Where to?” asked Sambo, his mind already made up to take the journey with her, wherever it might be. “You can’t go to Africa!”

“I don’t,” came the reply in a lower voice. “I go—to sleep.”

“Oh, that’s all right!” cried Sambo more cheerfully. “Then I shall see you again when you wake up.”

The lizard was silent for a moment. “When I go to sleep,” she resumed, presently, “it’s rather a long sleep.”

“Like me,” agreed the boy. “I sleep all night through. I hate getting out of bed in the morning. How long are you going to sleep for this time?”

Again Snitch kept silent for several minutes. “This time,” she said in a still lower voice, “I’m going to sleep for about six months, I’m afraid.”

Sambo caught his breath. “Six months!” he exclaimed. He thought at first his friend was teasing him. “Why, you’d die if you did that.” And he laughed a little. But his laughter stopped as he heard the lizard’s next words: “Oh, no,” she explained, “I shan’t die. Every autumn, when the insects get scarce, and the sun grows cold, we lizards just crawl into a shelter and go to sleep. We sleep till our food comes back and the days are warm again. We should never live through the cold winter if we didn’t do this.”

Sambo at first could hardly believe his ears. Then he remembered having heard that snakes and tortoises and bears and a few other creatures hibernated, and so realised that the lizard was not teasing him, but was telling him the truth. And as this dawned upon him, he felt very sad.

“Oh, Snitch, dear,” he said, bending his face towards her, “I shall miss you terribly. I shall come and put flowers on your grave—”

“My bed, you mean,” Snitch corrected him sharply. “I shall only be asleep. It’s rather a long sleep, I know, but it suits us lizards.”

“Will there be a lot of you all asleep together?” asked Sambo.

“About five or six,” was the reply.

“And will you show me where it is, please?”

The lizard’s voice was growing fainter and fainter. “It’s that heap of stones and leaves and turf on the edge of the wood,” she whispered. “The one near the gate, you know.”

“Yes, I know.”

“You might carry me over there now, perhaps,” the tired little voice went on. “I’m getting drowsier and drowsier every minute. I’ve had nothing much to eat lately, you see, and the sun really has so little heat left.” With a sinking heart Sambo walked across the lawn, carrying the tired lizard in his hand. He climbed the iron railing and reached the heap of stones. It was an untidy looking sort of place that nobody was likely to disturb. He stopped and stared down at the piled up stones and bits of turf. “Are the others already in there?” he asked, and Snitch told him in a murmur that they had gone in the day before and were already sound asleep, lying curled against one another.

“We shan’t wake till April,” she added. “The first thing I do when I’m out will be to come and find you. I promise.”

“That’s a real promise,” the boy repeated, feeling a lump rise in his throat. Snitch gave his skin a tiny nip by way of reply. She was evidently very sleepy and tired now.

“You might put me down on the stones,” she whispered, so faintly he could hardly catch the sound. And Sambo did so. She moved slowly, as though it cost her great effort, from his palm onto a piece of turf among the leaves. “I’m glad about the flowers,” he just heard, “I shan’t feel nigglelected now.” She had not enough energy left even to pronounce her words properly, but the boy knew what she meant.

“Every week I’ll come,” he promised. “On Mondays.”

“Goodbye, then, dear Sambo, and goodnight,” murmured the fading voice. And when he looked closer to see if she had moved, he saw the place was empty. Snitch had disappeared for her long winter sleep.

“April …” he just caught the tiny sound of her whisper rise up through the stones and leaves.

“Next April,” he repeated in a shaky little voice. “And I’ll come every Monday. I promise …”

He listened, but there was no reply. He had the tip of her broken tail in his little box in the house, but he would not see his friend, Snitch, again till the swallows and the insects came back in April with the flowers and the warmer sun.

For some minutes he stood beside the pile of stones, feeling sad and lonely, and repeating to himself the little song he had made up many weeks before, when he first met her:

“Dear little Snitch,
I’m all alone;
I wonder which
Way you have gone!”

But after a bit he stopped doing this, because he knew quite well where his friend was, and that she was now happy and comfortably asleep. She had taught him ever so many things worth knowing, and he would never forget her. Every Monday he would go to the pile of stones and keep his promise. Then, in the spring, he would see her crawl out again, and they would have a lot of new adventures together. So Sambo ran off to play with Topsy quite happily, knowing that in the little lizard he had a true friend he would meet again, because a true friend is never lost.

(While Snitch slept through the winter, the adventures, of course, came to an end. But one day she may come back to Sambo and to us again. Who knows?)

Sleep and How to Do Without It

The other day, in San Francisco, Thomas A. Edison said that the improvement in artificial light was waking up the people in the large cities, but that in the country districts, where only lamps and candles were used, people were still dull and stupid and slept the clock round. He added that where light was, thought was and that he expected that someday man would be able to do altogether without sleep.

He spoke (apparently) in ignorance of the work which has already been accomplished. The Rev. J. P. Bullock, fellow of Trinity, a great authority in Buddhistic art, and a member of the Royal Scientific Society, has published numerous studies on this question: “Sleep, Its Cause and Cure,” 1907, Williams Brothers, Liverpool; “Why Should We Waste a Third of Life?” 1909, William Dryden & Co., London; “Sleep, Twin-Brother of Death,” 1910, Bombay Press, Bombay; “Wake and Work,” 1913, Higher Thought Book Co., Birmingham. It is perhaps worthwhile here to give a short and popular résumé of Dr. Bullock’s theories.

From the scientific point of view, sleep is principally a question of elimination; one might almost dare to say that rest is not necessary to the human body in health; it is the accumulation of poison within it that puts it out of order. The heart needs no rest, because of several elaborate systems which ensure that all poisons are thrown out of the blood immediately. If you deliberately poison the blood, sleep or coma result; or in certain cases, convulsions. All of these may be regarded as more or less desperate efforts to eliminate. Sleep is a symptom of intoxication. It is caused by the poisons accumulated in the brain. We all know that under mental stimulation we can cause the brain to work at high pressure for a long time; the excretion works at a greatly increased rate, and sleep may be postponed indefinitely. (The present writer composed a four-act play continuously as long as 54 hours without rest or food, under the stimulus of a strong dramatic inspiration.) However, a time always arrives sooner or later when all stimulus fails, one must cease to accumulate poison, and allow a period for the body to get rid of it in due course.

The next point to consider is this; sleep is not a uniform phenomenon; it is of many qualities. Everyone knows, for example, that now and again one “dozes off” for a few minutes, intolerably sleepy, and wakes entirely refreshed, as if one had spent a long and dreamless night. On the other hand one knows that sometimes, after a good night’s rest under apparently perfect conditions, one wakes exhausted. There is every type of intermediate sleep between these extremes.

It therefore occurred to Dr. Bullock, when he was vicar of St. John’s at Manchester, that it might be possible to control these phenomena, to make certain of complete repose, by chemical means. He, therefore, proposed to construct a special chamber provided with apparatus to insure this. The main idea was to introduce definitely soporific vapors, such as carbon dioxide, into the room, so that the patient might immediately fall into the deepest slumber. As soon as this occurs, the carbon dioxide is absorbed by opening troughs of sodium hydrate solution, which are kept in constant and gentle motion by electric stirrers. A supply of pure oxygen is then allowed to flow into the room, and, as the night proceeds, this is reinforced by ozone. There is also a further device for stimulating material chemically treated by certain salts. Another way is to prepare the patient by a very thorough Turkish bath. It must also be made sure that none of the other methods of elimination are working badly, and laxatives and diuretics given, if needs be.

The result of all this is that the patient, who has been very fully asleep, wakes up into equally full and clear consciousness. He wakes, in short, as a healthy boy does. He does not turn over and yawn and try to go to sleep again, but jumps out of bed and makes a beeline for the bath. With this treatment about one and a half to three hours is a full night’s rest for anybody. There is a proposal for establishing places where this treatment can be applied, but naturally it can only be used in cities. When it comes to our own city, we can all test it! In the meantime, this is but a chemical device, and there are other ways of solving the problem.

The Hindus have had their eye on it for a good many centuries. They divide mental states into three main types: sattva, calm wakefulness, contemplation; rajas, mental activity, excitement; tamas, dullness, sleep. The first only is considered proper to the healthy man; in their view rajas is a kind of fever, and tamas a kind of death. One of their reasons for diminishing diet to a minimum is that food always encourages one of the lower “Gunas” as they call these states. However, since one must eat, they have selected certain foods as proper to sattva. This is not altogether a digression, for it was on these lines that Dr. Bullock first attacked the problem in the “Nineteenth Century.” There is a rotation of these Gunas; they follow each other at more or less regular intervals; and if the Tamo-guna is in course, and the man is not asleep, it is due to some interference. It subsequently occurred to Dr. Bullock that he might break up the power of the Tamo-guna altogether. To him, as to Edison, sleep appeared an altogether deplorable waste of time, and, more than this, decidedly harmful. It was a drag on sattva; a breach in the continuity of pure consciousness; an interference with the will and the highest aspirations of man.

He wished to mediate ceaselessly and tirelessly upon the weakness of man, to find a remedy for all evil, and behold! he was himself a slave to the most degrading weakness. Even a few minutes of such intense thought as he, by long assiduity and courage, had developed, were sufficient to dull the keen razor of his mind. For that mind had become exquisitely sensitive to the smallest impression. He was capable of ordinary work of the hardest kind in a measure which few men have ever equalled; but the super-work of meditation requires quite a superhuman power. He recognized the Tamo-guna as the enemy, and proceeded to destroy it.

How? We shall now consider.

When he was quite a boy sloth had been his chief enemy. There were reasons of ill-health for this condition, but he nonetheless determined to do better. A friend of his, Bishop Pearsall, of Bath, happened to be a descendant of the Iron Duke; and this friend told him—at Trinity College—that it had been the custom of the great commander to sleep on a narrow plank, so that if he turned over, he fell off. The theory was that unless sleep were so deep as to involve absolute bodily stillness, it was imperfect; any movement whatsoever was conclusive proof that the sleeper had had enough.

Dr. Bullock determined to copy Wellington—a pardonable imitation—and had a plank made eleven inches wide. He proceeded to improve on the idea, however, by screwing a few “mummery spikes” (which are made for the boots of mountain climbers, and give firm hold on ice) into this plank. These nails were necessary, not for any reasons which would appeal to the ascetic, but because the bare board soon became perfectly comfortable to him, so that when he woke there was no immediate pain which might drive him to get up. Upon this thorny couch he still sleeps, night after night when at home, even to this day.

This practice soon altered completely the quality of his slumber. It became very light, and yet very restful; he learnt to wake instantly and fully at a moment’s notice; and he soon found that it was equally easy to fall off to sleep again the moment that his will consented. It also occurred, after a few days, that he found no tendency whatever to sleep during the fourth period of two hours; and the third soon followed suit. However, the result was, at first, boredom; he did not know what to do with the time; but Satan soon found some mischief for his idle hands to do; and by increasing his quota—writing lyrical verse—he quickly remedied his trouble.

He then shortened the periods to one-and-a-half and subsequently to one hour. He ultimately tried half hours, but this did not seem to be much of an improvement on the one-hour bouts, not enough, at least, to make it worthwhile to acquire the habit. In this way he practically conquered the problem. He is 48 years old; he has been a great traveler and explorer; much of his time is taken up by teaching and correspondence; he has achieved the most remarkable feats in many lines of life; yet what he has written for publication alone averages over ten words an hour since the minute he drew breath! Yet no one ever sees him work; he seems to lead the lazy, drawling life of a man of fashion. The secret is that he has learnt to bring his average hours of sleep down to three.

It is a secret well worth knowing. And now that it is disclosed, in part, it is within the reach of everybody to take a few weeks’ pains and master it.

The other part of the secret is of course the training of the mind to extreme intensity and concentration; and this, it must be admitted, probably requires a good deal of natural aptitude, and is in any case a harder task. Dr. Bullock has admitted his failure to do it, but it can be done, and the details of how to do it may one day furnish us with material for another paper.

Special Delivery

Meiklejohn, the curate, was walking through the Jura when this thing happened to him. There is only his word to vouch for it, for the inn and its proprietor are now both of the past, and the local record of the occurrence has long since assumed the proportions of a picturesque but inaccurate legend. As a true story, however, it stands out from those of its kidney by the fact that there seems to have been a deliberate intention in it. It saved a life—a life the world had need of. And this singular rescue of a man of value to the best order of things makes one feel that there was some sense, even logic, in the affair.

Moreover, Meiklejohn asserts that it was the only psychic experience he ever knew. Things of the sort were not a ‘habit’ with him. His rescue, thus, was not one of those meaningless interventions that puzzle the man in the street while they exhilarate the psychologist. It was a deliberate and very determined affair.

Meiklejohn found himself that hot August night in one of the valleys that slip like blue shadows hidden among pine-woods between the Swiss frontier and France. He had passed Ste. Croix earlier in the day; Les Rasses had been left behind about four o’clock; Buttes, and the Val de Travers, where the cement of many a London street conies from, was his goal. But the light failed long before he reached it, and he stopped at an inn that appeared unexpectedly round a corner of the dusty road, built literally against the great cliffs that formed one wall of the valley. He was so footsore, and his knapsack so heavy, that he turned in without more ado.

Le Guillaume Tell was the name of the inn—dirty white walls, with thin, almost mangy vines scrambling over the door, and the stream brawling beneath shuttered windows with green and white stripes all patched by sun and rain. His room was sevenpence, his dinner of soup, omelette, fruit, cheese, and coffee, a franc. The prices suited his pocket and made him feel comfortable and at home. Immediately behind the hotel—the only house visible, except the sawmill across the road, rose the ever-crumbling ridges and precipices that formed the flanks of Chasseront and ran on past La Sagne towards the grey Aiguilles de Baulmes. He was in the Jura fastnesses where tourists rarely penetrate.

Through the low doorway of the inn he carried with him the strong atmosphere of thoughts that had accompanied him all day—dreams of how he intended to spend his life, plans of sacrifice and effort. For his hopes of great achievement, even then at twenty-five, were a veritable passion in him, and his desire to spend himself for humanity a devouring flame. So’ occupied, indeed, was his mind with the emotions belonging to this line of thinking, that he hardly noticed the singular, though exceedingly faint, sense of alarm that stirred somewhere in the depths of his being as he passed within that doorway where the drooping vine-leaves clutched at his hat. He remembered it a little later. The sense of danger had been touched in him. He felt at the moment only a hint of discomfort, too vague to claim definite recognition. Yet it was there—the instant he stepped within the threshold—and afterwards he distinctly recalled its sudden and unaccountable advent.

His bedroom, though stuffy, as from windows long unopened, was clean; carpetless, of course, and primitive, with white pine floor and walls, and the short bed, smothered under its duvet, very creaky. And very short! For Meiklejohn was well over six feet.

‘I shall have to curl up, as usual, in a knot,’ was his reflection as he measured the bed with his eye; ‘though to-night I think—after my twenty miles in this air-‘

The thought refused to complete itself. He was going to add that he was tired enough to have slept on a stone floor, but for some undefined reason the same sense of alarm that had tapped him on the shoulder as he entered the inn returned now when he contemplated the bed. A sharp repugnance for that bed, as sudden and unaccountable as it was curious, swept into him—and was gone again before he had time to seize it wholly. It was in reality so slight that he dismissed it immediately as the merest fancy; yet, at the same time, he was aware that he would rather have slept on another bed, had there been one in the room—and then the queer feeling that, after all, perhaps, he would not sleep there in the end at all. How this idea came to him he never knew. He records it, however, as part of the occurrence.

After eight o’clock a few peasants, and workmen from the sawmill, came in to drink their demi-litre of red wine in the common room downstairs, to stare at the unexpected guest, and to smoke their vile tobacco. They were neither picturesque nor amusing—simply dirty and slightly malodorous. At nine o’clock Meiklejohn knocked the ashes from his briar pipe upon the limestone window-ledge, and went upstairs, overpowered with sleep. The sense of alarm had utterly disappeared; his mind was busy once more with his great dreams of the future—dreams that materialised themselves, as all the world knows, in the famous Meiklejohn Institutes. …

Berthoud, the proprietor, short and sturdy, with his faded brown coat and no collar, slightly confused . with red wine and a ‘tourist’ guest, showed him the way up. For, of course, there was no femme de chambre.

“You have the corridor all to yourself/ the man said; showed him the best corner of the landing to shout from in case he wanted anything—there being no bell—eyed his boots, knapsack, and flask with considerable curiosity, wished him good-night, and was gone. He went downstairs with a noise like a horse, thought the curate, as he locked the door after him.

The windows had been open now for a couple of hours, and the room smelt sweet with the odours of sawn wood and shavings, the resinous perfume of the surrounding hosts of pines, and the sharp, delicate touch of a lonely mountain valley where civilisation has not yet tainted the air. WhifFs of coarse tobacco, pungent without being offensive, came invisibly through the cracks of the floor. Primitive and simple it all was—a sort of vigorous ‘backwoods’ atmosphere. Yet, once again, as he turned to examine the room after Berthoud’s steps had blundered down below into the passage, something rose faintly within him to set his nerves mysteriously a-quiver.

Out of these perfectly simple conditions, without the least apparent cause, the odd feeling again came over him that he was—in danger.

The curate was not much given to analysis. He was a man of action pure and simple, as a rule. But to-night, in spite of himself, his thoughts went plunging, searching, asking. For this singular message of dread that emanated as it were from the room, or from some article of furniture in the room perhaps—that bed still touched his mind with a peculiar repugnance—demanded somewhat insistently for an explanation. And the only explanation that suggested itself to his unimaginative mind was that the forces of nature hereabouts were—overpowering; that, after the slum streets and factory chimneys of the last twelve months, these towering cliffs and smothering pine-forests communicated to his soul a word of grandeur that amounted to awe. Inadequate and far-fetched as the explanation seems, it was the only one that occurred to him; and its value in this remarkable adventure lies in the fact that he connected his sense of danger partly with the bed and partly with the mountains.

“I felt once or twice,’ he said afterwards, ‘as though some powerful agency of a spiritual kind were all the time trying to beat into my stupid brain a message of warning.’ And this way of expressing it is more true and graphic than many paragraphs of attempted analysis.

Meiklejohn hung his clothes by the open window to air, washed, read his Bible, looked several times over his shoulder without apparent cause, and then knelt down to pray. He was a simple and devout soul; his Self lost in the yearning, young but sincere, to live for humanity. He prayed, as usual, with intense earnestness that his life might be preserved for use in the world, when in the middle of his prayer—there came a knocking at the door.

Hastily rising from his knees, he opened. The sound of rushing water filled the corridor. He heard the voices of the workmen below in the drinking-room. But only darkness stood in the passages, filling the house to the very brim. No one was there. He returned to his interrupted devotions.

“I imagined it,’ he said to himself. He continued his prayers, however, longer than usual. At the back of his thoughts, dim, vague, half-defined only, lay this lurking sense of uneasiness—that he was in danger. He prayed earnestly and simply, as a child might pray, for the preservation of his life. …

Again, just as he prepared to get into bed, struggling to make the heaped-up duvet spread all over, came that knocking at the bedroom door. It was soft, wonderfully soft, and something within him thrilled curiously in response. He crossed the floor to open—then hesitated. Suddenly he understood that that knocking at the door was connected with the sense of danger in his heart. In the region of subtle intuitions the two were linked. With this realisation there came over him, he declares, a singular mood in which, as in a revelation, he knew that Nature held forces that might somehow communicate directly and positively with—human beings. This thought rushed upon him out of the night, as it were. It arrested his movements. He stood there upon the bare pine boards, hesitating to open the door. The delay thus described lasted actually only a few seconds, but in those few seconds these thoughts tore rapidly and like fire through his mind. The beauty of this lost and mysterious valley was certainly in his veins. He felt the strange presence of the encircling forests, soft and splendid, their million branches sighing in the night airs. The crying of the falling water touched him. He longed to transfer their peace and power to the hearts of suffering thousands of men and women and children. The towering precipices that literally dropped their pale walls over the roof of the inn lifted his thoughts to their own wind-swept heights; he longed to convey their message of inflexible strength to the weak-kneed folk in the slums where he worked. He was peculiarly conscious of the presence of these forces of Nature—the irresistible powers that regenerate as easily as they destroy.

All this, and far more, swept his soul like a huge wind as he stood there, waiting to open the door in answer to that mysterious soft knocking.

And there, when at length he opened, stood the figure of a man—staring at him and smiling.

Disappointment seized him instantly. He had expected, almost believed, that he would see something un-ordinary; and instead, there stood a man who had merely mistaken the door of his room, and was now bowing his apology for the interruption. Then, to his amazement, he saw that the man beckoned: the figure was some one who sought to draw him out.

“Come with me,” it seemed to say.

But Meiklejohn only realised this afterwards, he says, when it was too late and he had already shut the door in the stranger’s face. For the man had withdrawn into the darkness a little, and the curate had taken the movement for a mere acknowledgment of his mistake instead of—as he afterwards felt—a sign that he should follow.

“And the moment the door was shut/ he says, ‘I felt that it would have been better for me to have gone out into the passage to see what he wanted. It came over me that the man had something important to say to me. I had missed it.’

For some seconds, it seemed, he resisted the inclination to go after him. He argued with himself; then turned to his bed, pulled back the sheets and heavy duvet, and was met sharply again with the sense of repugnance, almost of fear, as before. It leaped out upon him—as though the drawing back of the blankets had set free some cold blast of .wind that struck him across the face and made him shiver.

At the same moment a shadow fell from behind his shoulder and dropped across the pillow and upper half of the bed. It may, of course, have been the magnified shadow of the moth that buzzed about the pale-yellow electric light in the ceiling. He does not pretend to know. It passed swiftly, however, and was gone; and Meiklejohn, feeling less sure of himself than ever before in his life, crossed the floor quickly, almost running, and opened the door to go after the man who had knocked—twice. For in reality less than half a minute had passed since the shutting of the door and its reopening.

But the corridor was empty. He marched down the pine-board floor for some considerable distance. Below he saw the glimmer of the hall, and heard the voices of the peasants and workmen from the sawmill as they still talked and drank their red wine in the public room. That sound of falling water, as before, filled the air. Darkness reigned. But the person—the messenger—who had twice knocked at his door was gone utterly. … Presently a door opened downstairs, and the peasants clattered out noisily. He turned and went back to bed. The electric light was switched off below. Silence fell. Conquering his strange repugnance, Meiklejohn, with a prayer on his lips, got into bed, and in less than ten minutes was sound asleep.

“I admit,” he says, in telling the story, “that what happened afterwards came so swiftly and so confusingly, yet with such a storm of overwhelming conviction of its reality, that its sequence may be somewhat blurred in my memory, while, at the same time, I see it after all these years as though it was a thing of yesterday. But in my sleep, first of all, I again heard that soft, mysterious tapping—not in the course of a dream of any sort, but sudden and alone out of the dark blank of forgetfulness. I tried to wake. At first, however, the bonds of unconsciousness held me tight. I had to struggle in order to return to the waking world. There was a distinct effort before I opened my eyes; and in that slight interval I became aware that the person who had knocked at the door had meanwhile opened it and passed into the room. I had left the lock unturned. The person was close beside me in the darkness—not in utter darkness, however, for a rising three-quarter moon shed its faint silver upon the floor in patches, and, as I sprang swiftly from the bed, I noticed something alive moving towards me across the carpetless boards. Upon the edges or a patch of moonlight, where the fringe of silver and shadow mingled, it stopped. Three feet away from it I, too, stopped, shaking in every muscle. It lay there crouching at my very feet, staring up at me. But was it man or was it animal? For at first I took it certainly for a human being on all fours; but the next moment, with a spasm of genuine terror that half stopped my breath, it was borne in upon me that the creature was—nothing human. Only in this way can I describe it. It was identical with the human figure who had knocked before and beckoned to me to follow, but it was another presentation of that figure.

‘And it held (or brought, if you will) some tremendous message for me—some message of tremendous importance, I mean. The first time I had argued, resisted, refused to listen. Now it had returned in a form that ensured obedience. Some quite terrific power emanated from it—a power that I understood instinctively belonged to the mountains and the forests and the untamed elemental forces of Nature. Amazing as it may sound in cold blood, I can only say that I felt as though the towering precipices outside had sent me a direct warning—that my life was in immediate danger.

“For a space that seemed minutes, but was probably less than a few seconds, I stood there trembling on the bare boards, my eyes riveted upon the dark, uncouth shape that covered all the floor beyond. I saw no limbs or features, no suggestion of outline that I could connect with any living form I know, animate or inanimate. Yet it moved and stirred all the time—whirled within itself, describes it best; and into my mind sprang a picture of an immense dark wheel, turning, spinning, whizzing so rapidly that it appears motionless, and uttering that low and ominous thunder that fills a great machinery-room of a factory. Then I thought of Ezekiel’s vision of the Living Wheels. …

“And it must have been at this instant, I think, that the muttering and deep note that issued from it formed itself into words within me. At any rate, I heard a voice that spoke with unmistakable intelligence:

‘” Come!” it said. “Come out—at once!” And the sense of power that accompanied the Voice was so splendid that my fear vanished and I obeyed instantly without thinking more. I followed; it led. It altered in shape. The door was open. It ran silently in a form that was more like a stream of deep black water than anything else I can think of—out of the room, down the stairs, across the hall, and up to the deep shadows that lay against the door leading into the road. There I lost sight of it.’

Meiklejohn’s only desire, he says, then was to rush after it—to escape. This he did. He understood that somehow it had passed through the door into the open air. Ten seconds later, perhaps even less, he, too, was in the open air. He acted almost automatically; reason, reflection, logic all swept away. Nowhere, however, in the soft moonlight about him was any sign of the extraordinary apparition that had succeeded in drawing him out of the inn, out of his bedroom, out of his—bed. He stared in a dazed way at everything—just beginning to get control of his faculties a bit—wondering what in the world it all meant. That huge spinning form, he felt convinced, lay hidden somewhere close beside him, waiting for the end. The danger it had enabled him to avoid was close at hand. … He knew that, he says. …

There lay the meadows, touched here and there with wisps of floating mist; the stream roared and tumbled down its rocky bed to his left; across the road the sawmill lifted its skeleton-like outline, moonlight shining on the dew-covered shingles of the roof, its lower part hidden in shadow. The cold air of the valley was exquisitely scented.

To the right, where his eye next wandered, he saw the thick black woods rising round the base of the precipices that soared into the sky, sheeted with silvery moonlight. His gaze ran up them to the far ridges that seemed to push the very stars farther into the heavens. Then, as he saw those stars crowding the night, he staggered suddenly backwards, seizing the wall of the road for support, and catching his breath. For the top of the cliff, he fancied, moved. A group of stars was for a fraction of a second—hidden. The earth—the scenery of the valley, at least—turned about him. Something prodigious was happening to the solid structure of the world. The precipices seemed to bend over upon the valley. The far, uppermost ridge of those beetling cliffs shifted downwards. Meiklejohn declares that the way its movement hid momentarily a group of stars was the most startling—for some reason horrible—thing he had ever witnessed.

Then came the roar and crash and thunder as the mass toppled, slid, and finally—took the frightful plunge. How long the forces of rain and frost had been chiselling out the slow detachment of the giant slabs that fell, or whence came the particular extra little push that drove the entire mass out from the parent rock, no one can know. Only one thing is certain: that it was due to no chance, but to the nicely and exactly calculated results of balanced cause and effect. From the beginning of time it had been known—it might have been accurately calculated, rather—that this particular thousand tons of rock would break away from the crumbling tops of the precipices and crash downwards with the roar of many tempests into the lost and mysterious mountain valley where Meiklejohn the curate spent such and such a night of such and such a holiday. It was just as sure as the return of Halley’s comet.

‘I watched it/ he says,’ because I couldn’t do anything else. I would far rather have run—I was so frightfully close to it all—but I couldn’t move a muscle. And in a few seconds it was over. A terrific wind knocked me backwards against the stone wall; there was a vast clattering of smaller stones, set rolling down the neighbouring couloirs; a steady roll of echoes ran thundering up and down the valley; and then all was still again exactly as it had been before. And the curious thing was—ascertained a little later, as you may imagine, and not at once—that the inn, being so closely built up against the cliffs, had almost entirely escaped. The great mass of rock and trees had taken a leap farther out, and filled the meadows, blocked the road, crushed the sawmill like a matchbox, and dammed up the stream; but the inn itself was almost untouched.

‘Almost—for a single block of limestone, about the size of a grand piano, had dropped straight upon one corner of the roof and smashed its way through my bedroom, carrying everything it contained down to the level of the cellar, so terrific was the momentum of its crushing journey. Not a stick of the furniture was afterwards discoverable—as such. The bed seems to have been caught by the very middle of the fallen mass.’

The confusion in Meiklejohn’s mind may be imagined—the rush of feeling and emotion that swept over him. Berthoud and the peasants mustered in less than a dozen minutes, talking, crying, praying. Then the stream, dammed up by the accumulation of rock, carried off the debris of the broken roof and walls in less than half an hour. The rock, however, that swept the room and the empty bed of Meiklejohn the curate into dust, still lies in the valley where it fell.

‘The only other thing that I remember,’ he says, in telling the story, ‘is that, as I stood there, shaking with excitement and the painful terror of it all, before Berthoud and the peasants had come to count over their number and learn that no one was missing—while I stood there, leaning against the wall of the road, something rose out of the white dust at my feet, and, with a noise like the whirring of some immense projectile, passed swiftly and invisibly away up into space—so far as I could judge, towards the distant ridges that reared their motionless outline in moonlight beneath the stars.’

Spring and the Mountaineer

With these first softer winds of spring there breaks upon the mind a thought of flowers, sunny woods, mountains soaring through haze into blue skies—visions of some fair playground. For old Pan is out again. He has stepped forth from that “everlasting lair” of his, and pipe in hand—those huge yet gentle hands—is running over the world. And his music is strangely disquieting; it stirs the deep migratory instinct—to break camp and move on further. One sees water running through the meadows with feet of silver, hears the idle flapping of a sail, tastes in the very thickest of the office atmosphere the fresh, keen fragrance of some upland dawn. One longs to burn the desks and be off without delay. It is all very upsetting—this wild, sweet message spring brings, whispering cunningly to the heart that there are places where the world has never grown old, and that if one can only get away quickly enough, one’s own youth can be caught there, unchanged, untamed. Very fleeting, very fugitive, too; for most of us, alas, gone before it seized—a dream one sets aside with other dreams If only the bodily and physical transfer could be immediate, it might be otherwise! If one could shoot across the earth’s surface to these lovely places to catch them before the midsummer pomps have robbed them of their wonderful first suggestiveness—in May and early June!

With the waning of March the dream is apt to return more insistently, crossing the threshold into waking and action. One remembers that there is no harm, even thus early, in greasing the heavy stiff leather of the mountain boots, putting in new nails, airing that old grimy knapsack and seeing that the traps are right. It brings the playground nearer. The thoughts of thousands turn to their luring memories of the Alps: Italy, Tyrol, Switzerland. Eyes turn to flaming posters in the streets, the mind considers routes, the fingers probably turn the pages of a timetable as though it were some novel of adventure; a few may even hear the wind in those “dark clustered trees” that “fledge the wild-ridged mountains steep by steep.”

And at once, though with a sense of impatience that will not be denied, one’s daily work grows lighter. Magic names flit through the memory—the Engadine, the Bernese Oberland, the peaks of Valais and the valleys of Savoy, the flowered uplands of Tyrol, the rustling chestnut woods of the Italian slopes, or the Bernina snowfields, rosy in the dawn. They are endlessly seductive; the scenery passes through the mind with a vividness of cinematograph films. One feels the blazing sunshine on the dusty roads of the Upper Engadine, returning from a climb that began before the dawn. The peasants are already bringing down their hay—the early June crop, and the fields will yield at least two more before October slips upon the valley with its touch of frost and a wind chilled by the first flurries of snow. In the middle of the road the cart stands upon its tiny wheels, thick dust over the oxen hoofs, and the hay piled up on it in huge, bursting bundles packed in canvas sheets. It is three-parts flowers, and the perfume fills the air deliciously. Three hours before one passed the peasants, men and women, scything it on slopes of perilous steepness, still wet with sparkling dew, patches of Alpenrosen gleaming in between. The still air rings with the gentle music of the cowbells and the elusive tinkle of the smaller ones carried by the wandering herds of goats. For the goats are everywhere. In the valleys of the Austrian Tyrol, especially, the faint chiming comes upon every wind and haunts the air as inevitably as that other sound of falling water. The memory brings back the two together. Those small grey spots on some high, hanging slope beneath the very snow that looked like rocks, rise suddenly in a body and drift away to yet more dangerous declivities; the sound of bells floats across the deep, narrow valley; one thinks of “horns of Elfland faintly blowing” … the goats dot every landscape. Far above the tree-line, when life is least expected, one turns a corner, and there, lying among the boulders, grouped perhaps about some little wooden cross, their bodies rise out of the very ground, horns glistening in the sunshine. Not far away, hatless and usually barefooted, hovers the boy or girl who shepherds them, idly singing, or playing the hours away on some rude flute of home manufacture, and not uncommonly carrying in his arms a tired or injured young one. Dogs, except in the Bernese Alps, where, as a rule, they are big, ugly, savage brutes, are rarely seen with the flocks, but in the Valais villages every chalet owns at least one—cat! I remember seeing once, on the high uplands towards the frontier of Savoy, a herd of fifty goats led by a barelegged girl to early pasture, all following in single file a—tabby cat. With tail erect, jerking the dew from its paws delicately, it proudly showed the way. “It has done so since its kitten days,” said the girl. It rubbed against their legs, and when they butted it in play it easily evaded the horns and showed no fear. She told me that one year they also had a stork! Her father found it on the mountains in the late autumn, delayed in its flight southwards by a broken leg. He healed the leg and kept the bird all the winter in the chalet, where it established a firm, if curious, friendship with the cat. In the spring, as soon as he heard that the other storks had returned to their chimneys of South Germany, he let it go, watching it fly away northwards with unerring instinct across the mountains to find its own again.

The pictures throng and crowd; there comes again the perfume of the pine woods, baked in sunshine; the scents of thousand flowers where the swallowtails and apollos dance with the fritillaries; in the evenings the echoing notes of the great Alpine horns as the peasants call the cattle home: the banks of the rock-strewn torrent where they go down to drink and always that sky of clear and brilliant blue overhead … As yet the snow still lies thick, of course, but these first softer winds of spring are already at work upon it, “eating it up,” as the peasants say, “far more quickly than the sun,” The roar of the swollen torrents fills the air. The upper chalets, locked and shuttered all the winter often lying flush with the ground beneath enormous drifts, are being opened now. One thinks, and dreams, and calculates, making delightfu| plans. Old Pan has brought the news. Last night was heard that searching music of his pipes among the chimney-pots … and one begins to count the days.

Spring in Switzerland

There are places, it seems, where the earth, for all her aching load of time, cannot grow old, but retains her carefree spirit of unselfconscious youth. If one is lying at this time of year upon a green “alp,” some three thousand feet above the Rhone Valley, it is idle to remind oneself that human life has probably existed on the planet for 400,000 years: the fact is neither credible nor important. This landscape, surely, has but just emerged, clean and sparkling, from its primal chaos, a perfect thing, without a past, without traditions, without the sense of tears that brims up so often out of ancientness. This sea of flowers, rushing into form and colour the moment the snow melts, foams over the grass for the first time. No one has seen them before, nor do they expect to be seen. The mind receives the overflowing beauty without a hint of the weariness that thoughts of the long, long past bring usually. Laughter, dance and song are the passwords here, not reflection.

As spring steals over this region between the valleys and the heights, there comes with her a lightheartedness that belongs only to youth. Switzerland belongs to the childhood of the world, and the man who first called it the Playground of Europe had a moment of inspiration. A playground can offer little to the sophisticated, but spring in this land of running water and abundant flowers can certainly offer this magic touch of earth when it was young. The toy chalets, perched here and there as only a child, it seems, would perch them; the profusion of Christmas trees, balanced in ranks as though set upon flat wooden pedestals: the very cows emerging from long winter seclusion in countless picturesque arks, kicking and dancing as they taste the delicious lower pastures—all these contribute to the conviction that one has stumbled upon some primal nursery, where the earth is at play, refusing to be serious. The air is full of the sound of bells. There is even the detail of the naughty cow, punished for wilful disobedience by being deprived of her bell, put in the corner thus, and sent to Coventry, before the rest of the herd.

Few besides the natives, come to witness this annual exhibition of gay, carefree youthfulness. The winter tourists have gone home, the summer horde not yet arrived; the larger hotels, lately packed with teeming life, are given over to a general cleaning which makes them look as if they could never be habitable again; and the smaller inns, always open, attract no visitors as yet. Above four thousand feet, the snow still lies thick, and an occasional enthusiast, lingering on for wet-snow skiing, may still be seen, despite the uncomfortable heat of the sun, and although, in the valleys, the orchards are in bloom. He haunts the northern slopes, for the Souther ones that take the full sun are bright emerald green, held b the million flowers, with countless rivulets that sing their way over the soaked grass. This mood of generous exuberance when spring brings her profusion at about three thousand feet, is enjoyed every year by only a handful of adventurous; residents, who know just where to look for it.

A brief period, of course, but one of vivid, sharp refreshment it passes gradually up the great mountain sides. To each layer of a thousand feet, as summer threatens, and spring climbs higher, she brings the appropriate flowers; Whe summer is established at a thousand feet, spring flits to the next thousand feet above, taking her primulas, her soldanellas her anemones with her; above seven thousand feet or so she may be found even in the heats of August. The “région d’en haut,” as they call it, retains during April and May this happy air of careless youth, where the earth refuses to grow old. Daring the late spring storms, and before the summer blaze begins, is the time to taste it.

In so many places, and to so many minds, spring, with her hint of promises unfulfilled, conceals behind her gaiety a touch of sadness. The loveliest of old gardens has its wistfulness; the startling places, where emotions are deep and strong, their melancholy. To Paestum, for instance, where the Greek temples rise out of the forsaken plain, between the blue sea and the yet bluer Calabrian Hills, where roses and violets bloom twice a year, spring brings no lightheartedness, but rather the reverse:

“O world, in very truth thou art too young!
When wilt thou learn to wear the garb of age?
World with thy covering of yellow flowers!
Hast thou forgot what generations sprung
Out of thy loins, and loved thee, and are gone?
Hast thou no place in all their heritage
Where thou dost only weep—that I may come,
Nor fear the mockery of thy yellow flowers?”

Here on this green alp above the Rhéne Valley, spring invokes a gayer song than this mournful utterance. Remembering some great poet who “sang about thy prime,” one hears him singing still, entirely oblivious that “the worm had hardly left his tongue before thy nightingales were come again.” If necessary to remember anything in particular, it would be surely about “the cow jumped over the moon,” “dickory dickory dock,” or else about “Little Boy Blue, come blow your horn.” Nursery songs are here the appropriate note.

Strange Disappearance of a Baronet

His intrinsic value before the Eternities was exceedingly small, but he possessed most things the world sets store by—presence, name, wealth—and, above all, that high opinion of himself which saves it the bother of a separate and troublesome valuation. Outside these possessions he owned nothing of permanent value, or that could decently claim to be worthy of immortality. The fact was he had never even experienced that expansion of self commonly known as generosity. No apology, however, is necessary for his amazing adventure, for these same Eternities who judged him have made their affidavit that it was They who stripped him bare and showed himself to himself.

It all began with the receipt of that shattering letter from his solicitors. He read and reread it in his comfortable first-class compartment as the express hurried him to town, exceedingly comfortable among his rugs and furs, exceedingly distressed and ill at ease in his mind. And in his private sitting-room of the big hotel that same evening Mr. Smirles, more odious even than his letter, informed him plainly that this new and unexpected claimant to his title and estates was likely to be exceedingly troublesome “even dangerous, Sir Timothy! I am bound since you ask that it might be wise to regard the future—er—with a different scale of vision than the one you have been accustomed to.”

Sir Timothy practically collapsed. Instinctively he perceived that the lawyer’s manner already held less respect: the reflection was a shock to his vain and fatuous personality. “After all, then, it wasn’t me he worshipped, but my position, and so forth … !” If this nonsense continued he would be no longer “Sir Timothy,” but simply “Mister” Puffe, poor, a nobody. He seemed to shrink in size as he gazed at himself in the mirror of the gorgeous, flamboyantly decorated room. “It’s too preposterous and absurd! There’s nothing in it! Why, the whole County would go to pieces without me!” He even thought of making his secretary draft a letter to the Times a letter of violent, indignant protest.

He was a handsome, portly man, with a full-blown vanity justified by no single item of soul or mind; not unkind, so much as empty; created and kept alive by the small conventions and the ceaseless contemplation of himself, the withdrawal of which might be expected to leave him flat as a popped balloon. … Such a mass of pompous conceit obscured his vision that he only slowly took in the fact that his very existence was at stake. His thoughts rumbled on without direction, the sense of loss, however, dreadfully sharp and painful all the time, till at length he sought relief in something he could really understand. He changed for dinner! He would dine in his sitting-room alone. And, meanwhile, he rang for the remainder of his voluminous luggage. But it was vastly annoying to his diminishing pride to discover that the gorgeous Head Porter (he remembered now having vaguely recognised him in the hall) was the same poor relation to whom he had denied help a year ago. The vicissitudes of life were indeed preposterous. He ought to have been protected from so ridiculous an encounter. For the moment, of course, he merely pretended not to see him—certainly he did not commend the excellently quick delivery of the luggage. And to praise the young fellow’s pluck never occurred to him for one single instant.

“The house valet, please,” he asked of the waiter who answered the bell soon afterwards—and then directed somewhat helplessly the unpacking of his emporium of exquisite clothes. “Yes, take everything out—everything,” he said in reply to the man’s question—rather an extraordinary, almost insolent question when he came to reflect upon it, surely: “Is it worth while, perhaps, sir … ?” It flashed across his dazed mind that the Head Porter had made the very same remark to his subordinate in the passage when he asked if “everything” was to come in. With a shrug of his gold-braided shoulders that poor relation had replied, “Seems hardly worth while, but they may as well all go in, yes.”

And, with the double rejoinder perplexingly in his mind, Sir Timothy turned sharply upon the valet.

But the thing he was going to say faded on his lips. The man, holding out in his arms a heap of clothes, suits and whatnot, seemed so much taller than before. Sir Timothy had looked down upon him a moment ago, whereas now their eyes stared level. It was passing strange.

“Will you want these, sir?”

“Not tonight, of course.”

“Want them at all, I meant, sir?”

Sir Timothy gasped. “Want them at all? Of course! What in the world are you talking about?”

“Beg pardon, sir. Didn’t know if it was worth while now,” the man said, with a quick flush. And, before the pompous and amazed baronet could get any words between his quivering lips, the man was gone. The waiter, Head Waiter it was, answered the bell almost immediately, and Sir Timothy found consolation for his injured feelings in discussing food and wine. He ordered an absurdly sumptuous meal for a man dining alone. He did so with a vague feeling that it would spite somebody, perhaps; he hardly knew whom. “The Pol Roger well iced, mind,” he added with a false importance as the clever servant withdrew. But at the door the man paused and turned, as though he had not heard. “Large bottle, I said,” repeated the other. The Head Waiter made an extraordinary gesture of indifference. “As you wish, Sir Timothy, as you wish!” And he was gone in his turn. But it was only the man’s adroitness that had chosen the words instead of those others: “Is it really worth while?”

And at that very moment, while Sir Timothy stood there fuming inwardly over the extraordinary words and ways of these people—veiled insolence, he called it—the door opened, and a tall young woman poked her head inside, then followed it with her person. She was dignified, smart even for a hotel like this, and uncommonly pretty. It was the upper housemaid. Full in the eye she looked at him. In her face was a kind of swift sympathy and kindness; but her whole presentment betrayed more than anything else—terror.

“Make an effort, make an effort!” she whispered earnestly. “Before it’s too late, make an effort!” And she was gone. Sir Timothy, hardly knowing what he meant to do, opened the door to dash after her and make her explain this latest insolence. But the passage was dark, and he heard the swish of skirts far away—too far away to overtake; while running along the walls, as in a whispering gallery, came the words, “Make an effort, make an effort!”

“Confound it all, then, I will!” he exclaimed to himself, as he stumbled back into the room, feeling horribly bewildered. “I will make an effort.” And he dressed to go downstairs and show himself in the halls and drawing-rooms, give a few pompous orders, assert himself, and fuss about generally. But that process of dressing without his valet was chiefly and weirdly distressing because he had so amazingly—dwindled. His sight was, of course, awry; disordered nerves had played tricks with vision, proportion, perspective; something of the sort must explain why he seemed so small to himself in the reflection. The pier-glass, which showed him full length, he turned to the wall. But, none the less, to complete his toilet, he had to stand upon a footstool before the other mirror above the mantelpiece.

And go downstairs he did, his heart working with a strange and increasing perplexity. Yet, wherever he went, there came that poor relation, the Head Porter, to face him. Always big, he now looked bigger than ever. Sir Timothy Puffe felt somehow ridiculous in his presence. The young fellow had character, pluck, some touch of intrinsic value. For all his failure in life, the Eternities considered him real. He towered rather dreadfully in his gold braid and smart uniform—towered in his great height all about the hall, like some giant in his own palace. The other’s head scarcely came up to his great black belt where the keys swung and jangled.

The Baronet went upstairs again to his room, strangely disconcerted. The first thing he did as he left the lift was to stumble over the step. The liftman picked him up as though he were a boy. Down the passage, now well lighted, he went quickly, his feet almost pattering, his tread light, and—so oddly short. His importance had gone. A voice behind each door he passed whispered to him through the narrow crack as it cautiously opened, “Make an effort, make an effort! Be yourself, be real, be alive before it’s too late!” But he saw no one, and the first thing he did on entering his room was to hide the smaller mirror by turning it against the wall, just as he had done to the pier-glass. He was so painfully little and insignificant now. As the externals and the possessions dropped away one by one in his thoughts, the revelation of the tiny little centre of activity within was horrible. He puffed himself out in thought as of old, but there was no response. It was degrading.

The fact was—he began to understand it now—his mind had been pursuing possible results of his loss of title and estates to their logical conclusion. The idea in all its brutal nakedness, of course, hardly reached him-namely, that, without possessions, he was practically—nil! All he grasped was that he was—less. Still, the notion did prey upon him atrociously. He followed the advice of the strange housemaid and “made an effort,” but without marked success. So empty, indeed, was his life that, once stripped of the possessions, he would stand there as useless and insignificant as an ownerless street dog. And the thought appalled him. He had not even enough real interest in others to hold him upright, and certainly not enough sufficiency of self, good or evil, to stand alone before any tribunal. The discovery shocked him inexpressibly. But what distressed him still more was to find a fixed mirror in his sitting-room that he could not take down, for in its depths he saw himself shrunken and dwindled to the proportions of a …

The knock at the door and the arrival of his dinner broke the appalling train of thought, but rather than be seen in his present diminutive appearance—later, of course, he would surely grow again—he ran into the bedroom. And when he came out again after the waiter’s departure he found that his dinner shared the same abominable change. The food upon the dishes was reduced to the minutest proportions—the toast like children’s, the soup an egg-cupful, the tenderloin a little slice the size of a visiting-card, and the bird not much larger than a black-beetle. And yet more than he could eat; more than sufficient! He sat in the big chair positively lost, his feet dangling. Then, mortified, frightened, and angry beyond expression, he undressed and concealed himself beneath the sheets and blankets of his bed.

“Of course I’m going mad—that’s what it all means,” he exclaimed. “I’m no longer of any account in the world. I could never go into my Club, for instance, like this!”—and he surveyed the small outline that made a little lump beneath the surface of the bedclothes—“or read the lessons having to stand upon a chair to reach the lectern.” And tears of bleeding vanity and futile wrath mingled upon his pillow. … . The humiliation was agonising.

In the middle of which the door opened and in came the hotel valet, bearing before him upon a silver salver what at first appeared to be small, striped sandwiches, darkish in hue, but upon closer inspection were seen to be several wee suits of clothes, neatly pressed and folded for wearing. Glancing round the room and perceiving no one, the man proceeded to put them away in the chest of drawers, soliloquising from time to time as he did so.

“So the old buffer did go out after all!” he reflected, as he smoothed the tiny trousers in the drawer. “’E’s nothing but a gasbag, anyway! Close with the coin, too—always was that! He whistled, spat in the grate, hunted about for a cigarette, and again found relief in speech. My little dawg’s worth two of ’im all the time, and lots to spare. Tim’s real … !” And other things, too, he said in similar vein. He was utterly oblivious of Sir Timothy’s presence—serenely unconscious that the thin, fading line beneath the sheets was the very individual he was talking about. “Even hides his cigarettes, does he? He’s right, though. Take away what he’s got and there wouldn’t be enough left over to stand upright at a poultry show!” And he guffawed merrily to himself. But what brought the final horror into that vanishing Personality on the bed was the singular fact that the valet made no remark about the absurd and horrible size of those tiny clothes. This, then, was how others—even a hotel valet—saw him!

All night long, it seemed, he lay in atrocious pain, the darkness mercifully hiding him, though never from himself, and only towards daylight did he pass off into a condition of unconsciousness. He must have slept very late indeed, too, for he woke to find sunlight in the room, and the housemaid—that tall, dignified girl who had tried to be kind—dusting and sweeping energetically. He screamed to her, but his voice was too feeble to make itself heard above the sweeping. The high-pitched squeak was scarcely audible even to himself. Presently she approached the bed and flung the sheets back. “That’s funny,” she observed, “could’ve sworn I saw something move!” She gave a hurried look, then went on sweeping. But in the process she had tossed his person, now no larger than a starved mouse, out on to the carpet. He cried aloud in his anguish, but the squeak was too faint to be audible. “Ugh!” exclaimed the girl, jumping to one side, “there’s that ’orrid mouse again! Dead, too, I do declare!” And then, without being aware of the fact, she swept him up with the dust and bits of paper into her pan.

Whereupon Sir Timothy awoke with a bad start, and perceived that his train was running somewhat uneasily into King’s Cross, and that he had slept nearly the whole way.

Summering in Canadian Backwoods

With the word Muskoka there rises before my mind a picture of ideal summer loveliness. Three lakes I see, each about twenty miles by four, hidden cosily away in the heart of an immense stretch of Canadian forest. They are dotted with miniature archipelagos of pine-clad islands of every shape and size, that seem to float half on the blue waters and half in the haze of the soft Indian summer. The smoke of forest fires is in the air, with its strange fragrance and its mystery. Down the glades that everywhere pierce the huge mainland pinewoods flash the crimson and golden fires of dying maples and basswood trees. It is September. A pleasant west wind has been blowing all day, and is now going to rest with the sun. On its last breath come the resinous odours from miles and miles of trees basking all day long in the delicious heat—thousands and thousands of hemlock, pine, cedar, spruce and balsam. There are shadows in the sky and upon the lake. Already the eastern shores of the islands are growing dark, and night is settling down upon the woods—woods carpeted with moss a foot thick and knee-high with troops of graceful ferns.

There is a growing stillness in the air. Every moment the waves pass and lessen, weary of their long dance to the ceaseless music of the west wind; the streaks of foam melt away into the gathering darkness; the tumbling of the surf upon the shore sinks into a confused murmur, and the wind in the crests of the hemlocks sighs forth its gentle welcome to the stars. The lake is composing itself for sleep—its long, dreamless sleep beneath the moon that soon now will rise over the distant ridge of pines. Soon there will be no sound but the splash and drip round the grey Laurentian rocks that fringe every island and run out here and there into dangerous jagged reefs. But, perhaps, if your ears are trained to the necessary degree, you may catch that faint indescribable murmur of the forest life coming down to drink, the bestirring of countless slender legs, the shaking of furry bodies, and the tread of small feet and hoofs on the moss and pine needles. For with the setting of the sun the forest life rises and moves. It travels by night and rests by day. The evening drink is the beginning and not the end of the activity. The glades are alive and moving, and the moon peeping through the tangle of branches sees graceful shifting forms where a few hours before the sunlight found only ferns and moss and eddies of fallen leaves.

And when the sun is quite down, and the stars are out, perhaps the Northern Lights will dance and flash in weird splendour round the polestar for half the night, winning wonderful reflections from the still waters and warning the watchful hunters of the approach of cold and stormy weather.

The Muskoka Lakes have a charm peculiarly their own, and the summers I have spent in that invigorating atmosphere of pine forests, 800 feet above the sea, sometimes with tent and canoe, sometimes in the greater luxury of the hospitable island-homes, are certainly among the pleasantest memories of many years spent in Canada. Yet this fascinating nook in the Ontario backwoods is unknown to the ordinary traveller. Having “done” Niagara and Quebec, he forsakes Eastern Canada and rushes on with feverish haste to see the great lakes, the prairies and the giant Rockies. No one in a hurry would think much of Muskoka; no mind filled with terrifying pictures of the ocean-lakes of Huron and Superior or the vast precipices and glaciers of the Selkirks could find rest and enjoyment among those secluded little pools of blue waters. And so it is that this region of fairy loveliness, so deftly mosaiced into the endless network of lakes and streams that lie east of Huron and 150 miles north of Toronto, is neglected by the globetrotter and unvisited by the average tourist, greedy of wonder and eager for the exaggerated scenery of the Far West. For which neglect, however, there is nothing to be felt but the most devout thankfulness and relief.

Fifty years ago, and less, the Muskoka region was unadulterated backwoods. The fat black bears enjoyed the countless blueberries all to themselves, and no one disturbed the deer as they swam from island to island or sharpened their horns on the rough bark of the great hemlock stems. In the summer mosquitoes held sway over all, and in the winter both lakes and trees were covered with a carpet of snow six feet thick, that could not melt much before the end of March, because the temperature was never above zero and sometimes 40 below it. Now, however, Muskoka is only comparatively backwoods—with all their charm and few of their hardships. A railway skirts its eastern border, tapping the lakes at Gravenhurst on its way from Toronto to North Bay (Canadian Pacific Railway), and there are Scotch and English settlers on the shores of its picturesque lakes. After the settlers, who got their land for nothing and get nothing out of their land, came the hunters and the fishermen, and these soon found out that the delightful little islands, where they had fired their black bass and cooked their venison, would be ideal spots for summer homes. And so, one by one, the hunters brought up their families, and cottages were built on the prettiest islands. At the juncture of the three main lakes, Port Carling grew rapidly from a sawmill and a sluice to a village with a general store and a church; the Indian posts became hamlets; schools were built to which the settlers’ children went many miles round the shores of the lakes; a line of steamers was organised in connection with the railway; the larger stores sent puffing little provision boats from island to island, and in a few years Muskoka stepped forth from the untrodden wilderness, and was introduced to Montreal and Toronto folk as a full-blown Canadian watering-place with the most charming face and manners in the world.

The three lakes form a capital Y, of which Lake Muskoka is the stem, Lake Rosseau the right, and Lake Joseph the left branch. Two steamers leave the railway at the foot of Lake Muskoka, and together enter the lock at Port Carling, whence however they take opposite courses—the one sailing through the lovely reaches of Lake Rosseau till it reaches the old Indian post of that name at the far head; the other steering among the wild and tortuous channels of Lake Joseph, past the cliffs of the Crow’s Nest and the grandest scenery of the whole region, till it anchors in the wee harbour of Port Cockburn and gathers strength for the return journey on the following day to Gravenhurst. These steamers stop at any or all of the islands to disembark or take up passengers. Only a signal is necessary, and, weather permitting, they sidle up to the primitive wharves and bring additions to these free and easy summer camps in the shape of provisions or new arrivals. In rough weather there is often a safety wharf on the other side, away from the sharp rocks and sheltered from the sweep of the open water. The “wharf” is of the simplest possible description. In the winter huge hollow frameworks are built on the ice and filled with stones; then the ice is sawn through and the great things sink down to their proper places on the bottom of the lake; a platform is nailed across them, and the wharf is complete. Every island today has its wharf and house, the latter being sometimes a mere camping shanty of pine-boards, and sometimes a more pretentious wooden cottage with wide encircling verandah, two storeys, boathouse, icehouse, and even brick chimneys. The heat of the Muskoka summer is always tempered with plenty of ice—ice to make cooling drinks and to keep sweet the fish and perishables in the larder; for in the winter the nearest settler is glad enough to earn a few dollars by sawing several hundred blocks of ice fourteen inches thick from the surface of the frozen lake, and pack them deep in sawdust in the shed built for that purpose.

But the first-comers to Muskoka had neither ice, nor wharves, nor boathouses. They pitched their tents beneath the singing pine trees and paddled their graceful canoes wherever they pleased, sharing the fishing and hunting with the Chippewa Indians, and careless quite of the passage of time so long as they escaped back to civilisation before the lake became ice, and those fearful freezing winds whistled down from the north. To a long, slender island, shaped like a snake, in Lake Joseph, came the first group of Muskoka pioneers. They were five in number, and they bought the island from the government for a mere song and divided it into fifths. It was christened Yohocucaba, after the first syllable of each of their names, and today it is known as Yoho for short: there is a little post-office on it, and the sole remaining owner and occupier is Professor Campbell, of Montreal—the fourth syllable of that extraordinary baptism. Yoho is nearly a mile long, and nowhere more than a few hundred yards wide. It is a ridge of pine-covered rock in the far corners of Lake Josephy. On its lower end, in the rustling shade of a grove of magnificent hemlocks, a church service is held for the benefit of the islanders in the months of July and August. No bell announces the fact, but towards eleven o’clock on one of those hot Sundays I can see the canoes coming over the blue waves from every point of the great lake. Every island sends its contribution—skiffs, boats, sailboats, sedate family boats with three pairs of oars, mackinawa with white sails light in the fresh breeze—all sorts and kinds speeding across the lake and converging to the point of Yoho, where the wharf makes landing easy, What a picture they make in the brilliant sunshine, and what a singular charm the fleet of graceful, slender-nosed canoes lends to it all. Of every colour imaginable, from the dirty blue-white of the old stager, the dull grey of the much-worn birch-bark, to the fanciful crimsons, white with gold edges, and the pale yellow cedars that always tell of feminine owners. Silently and swiftly they come over the waves, gliding if it is smooth, leaping and dancing if the wind is fresh enough to make a little sea, just like things of life, the playful, gaily dressed spirits of these endless Canadian lakes. In one I see two men paddling with strong, sweeping strokes, men in white duck with faces brown as the Indians. In another a boy brings two girls in light summer frocks, with faces radiant as the sunshine. A third holds three girls all paddling at once; while a fourth, perilously close to the water, holds four young people—one in the stern, one in the bows, and two sardine-wise between the centre thwarts. The simple service, with the singing of our old English hymns and the eloquent address from Professor Campbell, standing bareheaded under the pines among the reclining audience—what a picture it all makes in the memory—the treetops bending and sighing overhead, and the water perpetually murmuring among the rocks and past the sides of the canoes at our feet. There is a subtle fascination in the Muskoka air that makes each summer seem sweeter than the last. Life there is ever delightful. It appeals to the dreamer as well as to the man of action. In those vast solitudes of wood and water one is conscious of a spirit that curiously combines a careless eastern languor with the immense potential energies of the west. In Muskoka you may dream, yet not be ashamed. It is only that the realities of life have sunk away out of sight below that far blue horizon of forest, and that the magical moonlight of those August nights brings an influence so soothing and restful that your too active spirit enters into the sweet sleep of the trees and waves, and you gather and store up, without expending it, strength for the duties that must come later. You may dream without enervating effect, for the working of the Muskoka divinity is first quieting, afterwards uplifting.

The enterprise of the pioneering quintet was quickly followed by others. The islands in each lake were bought up in turn. Well-wooded islands, some mere little rocks of an acre, others small continents of twenty to thirty acres, that were purchased in those days for a few pounds apiece, are now worth—though not intrinsically—ten times as much; and with the subsequent coming of the railway and the steamers the uttermost ends of Lake Rosseau and Lake “Jo” (as it is familiarly called) are within twelve hours of Toronto, and at a cost that need terrify no one.

Those early days in Muskoka before all the islands were inhabited and built upon, and before the settlers had erected their huge, unsightly caravansarais of yellow-painted wood, must have been exceptionally charming: the picnics, the exploration trips, the nightly campfires, and the paddling homewards under the stars; when the provision boats were not known, and it was important to catch fish for the table; and when letters were a weekly event, and not, as now, a daily certainty with the evening steamer. The edge of the wildness of those days has perhaps been taken off; but, even so, Muskoka is still the genuine backwoods, and you have only to carry your canoe over a few “portages,” and paddle it across a few lakes and streams to the west and north, to find yourself in the trackless and awful solitudes of a wilderness that at first frightens, that it may forever after completely fascinate you.

The settlers in the pioneer days must have had truly a lonely time of it. The soil is thinly scattered upon the surface of those ancient rocks. Only in the little valleys of this undulating territory, which never rises to the grandeur of real hills, is there any shelter or depth of earth. Poor oats, potatoes, and a few other vegetables, represent the Muskoka crops; but, on the other hand, “Muskoka mutton” is famous all over Eastern Ontario, and a most delicate and delicious dish it is, too. The farmers who have cleared enough land to furnish grazing for a flock of sheep have made both ends meet, and put by a little into the bargain. In the last ten years most of these savings have gone into the caravansarais mentioned above, and, though the season is short (June to September) and the prices moderate, some of the hotel-keepers are reported to have done very well for themselves, and certainly these houses are well patronised and always full.

The Muskoka hotels, perched here and there on promontories or hidden in quiet, sheltered bays, are very excellent in their way. They give comfortable accommodation at reasonable prices. There is always plenty of fresh fish, and the milk and butter are extra good. The jam, too, is worthy of mention. It is made from the wild raspberries, strawberries, and blackberries that grow in the woods in such profusion that you can fill pail after pail in a single afternoon. Every farmer’s wife knows how to make good jam, and these Muskoka jams—especially the strawberry—are the best I ever tasted. The Stratton Hotel at Port Carling, kept by an excellent Scotch host, who has wandered over half the world, and came to these solitudes last from an indigo plantation in Ceylon, was especially noted for its delicious jams and its savoury messes of black bass or venison.

But the stayer in hotels knows nothing of the real Muskoka life; generally speaking, he is not even a candidate for admission into the charmed circle. The “islanders” and the hotel visitors are, of course, the regulars and the transients respectively; and even in the genial, unconventional atmosphere of Canada these two classes do not readily amalgamate. Besides which, there has naturally grown up among the Muskoka regulars a select order of aristocrats, whose islands are their castles, and who, consciously or unconsciously, give their tone to the entire community.

The life is, first of all, free and easy. It is an open-air life. The days are made up of picnics on land or water, camping trips into the surrounding wilderness, expeditions into the forest, visits to neighbouring islanders, fishing excursions. The men chop down trees for the immense campfires at night; the girls go out sailing, canoeing, gathering the abundance of wild fruits; or lying with favourite books, guitars, and banjos in hammocks under the trees. Everybody bathes together, and the children learn to swim and dive like fish. Rafts are made of drifting logs, and perilous journeys are made thus in bathing suits from one island to another. The young men practise all sorts of tricks in their canoes: paddling while standing upright, or purposely upsetting and climbing in again after the canoe has been shaken empty—a most difficult feat. All locomotion is of course by water, and every Muskoka boy and girl is a good canoeist (or soon becomes one), from the expert who can shake his canoe empty in deep water and climb in again in fourteen seconds, to the ordinary man who can paddle three girls to Yoho P.O. for the letters in rough weather and not ship a drop.

Whatever the occupations of the day have been, everybody in the house-party meets at night round the campfire. And the campfire is a feature of the Muskoka life. Generally in the morning, soon after breakfast, half-a-dozen men of the party, with boats and axes and ropes, have collected the floating logs or cut down the dead monsters on the mainland, and chopped them into the necessary lengths. Four big logs placed in a square form the foundations, and upon this there is built up a huge, hollow framework, tapering to a height of twelve feet, and filled with brushwood and dead branches. When all the party is assembled, someone lights the pile at the top, and it burns slowly downwards, throwing out a fierce heat and crackling, gigantic flames. Long boards propped up against boulders form comfortable backs for most of the audience, who lie with rugs and cushions, singing songs and telling stories far into the night. Others, two and two, in canoes, float in the circle of light upon the lake. The sound of the guitars and voices travels far across the water, and often attracts visitors from other islands and campfires, who hover about in their canoes and enjoy the fun and music as it were from the gallery, until the party breaks up and they turn their silent craft homewards. A safe rock has to be selected for the conflagration, lest the sparks set on fire the dry wood and destroy the beauty of the island forever. The second growth, after a forest fire, is invariably scrub-oak and small hardwood trees, which afford no shade and are not beautiful in themselves. Thus the value as well as the charm of the islands depends upon their hemlocks and pines, and a true Muskokite is always noted for his extreme caution in lighting and extinguishing his campfires. And, in point of entertainment, the campfire is the theatre of Muskoka, just as the canoe is its hansom and omnibus. Perhaps some of our experiences on one of the smaller islands in Lake Joseph would be of interest to the English reader. We were a party of four. We rented the island from its owner in Montreal for the season May–October for 65 dollars, or £13. That included a shed packed full of ice and a stack of wood for the stove chopped into the right lengths by the settler during the winter. The island, whose pretty Indian name I am not at liberty to disclose, was about two acres in extent. It was circular. It rose to a point in the centre and was covered with pine-trees that crowded to the water’s edge, and carpeted with moss and blueberry bushes. From its little wharf the lake stretched away for four miles to the opposite shore. From the other side you paddled out into a sheltered channel half a mile in width to the mainland. A little wooden shanty, with a wide, covered verandah, stood among the trees on the highest point. The pine boughs brushed its roof; the waves almost lapped the walls. The house held nothing but a stove in the tiny kitchen and a rough wooden table in the front room, which was dining-room, drawing-room, library, and smoking-room combined. Two wee bedrooms opened off it, each with a window, and a narrow staircase led to a sort of loft overhead. The two men of the party slept in a tent outside near the canoes, and the two ladies had the house to themselves at night. They were not always sure they liked this, for the loneliness and remoteness and utter silence of the night on that little island were often weird in the extreme. The ladies washed in one little bay, the men in another. At 7 o’clock every morning the men jumped from the tent into the canoe and paddled two miles over to the farm of a Scotch settler on the mainland, where they obtained milk at 2½d. a quart, bread, eggs, vegetables, and Muskoka lamb at 5d. a pound. He rendered his little bill weekly. By the time we reached the island again coffee and porridge were ready. The ladies did the cooking and the men the washing up. At 11 o’clock we bathed for an hour, and the rest of the day was spent exploring, canoeing, sailing, and writing. At 8 o’clock in the evening we usually paddled down the three miles to Yoho for the mail which the steamer had left on its way north. Then the campfire was lighted, visitors were entertained, and plans were discussed for the morrow. Often we lay out half the night watching the glories of the Northern Lights, listening to the weird laughter of the loons out in the lake, or simply enjoying the beauty of the brilliant stars and the indescribable, calm wonder of the Muskoka night. When the moon was bright we would sometimes steal out in the canoes and pass silently along the shores of the mainland, peering into the blackness of the great forests, or coasting along from island to island past the glimmering ashes of other campfires and the rows of little white tents shining in the moonlight.

Twice a week the provision boats came. With a snort and a whistle they drew up alongside our little wharf, and sold us, from their miniature shop, whatever we wanted to buy. Meat, vegetables, milk, bread, and eggs were their staples, but they also sold sweets, fishing-tackle, cartridges, cheap novels, canoe-paddles, and flannel shirts. Sometimes the deck of the little cabin carried a number of people from the hotels, who, at two shillings a head, chose this way of seeing the lakes and calling without being asked at the different islands.

But nothing comes amiss in Muskoka, for the spirit of reasonableness reigns supreme, and everybody enjoys health and consequent good spirits.

The fishing in these lakes is not so good as it formerly was. There are still bass, whitefish, pickerel, and salmon trout to be caught in plenty, but probably not in such numbers as when the Yo-ho-cu-ca-ba gentlemen first cast rod over the waters. The expeditions into the surrounding wilds are of course legion, and can only be indicated generally. Due west lies Georgian Bay. It is an arm of Lake Huron, studded with thousands of unoccupied islands. For the expert canoeist there is direct water communication with it—from Lake Joseph by way of lovely lakes and secret winding streams, and across stretches of beautiful primeval forest. The distance is about fifty miles, and a halfway point is Blackstone Lake, whose name is derived from the black igneous boulders along the shore, and whose deep green waters are alive with bass up to five pounds and immense maskinonge lying in the mud of the bottom. These latter monsters can be caught by patient trolling, with a pound and a half of lead to carry the spoon deep enough. I have seen their savage heads nailed by other fishermen to the trees along the shores of Blackstone Lake, with fierce, pointed teeth and ugly grin. Their name of devilfish is well earned. And when you first catch them you think they are going to pull you out of the boat.

In another direction, along a route of perpetual wildness and beauty, you can shoot the rapids of the Moon River—if you know how, mark well—and enter the Georgian Bay at a more southerly point. And due north, on the way to Huntsville and Smith’s Falls, before you come to the French River, the home of the wild duck, you will find, after passing through a series of five exquisite lakes, a charming little wooden hotel, kept by an English gentleman named Waterfield, who, at very moderate prices, will serve you up black bass and cucumbers while he discourses to you on literature and music and the latest discoveries of science in the “Old Country.”

In conclusion, it may be mentioned that the name Muskoka belonged originally to an Indian chief of the Chippewas. This region was his own particular hunting ground. He fished these waters and tracked the deer and bear through these dense forests. Even today, the settlers say, his spirit haunts the more remote bays of Lake Joseph and Lake Rosseau, and the solitary hunter may see along shadow fall athwart his tent, when the branches are motionless in the windless night and there are no lost seagulls wandering beneath the moon. A spectral canoe has been seen by more than one backwoodsman in the lonely reaches of the Joseph River; and on wild nights, when the Northern Lights are flashing in the sky and the trees are tossing strangely, it has been said that a tall shadowy form lands silently from a phantom craft, and, passing along an ancient deer-run, disappears into the heart of the forest.

Switzerland

Present Conditions and Future Prospects

Having recently returned from a long sojourn in Switzerland, I have been bombarded with questions as to present conditions there and future prospects. What are prices like ? What about food and heating ? What is the feeling about the war? Will passports soon be available ? The answers to these enquiries are simple : Prices have doubled; food is very scarce and heating inadequate ; German-Switzerland, generally speaking, is still pro-German, while French-Switzerland is still splendidly pro-Ally (if perhaps, more strictly speaking, pro-French); and as for passports, that is a question to be solved by three main considerations: Whether Switzerland can feed an army of tourists, whether the French can supply rolling-stock to convey them there, and whether the British Government intends to encourage money being spent outside this country. There are evidently some optimists among us. A West End bootmaker, famous for his climbing boots, told me last week that he was already in receipt of many orders for Alpine purposes and that most of these orders were marked ‘‘ urgent.”” With the signing of the Armistice many saw our prison doors opening. The idea of travel became a possibility again. Thousands, after an enforced captivity of four years, turned their thoughts once more to lake and mountain and forest, and Switzerland still remains the most accessible, in point of time and money, of all available foreign playgrounds.

The Swiss, too, were optimistic. I use the past tense, for reflection has somewhat reduced the first hopeful estimate which followed the great event of mid-November. The hotels, of course, are hungry for us. The managers, scanning their empty dining-rooms (many a big hotel counts barely a dozen guests at present), return to their desks and calculate prices and profits in the good time coming. And these prices, they frankiy admit, must be high for a year or two at least; the losses, carried by the banks at a high rate of interest for the past four years, have been gigantic ; it is we who are expected to recoup them.

The days of a cheap Switzerland, I believe, are gone for ever, with many another happy prewar condition. One huge mountain hotel, for instance, in a certain place that was famous five years ago for its summer and winter season, a place crowded to overflowing by English visitors at reasonable prices, now has a debt of 600,o00fr. ; it was run this winter (only one wing in use and that wing so chilly that people came to dinner in furs and overcoats) at a heavy further loss. The bedroom radiators, owing to scanty coal of poor quality, were only hot in the top twelve inches, the rest of the pipes being too cold to touch with comfort. The rooms were, therefore, icy. ‘‘ It is a question of pressure,’ explained the resigned manager; ‘‘ with coal of low calories sufficient pressure is unobtainable.’’ He told the truth.

While on this question of heating, the trains, too, may be mentioned. The locomotive tenders are piled with wood, express trains hardly exist, not only is the service reduced to a minimum, but every train is an omnibus train, and from Geneva to Montreux, formerly a matter of three hours or so, is now a whole day’s journey. On Sundays no trains run at all, there is no post, no newspaper, an early milk train being the only Sunday traffic ;

The Armistice, however, brought with it a wave of happy optimism. The story ran from place to place, fathered upon Thos. Cook and Son, probably without a shred of evidence, that a thousand English were coming out at once—mostly invalids, the report took care to add, but still English visitors. Hotel managers certainly received applications and enquiries from would-be travellers, but these enquiries were not followed up; When I left the country in February, my own hotel in Territet, a popular resort of the English for many years, had not increased its list of a baker’s dozen (half of them in bed with influenza) by a single name. With slight modifications and exceptions, this is representative of all other hotels as well, although these remarks refer entirely to what are called ‘* Resorts ’’ which, whether in the valleys or on the mountains, depend upon tourists, transients and travellers generally for their clientéle. The towns, of course, are crowded to overflowing; in Berne, Geneva, Lausanne and Zurich quarters were only to be found with the greatest difficulty. In Berne the German Legation alone employed a staff of 1,500, and the increase of *‘ officials’ from every country, it may be added, while a source of joy to the hotel-keepers, has been a source of anxiety, annoyance and even anger to the Swiss authorities, and a cause of almost daily protest in the country’s Press. But the ‘‘ Resorts,’’ though eager for the English tourist, have now realised that they must still wait patiently for a considerable time before their hopes can be fulfilled, and that a summer season this year is out of the question altogether. They build their hopes, meanwhile, upon next winter.

Information as to actual present conditions may interest numerous readers of COUNTRY LIFE who are lovers of Switzerland, always bearing in mind that certain of these conditions may before very long be favourably modified. To begin at the beginning—I went out on behalf of a London newspa:er to study the question of our prisoners. ‘‘ Yes,” said the Si iss Legation here, ‘‘ we sl.all welcome your visit, but we can only give you permission to stay there two weeks. You mist arrange any extension of your visit with the police in Bern On arrival at one’s destination, the passport is surrendered and a permis de séjour, good for one month in my own case, receiv -d in exchange. This permis takes the form of a carte de contr upon which any and every change of address must be duiy entered. The movements of an individual are thus closcly checked. The Berne police, courteous if dilatory, extend t from month to month indefinitely, provided the individua!'s record remains good, and when a given month is up, the mere fact of having written for a further extension allows one, meanwhile, to remain on in the country. The days of free and happy Switzerland, it will be seen from this, have temporarily gone, and even after Peace is signed it is said to be probable that some modified form of controlling the movements of foreigners may remain in force.

When surrendering the passport, food cards must at once be obtained, for without them no single meal is obtainable. Bread, milk, cheese, fat, butter, grease are all very strictly rationed. Of the first no crumb is delivered without first handing up the corresponding coupon, the ration of 250 grams a day (raised last February to 300 grams) being amply sufficient for average need, the bread itself, however, being most unpalatable. The milk allowance is very small, and that of cheese scarcely worth buying, the latter also being often unobtainable in any case. Butter is in the same category as cheese—it has disappeared almost entirely. And that these staple foods, with which Switzerland formerly overflowed, should have become thus microscopic in quantity is probably the first thing that will strike the hungry visitor. As_ for “fat,” with every dish taken in a restaurant is printed the requisite number of grams deliverable, and if one’s food cards have been left at home by mistake, no food is obtainable at all. Meat, usually of execrable quality, is fairly plentiful. The table d’héte menus in hotels may be imagined without further description. Sugar is equally microscopic, of course, in quantity, but the individual has no sugar card.

With regard to cost of living generally, it may be said that prices in almost every commodity are double what they were, if not more. What we call methylated spirit and the Swiss call alcool a briiler, formerly sold at 7oc. a litre, now sells at 2fr. 50c. a litre. Paper is so expensive that the hotels no longer supply a single sheet in the writing-rooms, but seil packets of a few sheets, two ugly picture postcards showing the hotel, and one or two envelopes, also smothered by hote! designs, for 50c. a packet. Railway tickets are heavily taxed The Hotel Keepers’ Association not long ago agreed upon *** minimum price of a room at ofr. Halls and lounges are kep* gloomy in order to reduce the cost of burning electric light Two francs a day per room is charged extra upon the bill fo: heating, and hot baths, of course, are rare, varying, according to the hotel, from one a week to one in ten days or a fortnight. Even postage has risen in price, the postcard for the interio1 being **7c**. instead of 5c., and a letter 15c. in place of the former 10c.

This list of changes might be much extended, but enough has been said to show that Switzerland is no longer the paradise for short pockets that it used to be. It is, in fact, unrecognisable. And to the general cost of living, for an English visitor drawing his money from England, must also be added his heavy loss upon the exchange. When I left last month a pound sterling was worth 23fr. Switzerland just now is a somewhat dreary and uncomfortable place to live in, and the recent evacuation of the many thousands of prisoners interned there has certainly added to this desolation, both from the natives’ and residents’ points of view. The blue of the jolly potlu and khaki of our Tommy have disappeared; Château d’Oex, Muirren, Interlaken and a dozen mountain villages are empty of them ; kilts no longer swing down the streets of Montreux and Lausanne, and the gaiety of nations is no longer added to by the marvellous French heard for so many months in street and tram and shop. Those of us who in imagination just now yearn for sunny Switzerland would sympathise, after a sojourn there of a week or two, with the longings of the much reduced English colony to get back to foggy, black, rainy and expensive London. By way of compensation there is, certainly, both sun and scenery, but at a cost in cash and discomfort that seems prohibitive rather.

Switzerland in Wartime

There are villages, even within the radius of the London searchlights, where the remark is not uncommonly heard: “One almost forgets the war down here; it’s difficult to believe there is a war!”—the speaker usually some tired worker snatching a few days’ rest, but prevented by limits of time and money from a longer journey. The truth of the remark is relative, of course; it shows how the realisation of war has become habitual. The village has grown accustomed to the lesser evidences of change: the woman driving a milk-cart, girls in breeches working on the fields, scarcity of matches, butter, sugar and so forth in the local shop, even to the boom of antiaircraft guns and the shifting of mysterious lights across the night skies; the incessant thudding of the Flanders artillery calls for no particular comment any longer. Such details cannot shock the nerves as once they did. Minds satiated with revolutions and disasters on a colossal scale are blunted and unresponsive. The morning newspaper once read, the latest Prussian treachery discussed, the length of the Casualty List appreciated, the villagers then go about their duties until the following morning (there is no evening paper) provides the daily excitement, now become as habitual as breakfast. The war is not forgotten; it has grown into the routine of life; its realisation is almost functional. “It is difficult to believe there is a war—down here!”

Sometimes, however, the observation varies. This morning, for instance, an overworked woman, seeking a few days’ change and rest, but a woman still sensitive enough to dream of happier days in the careless Long Ago, mentioned her yearning for the peace of a beflowered valley of the Alps, where the glacier streams gush downwards from eternal snows, where the wind sighs softly through great pine woods, some quiet valley brimmed with crystal sunlight and lying beneath a dome of stainless blue.

“Just one week,” she sighed, “one little week in sight of the Eiger or the Blümlisalp! To see the stars round the crest of the Matterhorn again and hear the echoes of falling water all night long in the peaceful valleys. The dawns, the sunsets, the tinkling of the cowbells, the simple, happy peasants, and the children in the fields! If someone first would hypnotise me to forget … !” It was a natural longing that thousands feel today. Only the hypnotic forgetfulness would have to be very thoroughly managed. The speaker’s days in Bucharest, her share in the Romanian retreat, her experiences before that in Serbia. The hypnotic suggestion would have to be extremely competent, to say the least. And the fair Swiss valleys, haunted of our youth, bathed in clear sunshine and sweetened by fresh mountain winds—these valleys cannot now give the peace and blessing that once they did. The spell is broken and the joy has fled. Even could hypnotism sponge away all memory of the past, the sojourner there just now would find too many reminders of pain and terror and cruelty—ghastly reminders of Prussian frightfulness—to snatch even the most meagre comfort from the scenery, the sunshine and the flowers. Switzerland is no playground any more. Even in the remotest mountain village it would be difficult to say, “One almost forgets there is a war; it is difficult to believe up here!”

For Switzerland, an oasis surrounded on all sides by the great belligerents, offers no escape today from sharp reminders that Europe lies soaked in blood, the valleys have lost their hint of otherworldliness, the mountain hotels their fun and laughter. Winter and summer sports both languish; there are no merry dances, the orchestras are dumb, and many a resort that in peace time was unpleasantly overcrowded now experiences difficulty in keeping open at all. The question of State help is broached plaintively in the daily Press, and more than one popular hotel that filled its great salle à manger easily in 1913 now employs two or three waitresses at most for the handful of guests who occupy one corner only. The men—guides, waiters, porters, sometimes the hotelier himself—are mobilised and doing their service militaire on plain or frontier far away. Labour is as scarce as guests. In every department of her normal life Switzerland has suffered a violent, even a ruinous dislocation; and while the flow of tourist money has practically ceased, the cost of mobilising several divisions and keeping them on a war footing is a grave item in the national economy that must be met out of diminished revenues. Owing to the irregular supply, if not sometimes the actual lack, of fuel—the country’s coal is derived from Germany—more than one industry has been in peril and more than one factory, deprived of the necessary raw material, been shut down. Diminished income, scarcity of labour, of coal and raw material, combined with heavily increased expenses, have been among the great—though not, perhaps, the greatest—disabilities this little, enclosed country has suffered from the war.

There are far sharper reminders of the war, however, than these general trade and economic conditions, and the lady who yearned for the peace and seclusion of her favourite haunted mountain valleys would find them at her elbow everywhere. Swiss hospitality has become proverbial; Switzerland has opened her gates to the wounded and disabled; the grands blessés from the prison camps of Germany fill the streets of her towns and crowd the inns and chalets of even remote upland villages. Khaki from every corner of the British Empire, Australia, New Zealand, Canada, kilts from Scotland, Gurkhas from India, the uniforms of Belgium and of France are met in field and forest, on mountain paths, in rowing boats and steamers on the lakes, in shops and churches and cinemas of the towns. In every train and tram is khaki or the poilus blue, in the village café, at the Kursaal concert, half way up some dizzy height, or in the shady nook of some hotel or villa garden, is seen at every hour of the day that symbol of a fighting world—the military salute. The interiors of clinique and convalescent home, of doctors’ consulting rooms and private nursing quarters, are not, of course, so easily seen, but it needs no imagination to divine that they, too, are full. The crutches, the empty sleeves, the limping legs and shaded eyes are everywhere, and few of their owners, men and officers, but languished two years at least in one of the miserable German prison camps that have stained the name of Germany beyond all cleansing. Switzerland, indeed, is one vast hospital and convalescent home; you cannot pluck a gentian of the higher slopes nor a narcissus of the lush meadows in the valley without a stern reminder that happiness has fled, for a time at any rate, this once-radiant, careless playground we associate with youth and holidays. The sun goes down in wonder behind the lonely heights as before, but goes down in blood; rising beyond the snowfields tipped with gold, it but reminds you of the too familiar “we attacked at dawn.” The mountain winds are fresh and keen as of old; indeed, the forests rustle as sweetly, the cowbells float and tinkle down the air, the falling water echoes; there is no change in Nature; but these are as memories of another day, almost, it seems, of another life. Switzerland is no playground now, but rather a great camp for medical treatment for the heroes of 1914 broken by the war. Her natural beauty serves as painful contrast between the careless happiness of former years and the pain and suffering of today. Sadness casts its shadow on her fairest scenery, and though her loveliness remains as of old, it is poignant now with the tears and sighs of memories that no one can escape.

Yet, equally, there are compensations that no imaginative mind can fail to note; there are striking contrasts. The Red Cross flag that first waved from a Geneva tower now seems to stream from the summit of Mont Blanc itself, covering the entire land with its gracious and beneficent meaning. And, thanks to its protection, these khaki figures, officers and men, heroes all from Le Château, Mons and the rest, take their fill of the sunshine and the mountain wind, enjoying themselves at last, and trying to forget their vile captivity. Strange sights may be seen—is this the Switzerland that we remembered, or some dream with happiness and nightmare oddly mixed? Elderly, bronzed officers, beribboned and beclasped, chasing swallowtails with homemade nets and killing-bottles, and with the zest of eager boyhood! A first-lieutenant, one sleeve empty, casting a rod over a mountain stream for trout, a flying man behind him, limping badly, picking flowers as though he saw them for the first time in his life! Three others, with shaded eyes, or possibly with three sound eyes among the party, climbing trees for birds’ nests as though home for the summer holidays in Kent or Surrey! A Tommy, or a Jock in kilts, struggling with his dictionary in a grocery, a teashop or a railway booking office; while down the sun-drenched street outside a New Zealander and two Australians stump to the bathing-house, hang up their crutches (on the hotel billiard table later in the evening to be used as cue rests) and prove to all and sundry that a man with only one leg can swim as well as a man with two! Laughter, whistling, singing, cracking jokes alternately with “grousing,” this handful of the Old Contemptibles take their Swiss convalescence as cheerily as they took their other fate in the autumn of 1914. Switzerland today is full of the heroes of that first immortal batch. The lady in search of her quiet mountain valley in the shadow of the Eiger or the Blümlisalp would suffer poignant emotions as she crossed the Cantons of Vaud and Valais to reach it. She would meet sharp reminders of the war at every turn. At St. Maurice, too, she might be just in time to see the daily train of évacués from Northern France arrive with its charged cargo of human pain and suffering en route for Evian and distribution thence among the southern departments. The faces at the windows, the children especially, would not contribute to her later peace of mind. She would more probably decide to stay on the St. Maurice platform and help the kindly Swiss in their distribution of welcome material comforts among this daily consignment of sorely afflicted humanity.

Switzerland, indeed, today is changed beyond recognition. Prices are high and food is scarce. Rationing runs its difficult course, as elsewhere in our dislocated world. Trains are reduced, and railway, as also amusement, tickets heavily taxed. Instead of cheese and butter, the rule, strictly enforced, is cheese or butter, while one lump of sugar and one speck of saccharine is the sweetening allowance with thé or café complet. Eggs at 3.50frs. a dozen are a luxury, and cream is unobtainable; it is forbidden even for cakes and pastries in the ubiquitous confiseries. Thursday in every week is an unhappy day for people with sweet tastes, since no sweetened article, not even a cup of chocolate, may be bought at all. And the hotels, to add to their other troubles, are anxious for their supply of fuel. A chilly winter is a probability all have to face. The easygoing, happy Switzerland of former days exists no more. Even a homecoming traveller as he leaves Geneva by the single daily train—he must book his seat days, and his sleeper even weeks, in advance—is searched to see that he carries no foodstuffs out of the country with him. Matches, at any rate, so far, are obtainable in abundance, though not so cigarettes, which it is one of their purposes to light!

It is good to know that many of our own men and officers have come home now from Château d Oex, with its attendant villages of Rougemont and Rossiniéres, from Mürren in the Oberland and other places. The majority of these have not seen England for three years at least. Their evacuation will make room for others to come in from Germany, and no one can be more grateful for this than those whose places in Switzerland will thus be filled. Many may reach this haven just in time. The French exchanges came into effect befere our own, but Champéry in the Valais, Salvan, above the Rhone Valley, on the cold familiar route to Chamonix, and many other mountain villages known to us all as summer and winter resorts in happier days, or as climbing centres, still hum and buzz with busy poilus working in the vines, active with the sawmills whose produce is now taken by their mother country, or occupied by various lesser trades and duties that make the time of waiting less wearisome and long. The ingenuity of these occupations is considerable. There was, in Champéry, one poilu who turned the big nails used for building chalets into paper-knives, with sharp curved blades and delicate tapering points. His sole tool was a common hammer, and the nails sold at the Depot des Internés for 2frs., 3frs. and even 4frs. apiece. Wooden paper-knives, carved to represent soldiers of the Allies, and cleverly coloured, were another very popular employment. A very interesting collection of souvenirs might be made among the ingenious products of interned soldiers at the various villages. The French, in this respect it must be admitted, showed far more resource and ingenuity than the English.

Thcre is another aspect of life in Switzerland today that is less accessible to the public, as well as less free for the journalist to write about. Though the resorts are somewhat descrted, and the villages handed over to interned soldiers chiefly, the towns are crowded, and some of them are booming. Geneva, Bern, Zurich and Lausanne are packed with strange humanity, and rooms not easily to be had. Lucerne is thriving; Lugano very busy. Every nationality is represented, every shade of colour. Germans are ubiquitous, of course, making themselves at home even in French Switzerland, which does not welcome them, and whose newspapers can hardly be pleasant reading for them just now. At Montreux, for instance, they frequent certain hotels, spend money freely, and make themselves at home. The little country has distinguished visitors, some of them undesirably notorious these troubled days. Prince von Buelow showed his fondness for Lucerne, whose climate appealed equally to the famous Erzberger; while King Tino, still hoping probably against hope, nurses that treachery to which alone his soul is faithful in the seclusion of a sumptuous country villa. Near Clarens, in an expensive château, lived for a long time the ex-Khedive of Egypt, fearful, it was currently reported, of assassination, and so rarely, if ever, visible abroad; and von Gerlach, though the papers denied it later, was said to have found a haven of safety, after his audacious activities as a spy in the Vatican, with the monks of a monastery near Coire. Lenin, arch-reactionary, lived quietly in the country until the German interest whisked him across the Fatherland by a special train into Russia, and is now reported back again safely in his neutral home. Strange and various are the people from every country in the world who seek the salubrious climate of Switzerland today. They, with their retinues, doubtless bring money in. Judging, however, by the outspoken comments of the native Press, their absence, even in these hard times, would be preferable to their gold.

Testing His Courage

The Story of a Quaint Device

Julia Mansfield went disconsolately to her ball that night. She was learning, bit by bit, to pay the price that inevitably must be paid by a great heiress, and in the process she was coming to the conclusion that a little money—enough—is better than a lot.

Already, though she was barely twenty-three, cynical lines had traced their bitter story round the corners of her mouth, and in her eyes there occasionally shone a shrewd light which was certainly not there when she first came out. The fact was she was passing through that most swiftly disillusioning of all life’s processes-finding out the opposite sex.

Julia was not, strictly speaking, pretty. She possessed that intelligent sort of face which earnest men adore, but which bores the majority and alarms most of the rest. Hence, as we have said, she was going to the ball without the enthusiasm of the illusioned young girl. There was, however, one man she hoped to see there. Mark Lister had never paid her a compliment or shown the least desire to make love. She had always liked and respected him and, though he made no sign, her intuition persuaded her that it was a mutual liking, and that it was her money that made him keep aloof.

The ball commenced at ten, but it was considerably after midnight when Mark Lister entered the room.

He was an engineer; good-looking, big, strong, but with only his pay to live on. He was just leaving to take up a rather good appointment in India and he had come to confess his love.

He did not intend to ask her to marry him, but yet he wished her at the last to know his secret. It could not possibly hurt her, he argued, and in after life it would always be a source of pleasure to him to think that she knew.

Mark Lister’s mind was simple, direct, and without subtlety or guile, and the possible result of his rather selfish expedient did not cross his mind.

It did not take him long to find the girl he sought, and when, later, the time arrived to claim his dance he came at once to the point without hesitation.

“I have come to this ball simply and solely to see you,” he said. “I have something to say to you. No, do not be alarmed, there’s no question at the end of it. It’s a mere statement of fact. If you will sit out this dance, I’ll tell you.”

He led her to a secluded corner and began at once.

“I’m going to India in three days, but before I go I wanted to tell you-if I may- I—that I’ve been in love with you ever since I saw you first at your coming-out ball in this very house three years ago. I tell you this because I don’t quite know why—I fear my reason’s very selfish—because it will always be such a pleasure to me to feel that you know. It can do you no harm. I wanted you to know it. There, that’s all-and- well, that’s the longest speech I ever made in my life!”

He half rose to go, as the music was beginning again, but she held out a hand and stopped him.

“Wait,” she said peremptorily, “I’ll give you this dance too. I am interested in your declaration. It is unusual. You put no question at the end of it—that customary question I’m tired of hearing.”

“No; I think you are fitted for a better-a bigger career than I could hope to give you. Besides, I love my profession, and could not allow myself to think further than this : that I love you, and I want you to know it.”

“Evidently, we both unusual people,” she laughed, but in a tone that made his leap Now, suppose I put a question to you, will you answer it truly?”

“Yes.”

“Do you want to marry me?”

“Yes.”

“Would you have asked me if I were poor?”

“Yes.”

There was a long pause. He felt the girl drawing him with terrific force, but he made no sign. The fragrance of her hair and breath rose to his brain. Again he made a move, and again she stopped him with her hand.

“Mr. Lister,” she said—and the personality of the girl robbed the words of any reproach and unmaidenliness—” you have told me the the without humiliating me. Now, I’ll tell you something, too. You have won my love. I love you, and have loved you for a long time.”

“You really mean that ?” he cried.

“ You want to marry me—I want to marry you,” she continued quietly. “There’s only one thing I want you first to prove to -your courage. No, your · physical courage; that’s a mere matter of nerves and imagination. I mean your moral courage, which is matter of character.”

“How?”

“Go and ask my aunt for my hand in marriage. You know, she has the disposal of me. I am her ward.”

She watched his face, but he did not flinch. Her aunt had the reputation of being a veritable dragon, a woman to dread, a woman with a bitter and merciless tongue, a sayer of brutal things—usually true!

“All right, I’ll go,” he said ” without hesitation. ” Only, she’s never seen me, or heard of me.” ·

“That makes difference. This is my test. Do you accept it?” He bowed his head.

Then go to-morrow at four o’clock. I shall tell her another suitor is coming to ask for me. She hates the very name of suitor. It’s like a red rag to a bull.”

This was her parting shot. Mark Lister handed her over to Lord de Pennylesse to go down to supper, and left the ball room.

Next day at the appointed hour he presented himself at the door of the great mansion in Grosvenor Square, but before going up to the dragon’s den he asked to see Miss Mansfield alone.

“Miss Mansfield is out, sir, and will not return till evening,” was the footman’s reply to his question, and with rather a sinking heart he then sent up his card to aunt, Lady Hester. In due course he truth shown into a severe little upstairs drawing-room where, at once as he entered the room, he saw the figure of the much-dreaded old lady seated in an arm-chair by the fire. She looked very prim and severe, and the high fashion of wearing her hair, and the dark spectacles, certainly did not tend to soften the general aspect of severity with which she acidly welcomed him. Her attitude at once seemed to put him in the wrong. She motioned him to a chair, and without delay, in a thin, bored voice, plunged into her subject. Evidently her intention was to conclude the interview as soon as possible and get back to her novel. She sat up stiffly, facing him, yet never once actually taking the trouble to to look at him; her back was to the light.

“I believe you wish to marry my niece, Mr.-er—”

“Lister,” he supplied. Her voice was like the cracking of an icicle just before it drops.

“Mr. Lister,” she went on.” Well, sir, as she is also my ward, it is, of course, my duty to ask you if you are in a position to support her—”

“I am an engineer, with a salary of £400 and excellent prospects.”

“Please don’t interrupt,” she went on testily. “I was about to say, if you can support her in the way she has been accustomed to ?”

“No; I certainly cannot at present give her the luxury she has been accustomed to,” he answered frankly, but she can supply all that unnecessary sort of thing with her own money.”

Her own money, my dear sir! Are you aware that she has no money, practically speaking, of her own? Her fortune is entirely at my disposal, and if she marries a man of whom I disapprove she won’t have a penny.”

“This is news to me, and very good news,” he answered quite calmly, “ for if she loves me really she will not mind what—”

“Fiddlesticks, fiddlesticks!” ejaculated the old lady, kicking her footstool viciously. “You don’t know what you’re talking about, young man. Are you selfish enough to tempt the girl to lose her fortune? Don’t you know that money is one’s only real friend in this world and that—“

Mark Lister had a good deal of self- control, but he interrupted here.

“Lady Hester,” he said, quietly but firmly, “I have come here to make a formal demand for your ward’s hand. If you disapprove of me as her husband, and will kindly tell me so plainly, I shall then feel free ask her if she will have me without your consent. If she prefers her fortune I shall know how to value her love. But not for one minute do I believe that she loves her wretched money better than me.

“That’s delightfully plain talk, Mr. Lister,” snapped the old lady, “and I’ll meet you on equal terms. I refuse my consent. There! Now you can write and tell her so. If she she shan’t have penny except the £100 a year she has in her own right.”

“I’m delighted with your decision,” he said with some heat. “If she won’t marry me on what I’ve got, I don’t want her.”

” You’ll find a table with writing paper behind you,” wheezed the old lady, burying herself in her book without even looking up to see what he was doing.

Mark Lister turned to the table and began a letter. He did not hesitate for a minute. He believed the girl loved him. The decision was for her to make.

It was not that he valued himself so highly, but that he felt the right thing for him to do was to give her the chance. He would play the game. At least it would prove that he wanted herself, not her money.

He was half-way through his epistle when he suddenly felt a hand clapped over both his eyes. Good heavens! What was the old cat up to now? He struggled an instant to free himself, but the fingers only tightened their grasp. Then he seized the wrist to force it away, and half rose in his chair as he did so. Surely that tender little hand he felt so soft and yielding beneath his own was not that of the severe, prim, bony old maid he had been just arguing with ! It seemed incredible. He wrenched himself free, and turned upon his blindfolder.

Julia Mansfield stood before him, her face For reply he kissed her again. crimson with blushes, her eyes sparkling with happiness. Upon the floor at her feet lay a bundle of false hair, a pair of blue spectacles, a shawl, and other paraphernalia. Lady Hester’s armchair was empty; her book lay upon the floor. The disguise had been perfect and complete.

“Mark!” she cried. “Then you do love me for myself. Oh, if you knew the number of men that have failed to pass that test! I never really doubted you, but it was sweet to hear it from your own lips—and in such a temper, too! Of course, my fortune is my own, and, what’s more to the point, you are, too!

“You-little-minx-you!” he cried, kissing her between each word. “You don’t deserve to have a husband at all.”

“Am I forgiven?”

For reply he kissed her again.

“What about your aunt?” he asked presently.

“I am my aunt,” replied Julia, “and a very convenient relative I have always found myself. But this is the last of her. I must at once announce that Lady Hester is travelling on the Continent for an indefinite period.”

The Attic

The forest-girdled village upon the Jura slopes slept soundly, although it was not yet many minutes after ten o’clock. The clang of the couvre-feu had indeed just ceased, its notes swept far into the woods by a wind that shook the mountains.

This wind now rushed down the deserted street. It howled about the old rambling building called La Citadelle, whose roof towered gaunt and humped above the smaller houses—Château left unfinished long ago by Lord Wemyss, the exiled Jacobite. The families who occupied the various apartments listened to the storm and felt the building tremble. ‘It’s the mountain wind. It will bring the snow,’ the mother said, without looking up from her knitting. ‘And how sad it sounds.’ But it was not the wind that brought sadness as we sat round the open fire of peat. It was the wind of memories. The lamplight slanted along the narrow room towards the table where breakfast things lay ready for the morning. The double windows were fastened. At the far end stood a door ajar, and on the other side of it the two elder children lay asleep in the big bed. But beside the window was a smaller unused bed, that had been empty now a year. And to-night was the anniversary....

And so the wind brought sadness and long thoughts. The little chap that used to lie there was already twelve months gone, far, far beyond the Hole where the Winds came from, as he called it; yet it seemed only yesterday that I went to tell him a tuck-up story, to stroke Riquette, the old motherly cat that cuddled against his back and laid a paw beside his pillow like a human being, and to hear his funny little earnest whisper say, ‘Oncle, tu sais, j’ai prié pour Petavel.’ For La Citadelle had its unhappy ghost—of Petavel, the usurer, who had hanged himself in the attic a century gone by, and was known to walk its dreary corridors in search of peace—and this wise Irish mother, calming the boys’ fears with wisdom, had told him, ‘If you pray for Petavel, you’ll save his soul and make him happy, and he’ll only love you.’ And, thereafter, this little imaginative boy had done so every night.

With a passionate seriousness he did it. He had wonderful, delicate ways like that. In all our hearts he made his fairy nests of wonder. In my own, I know, he lay closer than any joy imaginable, with his big blue eyes, his queer soft questionings, and his splendid child’s unselfishness—a sun-kissed flower of innocence that, had he lived, might have sweetened half a world.

‘Let’s put more peat on,’ the mother said, as a handful of rain like stones came flinging against the windows; ‘that must be hail.’ And she went on tiptoe to the inner room. ‘They’re sleeping like two puddings,’ she whispered, coming presently back.

But it struck me she had taken longer than to notice merely that; and her face wore an odd expression that made me uncomfortable. I thought she was somehow just about to laugh or cry. By the table a second she hesitated. I caught the flash of indecision as it passed. ‘Pan,’ she said suddenly—it was a nickname, stolen from my tuck-up stories, he had given me—‘I wonder how Riquette got in.’ She looked hard at me. ‘It wasn’t you, was it?’ For we never let her come at night since he had gone. It was too poignant.

The beastie always went cuddling and nestling into that empty bed. But this time it was not my doing, and I offered plausible explanations. ‘But— she’s on the bed. Pan, would you be so kind— ‘ She left the sentence unfinished, but I easily understood, for a lump had somehow risen in my own throat too, and I remembered now that she had come out from the inner room so quickly— with a kind of hurried rush almost. I put ‘mère Riquette’ out into the corridor. A lamp stood on the chair outside the door of another occupant further down, and I urged her gently towards it.

She turned and looked at me—straight up into my face; but, instead of going down as I suggested, she went slowly in the opposite direction. She stepped softly towards a door in the wall that led up broken stairs into the attics. There she sat down and waited. And so I left her, and came back hastily to the peat fire and companionship. The wind rushed in behind me and slammed the door.

And we talked then somewhat busily of cheerful things; of the children’s future, the excellence of the cheap Swiss schools, of Christmas presents, skiing, snow, tobogganing. I led the talk away from mournfulness; and when these subjects were exhausted I told stories of my own adventures in distant parts of the world. But ‘mother’ listened the whole time—not to me. Her thoughts were all elsewhere. And her air of intently, secretly listening, bordered, I felt, upon the uncanny. For she often stopped her knitting and sat with her eyes fixed upon the air before her; she stared blankly at the wall, her head slightly on one side, her figure tense, attention strained— elsewhere. Or, when my talk positively demanded it, her nod was oddly mechanical and her eyes looked through and past me. The wind continued very loud and roaring; but the fire glowed, the room was warm and cosy.

Yet she shivered, and when I drew attention to it, her reply, ‘I do feel cold, but I didn’t know I shivered,’ was given as though she spoke across the air to some one else. But what impressed me even more uncomfortably were her repeated questions about Riquette. When a pause in my tales permitted, she would look up with ‘I wonder where Riquette went?’ or, thinking of the inclement night, ‘I hope mère Riquette’s not out of doors. Perhaps Madame Favre has taken her in?’ I offered to go and see. Indeed I was already halfway across the room when there came the heavy bang at the door that rooted me to the ground where I stood.

It was not wind. It was something alive that made it rattle. There was a second blow. A thud on the corridor boards followed, and then a high, odd voice that at first was as human as the cry of a child.

It is undeniable that we both started, and for myself I can answer truthfully that a chill ran down my spine; but what frightened me more than the sudden noise and the eerie cry was the way ‘mother’ supplied the immediate explanation.

For behind the words ‘It’s only Riquette; she sometimes springs at the door like that; perhaps we’d better let her in,’ was a certain touch of uncanny quiet that made me feel she had known the cat would come, and knew also why she came.

One cannot explain such impressions further.

They leave their vital touch, then go their way.

Into the little room, however, in that moment there came between us this uncomfortable sense that the night held other purposes than our own— and that my companion was aware of them. There was something going on far, far removed from the routine of life as we were accustomed to it.

Moreover, our usual routine was the eddy, while this was the main stream. It felt big, I mean.

And so it was that the entrance of the familiar, friendly creature brought this thing both itself and ‘mother’ knew, but whereof I as yet was ignorant. I held the door wide. The draught rushed through behind her, and sent a shower of sparks about the fireplace. The lamp flickered and gave a little gulp.

And Riquette marched slowly past, with all the impressive dignity of her kind, towards the other door that stood ajar. Turning the corner like a shadow, she disappeared into the room where the two children slept. We heard the soft thud with which she leaped upon the bed. Then, in a lull of the wind, she came back again and sat on the oilcloth, staring into mother’s’ face. She mewed and put a paw out, drawing the black dress softly with half-opened claws. And it was all so horribly suggestive and pathetic, it revived such poignant memories, that I got up impulsively—I think I had actually said the words, ‘We’d better put her out, mother, after all’—when my companion rose to her feet and forestalled me. She said another thing instead. It took my breath away to hear it. ‘She wants us to go with her. Pan, will you come too?’ The surprise on my face must have asked the question, for I do not remember saying anything.

‘To the attic,’ she said quietly.

She stood there by the table, a tall, grave figure dressed in black, and her face above the lampshade caught the full glare of light. Its expression positively stiffened me. She seemed so secure in her singular purpose. And her familiar appearance had so oddly given place to something wholly strange to me. She looked like another person— almost with the unwelcome transformation of the sleep-walker about her. Cold came over me as I watched her, for I remembered suddenly her Irish second-sight, her story years ago of meeting a figure on the attic stairs, the figure of Petavel. And the idea of this motherly, sedate, and wholesome woman, absorbed day and night in prosaic domestic duties, and yet ‘seeing’ things, touched the incongruous almost to the point of alarm. It was so distressingly convincing.

Yet she knew quite well that I would come.

Indeed, following the excited animal, she was already by the door, and a moment later, still without answering or protesting, I was with them in the draughty corridor. There was something inevitable in her manner that made it impossible to refuse. She took the lamp from its nail on the wall, and following our four-footed guide, who ran with obvious pleasure just in front, she opened the door into the courtyard. The wind nearly put the lamp out, but a minute later we were safe inside the passage that led up flights of creaky wooden stairs towards the world of tenantless attics overhead.

And I shall never forget the way the excited Riquette first stood up and put her paws upon the various doors, trotted ahead, turned back to watch us coming, and then finally sat down and waited on the threshold of the empty, raftered space that occupied the entire length of the building underneath the roof. For her manner was more that of an intelligent dog than of a cat, and sometimes more like that of a human mind than either.

We had come up without a single word. The howling of the wind as we rose higher was like the roar of artillery. There were many broken stairs, and the narrow way was full of twists and turnings. It was a dreadful journey. I felt eyes watching us from all the yawning spaces of the darkness, and the noise of the storm smothered footsteps everywhere. Troops of shadows kept us company.

But it was on the threshold of this big, chief attic, when ‘mother’ stopped abruptly to put down the lamp, that real feat took hold of me. For Riquette marched steadily forward into the middle of the dusty flooring, picking her way among the fallen tiles and mortar, as though she went towards— some one. She purred loudly and uttered little cries of excited pleasure. Her tail went up into the air, and she lowered her head with the unmistakable intention of being stroked.

Her lips opened and shut. Her green eyes smiled. She was being stroked.

It was an unforgettable performance. I would rather have witnessed an execution or a murder than watch that mysterious creature twist and turn about in the way she did. Her magnified shadow was as large as a pony on the floor and rafters. I wanted to hide the whole thing by extinguishing the lamp. For, even before the mysterious action began, I experienced the sudden rush of conviction that others besides ourselves were in this attic—and standing very close to us indeed.

And, although there was ice in my blood, there was also a strange swelling of the heart that only love and tenderness could bring.

But, whatever it was, my human companion, still silent, knew and understood. She saw. And her soft whisper that ran with the wind among the rafters, ‘Il a prié pour Petavel et le bon Dieu l’a entendu,’ did not amaze me one quarter as much as the expression I then caught upon her radiant face. Tears ran down the cheeks, but they were tears of happiness. Her whole figure seemed lit up.

She opened her arms—picture of great Motherhood, proud, blessed, and tender beyond words. I thought she was going to fall, for she took quick steps forward; but when I moved to catch her, she drew me aside instead with a sudden gesture that brought fear back in the place of wonder.

‘Let them pass,’ she whispered grandly. ‘Pan, don’t you see.... He’s leading him into peace and safety ... by the hand!’ And her joy seemed to kill the shadows and fill the entire attic with white light. Then, almost simultaneously with her words, she swayed. I was in time to catch her, but as I did so, across the very spot where we had just been standing—two figures, I swear, went past us like a flood of light.

There was a moment next of such confusion that I did not see what happened to Riquette, for the sight of my companion kneeling on the dusty boards and praying with a curious sort of passionate happiness, while tears pressed between her covering fingers—the strange wonder of this made me utterly oblivious to minor details. ...

We were sitting round the peat fire again, and ‘mother’ was saying to me in the gentlest, tenderest whisper I ever heard from human lips —‘Pan, I think perhaps that’s why God took him....’

And when a little later we went in to make Riquette cosy in the empty bed, ever since kept sacred to her use, the mournfulness had lifted; and in the place of resignation was proud peace and joy that knew no longer sad or selfish questionings.

The Barmecide Feast

He realised that he was asleep sure sign that he was just about to wake: and something whispered that it was very early, and that it would be far better if he could prevent waking. For a long time he made a half-hearted effort, craving a continuation of the deli- cious state of unconsciousness. But it lay beyond his powers. He moved : he turned over in bed, vet still keeping his eyes tightly shut. "I’m waking,” he whispered to himself. "What a bore!" The springs in his eyelids were released. The room, he saw, was tinged with that thin, clear light which means very early morning, and he gave up the struggle. ‘‘ Hang this early waking! I shall be tired all day now!” And he noticed with disgust the candle and pillow-book, left hours ago in the comforting darkness. He lay back, staring angrily at the white ceiling. But nothing banishes sleep so effectively as anger. Jones, disgruntled and annoyed, sat up in bed at two o’clock in the morning, in the little Sussex cottage where he was spending the week-end with a married cousin of slight acquaintance, and remembered next that even in his sleep there was something that had bothered him. His dreams, now forgotten, had been anxious, troubled, searching. What was it ? His mind sent scurrying messengers. Memory became active. He was painfully wide awake now. Ah! He had found it. The night before—it seemed so long ago, so far away—a plan had been arranged: a bicycling trip across the Downs, himself as leader; the children had been sent early to bed on purpose, and he had fallen asleep, thinking hard about the route, yet uncertain of It. He dared not fail, for the children thought him marvellous. And the search had been continued in his dreams, endlessly, in vain. He had failed utterly; the children would never believe in him again. There was still a sinking sensation at his heart, a kind of gnawing that craved for satisfaction. And then, suddenly, he realised the truth: that he was hungry! Accustomed to late dinners in London, the light country supper in the cottage at seven o’clock had damaged interior routine, and his interior had wakened him at 2 a.m. to inform him of the fact. Jones felt very empty indeed.

The next minute he stood in the middle of the room, his mind holding but a single thought—Larder. His interior and the cottage larder were two points in space, and he sought the straight line between them. Behind this flickered lighter pictures, which ex- plained themselves without effort on his part, as he remembered the wife’s apology that the butcher in this isolated region often failed them, that F.H.B. (family hold back) had been mentioned at the table, and that his two helpings of bread-and-butter pudding, so stuffing at the moment, could not possibly be expected to satisfy for long. But it was the geographical situation of the larder, what he might find there, and how awkward it would be if he were discovered on the prowl—it was this that occupied his thought as, in slippers and pyjamas, he cautiously opened his door and peered forth into the silent emptiness of the outside world. His one terror was that he might see, or be seen by, his cousin’s wife—his hostess. Why, exactly, he could not explain quite; but it would reflect on her housekeeping, for one thing; she would be so full of apologies, for another: and, for a third, she would load him with more than he wanted. She might even watch him eat, or catch him disappear- ing into his room with a plateful of assorted nourishment stolen from her larder. He felt guilty and ashamed the moment he opened his bedroom door and stole softly on tiptoe down the narrow corridor, that creaked beneath his tread as though each separate board was loose. He felt so light and empty that this surprised him; his weight, though small, seemed centred in his feet. The thick matting on the stairs was a great relief, and he crept safely past his hostess’ door, astonished at the extraordinary silence every- where. Husband and wife, both of heavy build, were born snorers, he would have said, vet no faintest sound was audible, and he pic- tured them now, sitting up in bed, disturbed by the creaking that he made—and listening. Distributing his weight carefully with one hand on the banisters and another on the wall, he next got past the maid’s room, and the room where the children slept with the diminutive watch-dog, and successfully reached the ground floor, where the bricks of the hall struck chill through his thin Egyptian slippers. Those pointed yellow slippers, from a Cairo bazaar, looked painfully ludicrous, he realised, and the colour of his pyjamas was in shouting con trast. The whole house watched him with a grin. Everywhere was a silence of tombs and catacombs Only a rustling of early wind against the black front door was audible The dining-room and draw Ing-room stared suspiciously at his back; but already a_ certain carelessness was in him, for no one slept on this floor, and he could move with greater freedom. Would the larder doo: be locked ? What would he find there 2? Should he take the food upstairs with him or—horrors! Was that whispering-? The long, dark passage gaped before him, and at the further end, behind a door it seemed, came a faint sound of voices, subdued and cautious. There was a stealthy step. A latch rattled. He shrank against the wall, standing stock still. In the semi-gloom he might have been hidden but for those glaring yellow slippers, a size too large for him, and for the striped pyjamas, looking like a convict’s dress He waited, breathing only through his nose—trying, indeed. not to breathe at all.

Yes; the steps and voices were unmistakable No thought of ghosts or burglars had yet entered his mind, and a voice, if any should have come from overhead: ‘‘ Who’s there ?”’ o1 ll fire unless you come out and show yourself" but whispers and steps so close to him were an unexpected shock. For a moment he hardly knew what was best to do. He forgot his hunger alto gether, and braced himself for action. It was quite plain that strangers had broken into the cottage, attracted by its extreme: loneliness, and were at this very moment in larder or kitchen at the end of the passage, arranging their booty, perhaps just making ready to depart. And he remembered then that he had smelt flowers and grass and earth as he came down the staircase sign that a door or window had been opened below—and that the air in the hall was uncommonly fresh and sweet. "There are two of them," Jones reflected, in this awkward moment of greatness which had been thrust upon him, “ and I have no weapon, not even a poker !”’

A door halfway down the passage opened softly, so close that the gush of warmer air reached his nostrils, and he knew it was the kitchen; while a voice, whispering to his companion, was just audible: "There’s no one. It’s all right. We might go upstairs now if you're The stealthy closing of the door smothered the rest of the sentence, but not before he had caught another sentence spoken simultaneously by the companion. Jones heard both. And the other was a man’s voice, gruff and short and cautious : ‘‘ What did you do with the knife? You had it last . . .’ And, hearing it, Jones, in his unsheltering pyjamas, felt so helpless that his modicum of courage failed him. Hungry cold and weaponless, taken utterly by surprise, he felt in no condition to meet two desperate tramps at close quarters, one of them with a knife. He hurriedly, wildly, reviewed a dozen possibilities. It was a moment for clear, quick thinking and decisive action Shouting was useless: there were no passers-by or policemen in the lonely country lane outside. Had there been a single burglaa only he might have faced him, rousing the household at the same time by cries for help. But against two he could do nothing And cold steel always filled him with peculiar terror. His mind flashed the only possible course—to dart upstairs and waken his cousin. His cousin was sure to have a pistol in his bedroom And Jones was in the very act of turning to put his plan in execution when the door of the kitchen opened wide again. He had been too slow, too long reflecting. He was fairly caught. Two figures, he saw, were already in the passage. They moved quic kly and on tip-toe. They were within three feet of him. He knew a sharp moment of hysterical terror first before his courage—at heart he was no coward—came to help him.

"Arthur!" he yelled, at the top of his voice. "Arthur! There are burglars in the house. Quick! With the pistol—!" and flung himself at the same moment with violence against the still advancing figures. And to protect his body from the point of entering steel, he caught at the first thing handy he could find the thick door-mat on which he stood. Holding it before him like a shield, still shouting for help as he charged, Jones hurled himself with reckless onslaught against—his hostess and het husband.

All three collapsed against the wall with a crash, then sprawled through the open door into the kitchen The disentanglement was at first in silence, for the shock of bewildered astonishment was too great for speech The breathless chorus of explanation, apology, unanswered questions and questionable answers cam¢ next, pell-mell.

"I thought—I was sure—I heard a noise," prevaricated Jones "and came down to see." The elucidation, all three, clothed not for daylight, standing upon the kitchen floor, lasted some time, for Jones stuck to his story so manfully that the burden of explanation was transferred to his host and host It was resourceful, but not strictly honest, on his part For the life of him, however, he could not find it in his heart to admit the truth.

Only a portion of the truth he told “Of course, I thought you were burglar ‘he repeated I heard steps and voices, and something about a knife when you opened the door first to go upstairs—""

He looked his cousin straight in the ey as a brave man should it wa left to his hostess to confess het soul and her husband's, too They looked so sheepish, standing ther in the morning light without an adequate reason for being out of their bedroom together at such an hou Jones had managed the situation admirably for himself—in one way.

"The fact is, Mr. Jones," she said, then paused a moment; we both woke up—"

"Yes,”’ he helped her. She said it so awkwardly, almost guiltily, that he wondered what was coming.

"Feeling hungry," she concluded, with a little, shame-faced laugh, “dreadfully hungry—"

"And stole down to get something to eat," put in her husband, boldly filling in the pause.

"I'm frightfully sorry—so ashamed—we disturbed your sleep like this," she added, and then went softly upstairs again to see if the children had slept safely through the noise of battle.

Jones waited a little longer while his cousin, laughing ovet the adventure, put away the delicious eatables. But, somehow or other, he had not the courage to ask a single crumb. There was loaf and butter on the kitchen table, cake as well, but he did not touch them.

He put away the saw-toothed bread knife in the drawer his cousin opened, then followed him upstairs to bed again. But not to sleep. He ate nothing till nine o’clock, when he came down to breakfast, weary and unrefreshed, obliged to tell his story ul over again with convincing detail for the children’s benefit, joining in the laugh against himself, while he devoured the biggest breakfast of his life.

The Boy Messenger

A Christmas Fantasy

It was the afternoon of Christmas Eve.

Partly by train, partly on foot, they had come to a charming village, not much more than a dosen miles from London Bridge, and were sitting at tea looking out upon the garden of the inn, The dusk, lke a thin veil, gathered silently’ about them, and a curtain of wintry mist, half mo jure from the near woodlands, half smoke from the village, hung over the tum bled cottage roofs and shrouded the crests of the elm trees that circled the green.

A few children played near the well, a line of white geese straggled over from the pond, aad a typical village dog strayed dangerously near the hoofs of a typical village donkey that was trying its best to nibble grass where grass there was none. For the rest, the hamlet seemed deserted, the street peopled by shadows only,’ and the dishevelled yew-tree in the church~ yard spread vaguely through the gloom tll it embraced the church and most of the gravestones into the com- pass of its aged arms.

They were an unimaginative party. It is doubtful if any one of them pos- sessed sufficient insight to appreciate the feelings of an untipped waiter—surely the least of tests—and yet, be- fore the eyes of three of them, two girls and a man, this thing plainly happened. True, their accounts varied curiously when ‘they came. later to compare notes; but then accounts of the simplest occurrence—say, a rabbit running across a read—will vary amaz- ingly when half a dozen persons who saw it rum come to relate their im- pressions, So that proves nothing; the important thing is that something happened, and the observers started even. The rest remains to be told.

They were waiting for the arrival of another friend, who was to bicycle over and meet them at the inn, and then return for the Christmas Eve pee when they realised that the cold kad grown suddenly much greater, and one of them—it was the younger girl—made the suggestion that they should go part of the way to meet him. The proposal was welcomed, ‘and instantly acted upon, and the man and the two girls were up and away in a twinkling, leaving the others behind to nurse the tea against their speedy return.

“The moment we hear the bicycle bell we’ll make tea,” they shouted from the ina porch, a» the three forms scattered into the darkness, the voices and footsteps making an unusual clam our in the peaceful little hamlet.

The road, winding like a white stream, and slippery with occasional ice, ran downhill out of the nest of cottages, and the trio followed its course headlong through the gloom, regardless of ruts or loose stones. A couple of villagers, walking briskly by, turned their heads to stare; a dog made a sudden run, barking shrilly @ cat shot silently across the road im front of them; and then, quite sud- denly the village was lett’ behind and the broad highway dwindled into a country lane. “As they ram, the hedge- rows flew past like palings with a level top, and the frosty evening ait, keen Sa re ene ead leaves, stung their checks si ly and whistled in their ears.”

They bad gone perhaps half a mile in this way, still urging the pace downhill, “and they were running abreast along a clear stretch wit nothing to obstruct, so that all had the Same point of view, when suddenly—sis where the accounts first to vary—they realised that some- stood immediately in the road before them, som that brought them all up’ instinctively with a dead halt.

How they managed it, going at that pace downhill, is hard to understand—some things apparently possess the curious power compelling a stop—for they came w a full halt as com- pletely as though they had charged an am iron barrier breast-high across the road. Panting and speech- they drew up in line as by com- moo instinct—drew up in presence of a fourth.

So tar at least, they were all agreed—that it was a fourth.

Outlined against the white road where a moment before had been empty dusk, of indehnute in the sia the lights, stock still and bang oo oremce ot thee path—the slang alone. describes the uncompromising attitude of the thing—stood this fourth ute, faci them with a deliberate calmness of survey that seemed a little than insolence, and only a little Jess than menace. ‘ Another second and ther headlong rush would have vent them ploughing over it as am ocean liner ploughs over a fishing smack in the mght, Moreover, so sudden Was the appearance, and so abrupt the halt, that for more than a whole minute they. merely stood in silence facing it, and staring bac with no thought of doing anything. To each of them the idea came that WAS Not possible to get past it, that there was no available space. Though actually diminutive, it seemed to fill the entire road just as a mail cart might have done. And, quite apart from this singular dex ept.on of sight, each member confessed afterwards io an uncommon emotion, which warned them that to force a way past was somehow not exactly the right, oF proper, or safe thing to do.

So at first they stued and stared rather helplessly—ull at jength theu Startled vision tocussed itself better and the man of the party, Hading bis renses, eBpressed the relieved convic- tion of them all with a loud exclama tion;—

“Why I declare, it’s only a boy after all!” he cred, with a laugh.

Yet the words, as soon as uttered, had a false ring about them, for there was that about the figure of of this little boy~this diminutive person dressed in clothes of oe mreen, oddly cut, with the white face and large blue eyes so wide apart in it—there was that about him which made it not difficult to imagine that, if he was something less than a man, he was at the same time something more than a boy. His self- possession was perfect The manner in which he dominated the entire road, gazing up so quietly and finedly at them—peering it really was—produced an effect privileged importance that was not calculated according to his mere size at any rate. Aided, perhaps. by the twilight and the background o! dark woods, he certainly managed to convey an impression, strangely in- sistent, of being other than he was—other, at least, than these three saw him.

And, beyond question, each one saw him differently—at first, The picture varied astonishingly. For the elder girl thought it was a “woman or a shadow,’’ and her sister said it looked i:ke an animal on its hind legs, paus- ing to start in its flight across the road—a hare, for instance, magnified hugely the dusk—while the man could have sworn, he declared, that at first he saw several figures, a whole line of them, indeed, which had then suddenly telescoped down into the single outline of this diminutive boy.

And the three accounts seem very suggestive of the curiously confusin, effect produced upon their sense 0! sight trom the very beginning.

For a time no one said a word, and up the spines of. all three ran chills ot various degrees. For the place had turned suddenly lonely; no habitation was in sight; dark woods lay close at hand, with mist creeping everywhere over the sombre landscape; and, im- mediately in front of them, this imp- thine with the glowing eyes and the confident manner, barring their way. It was eerie; though what there contd be about a twilight country lane and an inquisitive little boy to make it so, no one of them could understand,

And then, while a stray. breeze brought the dead leaves whirl-ng about their feet in a little rustling eddy,.the embarrassing silence was broken the fourth itself, who in a thin, p’pin voice, like wind blowing through small reeds, ejaculated a sound that all heard differently.

“Surely it was my name that he called,’ was the thought in the mind of each.

This, however, they discovered afterwards when comparing notes, and discussing the singular affair from every possible point of view; for at the actual moment the man of the party, remembering the character of the friend they were come to meet, and his love of practical joking, thought to see his hand in the behaviour of the youngster, and cried again with a laugh :—

“But it’s some elaborate trick of tlarry’s! He has sent the boy ahead to meet us, He is not far off himself at this very moment, and this is his messenger boy i

But was it really a boy! Did it cast a shadow like the rest of them under the gathering stars? Was it wnaccom- panied truly, or were those merely shapes of mist that rose and melted so mysteriously into one another beside the hedge yonder? And how was it so vividly impressed upon the minds of all that the boy stood there with a definite purpose, a deliberate mission, and sought to spell some message to their brains? For, afterwards, it came out clearly, that it was this conception of the messenger—of someone come to tell something—that had impressed and perplexed the unimaginative three far more than the mere differences of sight and hearing.

“Let’s go back,” whispered—the younger girl, ‘He frightens me.”

It was the one who had most reason to wish for the arrival of the expected friend, and her vaice gave utterance to a secret emotion that was beginnin to stir in them all—an emotion of chi presentiment and fear. The imp, how- ever, was far too fascinating tor this course to recommend itself just then,

and the others soon found their voices

and began to ply the little fellow with questions. First of all they asked him who he was and where he lived; and without speaking, he pointed in a vague way, waving his hand generally to include sky and fields as though it were impossible more particularly to give his name or describe the place where he dwelt.

“He doesn’t know who he is, or where he hives,’’ cried the girl, who wanted the comforting lights of the inn, and the comfortable presence of the one they awaited. ‘He’s a goblin—of course, but a very nice goblin,” she added quickly with an odd little forced laugh. The boy had turned his eyes upon her face. They seemed such

old, old eyes, she declared afterwards by way of explanation,

“Do you live in the village?’ asked the man next.

The or shook his head with an in- describable gesture of contempt.

“Then where do you live?’

He opened his mouth so that they saw the white line of his teeth, and he began to utter a sound that was not unlike the throaty notes of a big bird. It continued for some seconds, but no words came, He stared at each of them in turn, the stream of sound broken at intervals by tiny explosions from the lips. It ost seemed as though speech were unfamiliar to him something he could not manage an was struggling with for the first time. Then they discovered that the child had a dreadful stammer but a stam- mer unlike anything they had ever heard before. It was fully a minute before he managed to produce the words, yet in the direction where he pointed finally there was nothing to be seen but ploughed fields looming darkly, and a few ragged and ungain- ly elms standing lke broken pillars in the night.

“Over there—beyond,” ’ was what he seemed to say,

They began to realise somewhat vividly that it was a late December evening; the night gathered increas- ingly about them; in the tops of the high elms a faint wind stirred and whispered ; the face of the world grew unfamiliar, as though they were plunged i» some desolate region where uman help availed not. The shadows had come forth in troops and taken possession of the landscape, somehow altering it. For the moment they for- got their immediate purpose of meet- ing a hungry bicycle-rider and hurry ing back to tea at the inn, The pas- sage of time shpped back, as in dreams, to where it was af no account, and they stood there, half fascinated, hall frightened by this imp of a crea- ture who seemed to them about to fi a corner of the veil that hangs ever be- tween the illusions ef the broken enses and the realities that lie be- yond.

But it was the boy himself who broke the spell by suddenly stepping forward and holding out his hands to them. A smile slipped out of his strange eves and ran is cus his face, making it shine.

“Come,”’he said, without any sign now of a stammer, “come, and T will how you where T live, Your friend ts already there waiting.’

And the imp mentioned him hy name!

The younger girl—she who most looked forward to his coming—gave a perceptible start. and moved quickly backwards towards the hedge. Some- thing clutched at her heart, and made her horribly afraid.

But at mention of their friend’s name, the man of the party burst into a cheery laugh.

“There! he cried, “I told you it was Harry! It’s his idea of a Christ- mas joke. He’s gone on to the other imp, the Black Horse, and sent this imp of darkness to waylay us. Now we shall have two teas to negotiate!” He clapped his hands and turned to the girls behind him. ‘‘Come on,’’ he said, ‘‘let’s follow the youngster to the Black Horse and then send him to fetch the others.”

Yet the man’s words seemed a sham, signifying nothing, or at most merely cheap bravado. They all stood stock still and made no pretence of moving. Their real business was with this boy who hovered there before them be- tween the dusk and the darkness, his hands still outstretched, an air of in- vitation in his face and manner. It was the boy’s message they wanted, yet dreaded to hear, the real message not yet delivered. His eyes, there in the gloom, were so preternaturally steady, so compelling, so stern almost for a ch ld, the younger girl thought. And they sought ever the one face, disregard.ng the other two. For each girl was positive he looked only into het own eyes, while the man after- wards declared that the boy looked only at him. To each the illusion was perfect,

Thus it seemed an act of inspiration, bringing relief to the’ uneasy feelings of them all, when the man walked for- ward towards the imp, and into those outstretched hands—cones coppers.

Certainly it was a relief to see him pocket them without an instant’s hesi- tation, for this was an eminently hu- man proceeding. But the thin peal of elfin laughter that followed the action was not what they had expected, and the echoes that came from the leafless woods beyond, and prolonged the sound, made them all turn sharply about and try to face in every direction at once. The echoes had seemed so curiously like real voices.

Then the man, by way of protest against the increasing strangeness of it all, resolved to test the spell more vigorously,

“Come,” he cried, laughing rather boisterously, ‘we’ll play puss in the corner. You shall be puss, and each time you Bet into a corner you shall have a halfpenny.”

The bey made no audible reply, but danced about lightly in the twilight in the middle of the lane, while the smile flitted over his face like the re- flections of an unseen lan‘ern and the others ran wildly from corner to cor- ner, till the imp hat finally won six pence. Jt was easy for him to w-n. The moment hé made for a corner, its occupant fled screaming into the lane. It was impossible, they felt, to con test the points of a merely human game with such a creature of the shad- ows and the dusk.

Then occurred the strangest thing of all. The game was over and they were girding up their loins to follow the boy to the Black Horse first, and afterwards to their own inn, when, with a quick motion like the rush of a bird, he darted to the younger girl, flung down all the coppers into her hands, before she even guessed what he was about, whispered some words close to her face, uttered a shrill ery of laughter—and was gone!

“Oh, Ohl’ she cried out piteously—and this time there was real pain and terror in her voice, ‘‘Now I know! Now I know why I was afraid!”

She half fell backwards across a heap of broken stones, and the other two were swiftly at her side with sym- pathetic questions of alarm. But she was on her feet again in a second. She ran a few paces down the road to the spot where the boy had so mys- teriously vanished, None of them had seen exactly how we went, for one second he was there, and the next he was not there. That was all they knew. :

The girl paused and held her hand to her side. She peered into the dark- ness.

“Harry!” she called faintly; and again with anguish in her voice, “Harry! Are you there !’’

ee were standing in the level space between the two sharp hills. In front of them, after an abrupt turn, the long white road seemed to run steeply into the sky. And it was down this hill that the coming bicyclist must shape his dangerous course.

“There!” she cried again suddenly, running to the side of the road where the hedge ceased, and an open gap led the sight as a single plunge into ed space. ‘Oh, I knew it, I knew it!’

And when the others joined her, and peered over the hedge they found themselves looking down into the chasm of a disused chalk pit, at the bottom of which in the faint glimmer of the lime and the starlight, lay the smashed bicycle, with the lifeless body of its rider outstretched beside it.

The “Country Life” Anthology of Verse

Edited by P. Anderson Graham, Reviewed by Algernon Blackwood

Here is a little book of joy, of comfort, too qualities of primary importance at a time like this. It is a book of songs, of singing. I should like to send a copy to every trench; they would be well thumbed, well loved copies before a week was over. ‘ “ You might send a few books, too,” wrote a soldier recently, ‘and don’t forget a bit of poetry, mind. Only—it must be good, simple stuff—the real article, something the men can understand. They read poetry now—when they can get it. They love it.” Well, here is the very book to send. It has happiness and beauty in it on every page, it has depth as well, above all there is courage, hope and tenderness: it holds the essential English spirit. With hardly an exception, the poems have sprung from hearts touched into fire by emotion—true songs, that is to say, and, while technique may vary, the authentic singing is almost always there. It is what the soldier called “the real article.” I am sending copies out to the trenches; I hope others who read these words will do the same.

All the poems have appeared at one time or another in Country Life—certainly, the colour and fragrance of English country life rise from the very ink and _ paper. Open the little volume, and you hear the mavis sing; the murmur of woodland streams among the beeches haunts the ear; the poplars rustle; you see the stars above the Sussex downs. The selection obviously has been a work of love, but the fine taste that made it has done’so with the heart as well as with the head. In my travels, with luggage reduced to a minimum, six books has been my rule. I must now take seven. “Experience shows,” writes the editor in a word of introduction, “ ‘ that in times of greatest stress what is real in poetry comes as a solace because it corresponds with the depth, tenderness, and emotional force evoked by stress and grief. Soldiers in the trenches have developed a hitherto latent taste for poetry, just as they have shown a resurgence of religious feeling.” In other words, the heart is open, and must be fed. And 1] would quote another passage, since it expresses better than I can precisely what I feel about this particular anthology: “There are poems to suit many tastes, but there are none given over to vague, ill defined emotion or any merely fanciful sentimentality. There are poems for to-day of ‘the lads who have gone to the war,’ and of those who will come back no more. The poems of loss and regret will appeal to the many who have heard the beating of the wings of the Angel of Death. And it is hoped that the beautiful poems of our countryside, of our grey seas and tumbling burns, will be read with joy by soldiers far from home and land where their hearts are. May they prove to be pictures as intimate to their hearts as the remembrance of dear familiar faces.” ’

In any brief notice of a book of poems that gives pleasure as this one does, it is difficult, and invidious, perhaps, to make quotations. Many poets of established fame have contributed to Country Life; others who have since attained to distinction sent to it their earliest verses; unknown writers made their appearance, too, in the postbag from all parts of the world. In the 200. pages there is something to suit all tastes. From the searching lines called ‘ Territorials,’ by Agnes Falconer, and a_ very poignant poem of Miss Friedlaender (“Passover”) at the beginning, down to the beauty and restrained sweetness of C. F. Keary’s “Valedictio” towards the close, there is a rich choice to be enjoyed. The deft arrangement of the contents makes it easy to find something for the dominant mood of the reader at the moment: “The Days of War,” “Desideria,” “Country Life,” “Love and Life,” “Poems of Places,” “Sea Magic,” “Lullabies,” and so forth. “I saw history in a poet’s song,” as John Drinkwater puts it, “and I saw the glory of all dead men in a shadow that went by the side of me.” This modest little book enshrines a moment of our history in its songs of the war; it records what our singers (and minor singers are just as authentic as the major singers !), have felt and thought. They interpret for the army of the inarticulate. Read the “Wykhamist” (Nora Griffiths) with its touch of fire at the close:

You … “died of wounds,” they told me,
. … Yet your feet
Pass with the others down the twilit street.

and Isabel Butchart’s “Separation” and Agnes Falconer’s “In vain, in vain and all in vain,” with its courageous note, “ ‘ there is no sorrow—save our own.” It is, as I sa\, difficult to quote with fairness from this delightful book. It holds many names well known to lovers of true poetry: Henley, Jane Barlow, Laurence Binyon, Walter de la Mar Margaret Sackville, Laurence Housman, Violet Jacobs, the Laureate himself, with William H. Davies, Henry Newbolt, James Elroy Flecker, Fiona Macleod and many, many others. Mrs. Gurney and A. Hepple Dickinson are well loved by the readers of Country Life, and are exquisitely represented here. I hope by Christmas there will be many of our fighting men in the trenches who will taste the joy and comfort that these poems hold. They will realise, at any rate, that all over England there are singers who think of them with gratitude and love. It is a book to slip into your next parcel!

The Daisy World

Adventure means saying Yes, and being careless; children say Yes to everything and are very careless indeed: even their No is usually a Yes, inverted or deferred. “I won’t play,” parsed by a psychologist, means “I’ll play when I’m ready.” The adventurous spirit accepts what offers regardless of consequences; he who hesitates and thinks is a mere Policeman who prevents adventure. Now, everything offers itself to children, because they rightly think that everything belongs to them. Life is conditionless, if only people would let them accept it as it is. “Don’t think; accept!” expresses the law of their swift and fluid being. They act on it. They take everything they can—get. But it is the Policeman who adds the “get,” changing the whole significance of life with one ugly syllable.

Each of the children possessed and treasured an adventure of its very own: an adventure-in-chief, private and particular, that could not possibly have happened to anybody else in the world. Grownups have these too, of course, whether they be kings, or married men, or private detectives. The child in us persists until the last hair and tooth fall out.

Thus, Jinny, Jimbo and Maria—three survivals in an age when education considers childhood a disease to be cured as hurriedly as possible—took their adventure the instant that it came, and each was proud with a complete assurance of superiority that his or her particular one was unique. To no one else in the world could such a thing have happened, least of all to the other two. Each took it characteristically, according to his or her individual nature—Jinny, with a sense of Romance called deathless; Jimbo, with a taste for Poetic Drama, a dash of the supernatural in it; and Maria, with a magnificent inactivity that ruled the world by waiting for things to happen, then claiming them as her own. Her masterly instinct for repose ran no risk of failure from misdirected energy. And to all three secrecy, of course, was essential: “Don’t never tell the others, Uncle! Promise faithfully now!”

For, to every adventure Uncle Henry acted as audience, atmosphere and chorus. He watched whatever happened—audience; believed in its reality—atmosphere; and explained without explaining away—chorus. He had the unusual faculty of being ten years young as well as forty years old, and a real adventure was not possible without him.

The secrecy, of course, was not preserved for long; sooner or later the glory must be shared so that “the others” knew—and envied. For only then was the joy complete, the splendour properly fulfilled. And so the old tired world went round and life grew more and more wonderful each day. For children are an epitome of life—a self-creating universe.

That week was memorable for several reasons. Daddy, overworked in an office, went for a change by sea to Scotland, taking Mother with him; Aunt Emily, in her black silk dress that crackled with disapproval, went to Tunbridge Wells—an awful place in another century somewhere; and Uncle Henry was left behind to “take charge of ‘em,’”—“em” being the children and himself. It was evidence of monumental trust and power, placing him in their imaginations even above the recognised Authorities. His sway was never for a moment questioned.

“No lessons, then!” he had insisted as a condition of acceptance, and after much confabulation the point was yielded with reluctance. Maria claimed the victory, of course, by merely sitting still and affirming that her state of health was not satisfactory. Anyhow, it was to be a ten days’ holiday all round. They had the house and grounds entirely to themselves, and with the departure of the elders a sheet was pulled by someone off the world, a curtain rolled away, another drop-scene fell, the word No disappeared, they saw invisible things.

Another reason, however, made the week memorable—the daisies. It was extraordinary. The very day after the grownups left the daisies came. Like thousands of small white birds, with bright and steady eyes, they arrived and settled, thick and plentiful. They appeared in sheets and clouds upon the grass, all of their own accord and unexplained. In a night the lawns turned white. It seemed a prearranged invasion. Jinny, first awake that morning, looked out of her window to watch a squirrel playing, and noticed them. Then she told the others; and Maria, one eye above the blankets, ejaculated “Ah!” She claimed the daisies too.

Now, whereas a single daisy has no smell and seems a common, unimportant thing, a bunch of several hundred holds all the perfume of the spring. No flowers lie closer to the soil or bring the smell of earth more sweetly to the mind; upon the lips and cheeks they are softer than a kitten’s fur, and lie against the skin like tired eyelids. They are, perhaps, the common people of the flower world, but they have in virtue of that fact the beauty and simplicity of the common people. They own a subdued and unostentatious strength, are humble and ignored, are walked upon, unnoticed, rarely thought about and never praised; they are cut off in early youth by nowing machines; yet their pain in fading is unreported, their little sufferings unsung. They cling to earth and never aspire to climb, but they hold the sweetest dew and nurse the tiniest little winds imaginable. Their patience is divine. They are proud to be the carpet for all walking, running things, and in their universal service is their strength. The rain stays longer with them than with grander flowers, and the best sunlight goes to sleep among them in great pools of fragrant and delicious heat. The daisies are a stalwart little people altogether.

But they have another quality as well—something elfin, wayward, mischievous. They peep and whisper. It is said they can cast spells. Certainly they can coax humans into their own lovely world and keep them there. There is a hint of impudence in their private conduct, half audacity, half wickedness, that shows itself a little in the way they stare unwinkingly all day at everything above them—at the stately things that tower proudly in the air—then just shut up at sunset without a word of explanation or apology. They see everything, but keep their opinions to themselves. Because people notice them so little, and even tread upon their tiny and enquiring faces, they are up to things all the time—undiscovered things. They know, it is said, the thoughts of Marble Whites and Clouded Brimstones, as well as the intentions of the disappearing golden flies; why wind keeps often close to the ground when the treetops are without a single breath; but, also, they know what is going on below the surface. They live, moreover, in every country of the globe, and their system of intercommunication is so perfect that even birds and flying things can learn from it. They prove their breeding by their perfect taste in dress, the well-bred being ever inconspicuous; and their simplicity conceals enormous, undecipherable wonder. One daisy out of doors is worth a hundred shelves of text books in the house. Their mischief, moreover, is not revenge, though some might think it so—but a natural desire to be recognised and thought about and talked about a little. Daisies, in a word are—daisies.

And it was by way of the daisies that Jinny’s great adventure came to her, the particular adventure that was her very own. For she had deep sympathy with flowers, a sympathy lacking in her brother and sister, and it was natural that her adventure in chief should come that way. She could play with flowers for long periods at a time; she knew their names and habits; she picked them gently, without cruelty, and never merely for the fun of picking them; while the way she arranged them about the house proved that she understood their silent, inner natures, their likes and dislikes—in a word, their souls. As has been seen, she was the first to notice the arrival of the daisies. From the bedroom window she waved her arm to them, and showed plainly the pleasure that she felt. They arrived in troops and armies. Risen to the surface of the lawn like cream, she saw them staring wide-eyed with suspicious innocence at the sky. They stared at her.

“Just when the others have gone away!” was her instant thought, though unexpressed in words. There was meaning somewhere in this calculated arrival!

“They are alive,” she asked that afternoon, “aren’t they? But why do they all shut up at night? Who—” she changed the word—“what closes them?”

She was alone with Uncle Henry, and they had chosen with great difficulty a spot where they could lie down without crushing a single flower with their enormous bodies. With considerable difficulty they had found it. Having done a great many things since lunch—a feast involving several second helpings—they were feeling heavy and exhausted. So Jinny chose this moment for her simple question. The world required explanation.

“There’s life in everything,” he mumbled with his face against the grass, “everything that grows especially.” And having said it he settled down comfortably again to doze. His pipe was out. Нө felt rather like a log.

“But stopping growing isn’t dying,” she informed him sharply.

“Oh, no,” he agreed lazily. “You’re alive for a long time after that.”

“Because you stopped growing before I was born.”

“And I’m not quite dead yet.”

“Exactly,” she said, “so daisies are alive.”

It was absurd to think of dozing at such a time. He rolled round heavily and gazed at her through half closed eyelids. “A daisy breathes,” he murmured, “and drinks and eats; sap circulates in its little body. Probably it feels as well. Delicate threads like nerves run through it everywhere. It knows when it is being picked or walked on. Oh yes; a daisy is alive all right enough.” He sighed like a big dog that has just shaken a fly off its nose and lies waiting for the next attack. It came at once.

“But who knows it?” she asked. “I mean there’s no good being alive unless someone else knows it too!”

Then he sat up and stared at her. Jinny, he remembered, knew a lot of things she could tell to no one, not even to herself—and this seemed one of them. The question was a startling one.

“An intellectual mystic at thirteen!” he gasped. “How on earth did you manage it?”

“I’m not quite thirteen,” she replied gravely, “and I’m not a mistylectual insect at all. But what’s the good of being alive, even like a daisy, unless all the others know it—us, for instance?”

He still stared at her, sitting up stiffly, and propped by his hands upon the grass behind him. After prolonged reflection, during which he closed his eyes and opened them several times in succession, sighing laboriously while he did so, low mumbled words became audible:

“Forgive my apparent slowness,” he said, “but I feel like a mowing machine this afternoon. I want oiling and pushing. The answer to your enquiry, however, is as follows: We could—if we took the trouble.”

“Could know that daisies are alive?” she cried. His great head nodded.

“If we thought about them very, very hard indeed,” he replied, “and for a very, very long time, we could feel as they feel, and so understand them and know exactly how they are alive.”

And the way he said it, the grave, thoughtful, solemn way, convinced her, who already was convinced beforehand.

“I do believe we could,” she answered simply.

“I’m sure of it,” he said.

“Let’s try!” she whispered breathlessly.

For a minute and a half they stared into each other’s eyes, knowing themselves upon the verge of an immense discovery. They balanced on the threshold of untold adventure. She did not doubt or question; she did not jeer and tell him he was only humbugging. Her heart thrilled with the right conditions—expectation and delight. Her dark brown eyes were burning.

He murmured something then she did not properly understand.

“Expect and delight
Is the way to invite;
Delight and expect—
And you’ll know things direct!“

“Let’s try!” she repeated, and her face proved that she fulfilled his conditions without knowing it; she was delighted, and she expected everything. He scratched his head, wrinkling his nose and pursing up his lips a moment. “There’s a dodge about it,” he explained, “a certain kind of dodge. To know a flower yourself you must feel like it. Its life, you see, is different to ours. It doesn’t move and hurry, it just lives. It feels sun and wind and dew; it feels the insects’ tread; it lifts its skin to meet the rain drops and the whispering butterflies. It doesn’t run away. It has no fear of anything, because it has the whole green earth behind it, and it feels safe because millions of other daisies feel the same—”

“And smells because it’s happy,” put in Jinny. “Then what is a daisy? What is it really?”

She was “expecting” vividly. Her mind was hungry for essentials. This mere description told her nothing real. She wanted to feel “direct.”

What is a daisy? The little word already had a wonderful and living sound—soft, sweet and beautiful. But to tell the truth about this ordinary masterpiece was no easy matter. An ostentatious lily, a blazing rose, a wayward hyacinth, a mass of showy wistaria—notorious, complicated flowers—presented fewer difficulties. A daisy seemed too simple to be told, its mystery and honour too humble for proud human minds to understand.

So he answered gently, while a Marble White sailed past between their very faces: “Let’s think about it hard; perhaps we’ll get it that way.”

The butterfly sailed off across the lawn; another joined it, and then a third. They danced and fitted like winged marionettes on wires that the swallows pulled; and, as they vanished, a breath of scented air stole round the trunk of the big lime tree and stirred the daisies’ heads. A thousand small white faces turned towards them; a thousand steady eyes observed them; a thousand slender necks were bent. There seemed a little wave of movement over the lawn as though the flowers pressed nearer, aware at last that they were being noticed. And both humans, the big one and the little one, felt a thrill of sudden happiness and beauty in their hearts. The rapture of the Spring slipped into them. They concentrated all their thoughts on daisies. …

“I’m beginning to feel it already,” whispered the Little Human, turning to gaze at him as though that breath of air impelled her to.

The wind blew her voice across his face like perfume; he looked, but could not see her clearly; she swayed a little; her eyes melted together into a single lovely circle, bright and steady within their fringe of feathery lashes. He tried to speak—“Delight and expect, and we’ll know it direct”—but his voice spread across whole yards of lawn. It became a single word that rolled everywhere about him, rising and falling like a wave upon a sea of green: “Daisy, daisy, daisy.” On all sides, beneath, above his head as well, it passed with the music of the wandering wind, and he kept repeating it—“Daisy, daisy!” She kept repeating it too, till the sound multiplied, yet never grew louder than a murmur as of air and grass and tiny leaves—“Daisy, daisy, daisy.” It broke like a sea upon the coastline of another world. It was everywhere.

But another sound lay underneath. As the crest of a breaking wave utters its separate note of foam above the general booming of the sea that bears it, so the flying wave of daisy-tones rose out of this deeper sound beneath. Both humans became aware that it was but a surface voice they imitated. They heard the foundation sound that bore it—deep, booming, thunderous, half lost and very far away. It was prodigious; yet there was safety and delight in it that brought no hint of fear. They swam, it seemed, upon the pulse of some enormous but very gentle life that rose about and through them in a swelling tide. They felt the heave of something that was strong enough to draw the moon, yet soft enough to close a daisy’s eyes. They heard the deep, lost roar of it, rising and coming nearer. Ah, it was exquisite. They were in the Daisy world.

“The Earth!” he whispered. “And the Spring is rising through it. Listen!”

“We’re growing together,” replied the Little Human. “We’re rising with the Spring!”

He tried to move and reach her, but found that he could not take a step in any direction, and that his feet were imbedded in the soft damp soil. The movement that he tried to make spread wide among a hundred others like himself. They rose on every side. All shared his movement as all had shared his voice. He heard his whole body murmuring, singing “Daisy, daisy, daisy. …” And she leaned over, bending towards him a slim form in a graceful line of green that formed the segment of a circle. A little shining face came close for a moment against his own. It was rimmed with delicate spears of pink and white. It sang as it shone. The Spring was in it. There were hundreds like it everywhere, yet he recognised it as one he knew. There were thousands, tens of thousands, yet this one he distinguished because he loved it.

Their faces touched like the fringes of two clouds, and then withdrew. They remained very close together, side by side among thousands like themselves, slowly rising on the same great tide. The Earth’s round body was beneath them. They felt quite safe. But already they were different—they were otherwise than they had been.

“We’re changing,” he murmured, seizing some fragments of half-remembered speech.“We’re marvellously changed!”

“We’re daisies,” he heard her vanishing reply, “two daisies on the lawn!”

And then their voices went. That was the end of speech, the end of thinking too. They only felt.

Long periods passed above their heads and then the air about them turned gorgeous as a sunset sky. It was a Clouded Yellow that sailed lazily past their faces with spreading wings as large as clouds. They shared that saffron glory. The draught of cool air fanned them. The splendid butterfly left its beauty in them and sailed away. But that sunset sky had lasted for hours; that cool wind fanning them was a breeze that blew steadily from the hills making “weather” for half an afternoon. Time and duration as humans measure them had passed away; there was existence without hurry; end and beginning had not been invented yet. They did not know things in the stupid sense of having names for them; all that there was they shared: that was enough. They knew by feeling.

For everything was plentiful and inexhaustible—the heavens emptied light and warmth upon them without stint or measure; space poured about them freely, for they had no wish to move; they felt themselves everywhere, for all they needed came to them without the painful effort of busy things that hunt and search outside themselves; both food and drink slipped into them unawares from an abundant source that equally supplied whole forests without a trace of lessening or loss. All life was theirs, full, free and generous beyond conception. They owned the world, without even the trouble of knowing that they owned it. They lived, simply staring at the universe with eyes of exquisitely fashioned beauty. They knew joy and peace, and were content with that.

They did communicate; oh, yes, they shared each other’s special happiness. There was, it is true, no sound of broken syllables, no speech which humans use to veil the very thing they would express; but there was that simpler language which all Nature knows, which cannot lie because it is unconscious, and by which constellations probably converse with buttercups or cedars with the flying drops of rain—there was gesture. For gesture and attitude can convey all the important and necessary things, while speech in the human sense is but an invention of some sprite who wanted people to wonder what he really meant. In sublimest moments it is never used even in the best circles of intelligence; it drops away quite naturally; souls know one another face to face in dumb yet eloquent gesture:

“The sun is out; I feel warm and happy; there is nothing in the world I need!”

“You are beside me,” he replied. “I love you and we cannot go apart. I smell you even when no wind stirs. You are sweetest when the dew has gone and left you moist and shiny.”

A little shiver of enjoyment quivered through her curving stem. His petals brushed her own. She answered:

“Wet or fine, we stand together, and never stop staring at each other until we close our faces—”

“In the long darkness; but even then we whisper while we grow—”

“And open our eyes exactly at the same moment when the light comes back—”

“And feel warm and soft, and smell more delicious than ever in the dawn.”

These two brave daisies, growing on the lawn, had lives of concentrated, crammed enjoyment, asking no pity for their humble station in the universe. All treated them with unadulterated respect, and everything made love to them because they were so tender and so easily pleased. They knew, for instance, that their splendid Earth was turning with them, for they felt the swerve of her, sharing from their roots upwards her gigantic curve through space; they knew the sun was part of them, because they felt it drawing their sweet-flavoured food up all their dainty length till it glowed in health upon their small, flushed faces; also they knew that streams of water made a tumbling fuss and sent them messages of laughter, because they caught the little rumble of it through miles of trembling ground. And some among them—though these were prophets and poets but half believed, and looked upon as partly mad and partly wonderful—felt the sea itself far leagues away, bending their heads this way and that for hours at a stretch according to the thundering vibrations that the tide sent through the soil from distant shores.

But all, from the tallest spread—heads to the smallest button-faces—all knew the pleasure of the uncertain winds; all knew the game of holding flying things just a moment longer, by fascinating them, by drowsing them into sleepiness, by nipping their probosces, or by puffing perfume in their nostrils while they fastened their feet with the pressure of a hundred yellow rods. For they could regulate their perfume just as humans can regulate emotion.

Enormous periods passed away. A cloud that for a man’s “ten minutes” hid the sun, wearied them with depression, so that they simply closed their eyes and went to sleep. Showers of rain they loved, because it washed and cooled them and they felt the huge satisfaction of the earth beneath them as it drank; the sweet sensation of wet soil that sponged their roots, the pleasant gush that sluiced their bodies and carried off the irritating dust. They also felt the heavier tumbling of the swollen streams in all directions. The drops from overhanging trees came down and played with them, bringing another set of perfumes altogether. A summer shower was, of course, “a month” to them, a day of rain like weeks of holiday by the sea. But, most of all, they enjoyed the rough and tumble nonsense of the violent weather, when they were tied together by the ropes of running wind; for these were visiting days—all manner of strangers dropped in upon them from distant walks in life, and they never knew whether the next would be a fir-cone or one of those careless, irresponsible travellers, a bit of thistledown.

And for all their steadiness of life, they knew incessant change—the variety of a daisy’s existence was proverbial. Nor was the surprise of being walked upon too alarming—it did not come to all—for they knew a way of bending beneath enormous pressure so that nothing broke, while sometimes it brought a queer delicious pleasure, as when the bare feet of some flying child passed lightly over them, leaving wild laughter upon a group of them. They knew, indeed, a thousand joys, proudest of all, however, that the big Earth loved them so that she carried millions of them everywhere she went.

And all, without exception, communicated their knowledge by movements, attitudes and gestures they assumed; and, since each stood close to each, the enjoyment spread quickly till the entire lawn felt one undivided sensation by itself. Anything passing across it at such a moment, whether insect, bird, loose leaf or even human being, would be aware of this—poets, it is said, have received their sweetest inspirations upon a daisied lawn in the flush of spring!—and thus, for a fleeting second, share another world. Nor is it always a sight of prey that makes the swallows dart so suddenly sidewards and away, but some chance message of joy or warning intercepted from the hosts of flowers in the soil.

And from this region of the flower-life comes, of course, the legend that fairies have emotions that last forever, with eternal youth, and with loves that do not pass away to die. Because the measurement of existence is a mightier business than with overdeveloped humans-in-a-hurry. For knowledge comes chiefly through the eye, and the eye can perceive only about six times in a second—things that happen more quickly or more slowly than six times a second are invisible. No man can see the movement of a growing daisy, just as no man can distinguish the separate beats of a sparrow’s wing: one is too slow and the other is too quick. But the daisy is practically all eye. It is aware of most delightful things. In its short life of months it lives through an eternity of unhurrying perceptions and of big sensations. Its youth, its loves, its pleasures are—to it—quite endless.

“I can see the old sun moving,” she murmured, “but you will love me forever, won’t you?”

“Even till it sinks behind the hills,” he answered; “I shall not change.”

“So long we have been friends already,” she went on. “Do you remember when we first met each other, and you looked into my opening eye?”

He sighed with joy, as he thought of the long stretch of time.

“That was in our first reckless youth,” he answered, catching the gold of passionate remembrance from an amber fly that hovered for an instant and was gone.“I remember well. You were half hidden by a drop of hanging dew, but I discovered you! That lilac bud across the world was just beginning to open.” And, helped by the wind, he bent his shining head, taller than hers by a sixtieth of an inch, towards the lilac trees beside the gravel path.

“So long ago,” she murmured, happy with the exquisite belief in him, “so long ago as that! And you will never change or leave me—promise, oh, promise that!”

His stalk grew nearer to her own. He leaned protectively towards her face.

“Until that bud shall open fully to the light and smell its sweetest,” he replied—the gesture of his petals told it plainly—“so long shall you and I enjoy our happy love.”

It was an eternity to them. “And longer still,” she pleaded.

“And longer still,” he whispered in the wind. “Even until the blossom falls.”

Ah, it was good to be alive with such an age of happiness before them!

He felt the tears in her voice, however; he knew there was something that she longed to tell.

“What is your sadness?” he asked softly, “and why do you put such questions to me now? What is your little trouble?”

A moment’s hesitation, a moment’s hanging of the graceful head the width of a petal’s top nearer to his shoulder—and then she told him.

“I was in darkness for a time,” she faltered, “but it was a long, long time. It seemed that something came between us. I lost your face. I felt afraid.”

And his laughter—for just then a puff of wind passed by and shook his sides for him—ran across many feet of lawn.

“It was a Bumble Bee,” he comforted her. “It came between us for a bit, its shadow fell upon you, nothing more! Such things will happen; we must be prepared for them. It was nothing in myself that dimmed the world.”

“Another time I will be braver then,” she told him, “and even in the darkness I shall know you close, ah, very close to me.…”

For a long, long stretch of time, then, they stood joyfully together and watched the lilac growing. They also saw the movement of the sun across the sky. An eternity passed over them.… The vast disc of the sun went slowly gliding.…

But all the enormous things that happened in their lives can not be told. Lives crammed with a succession of such grand and palpitating adventures lie beyond the reach of clumsy words. The sweetness sometimes was intolerable, and then they shared it with the entire lawn and so obtained relief—in order to begin again. The humming of the rising Spring continued with the thunderous droning of the turning Earth. Never uncared for, part of everything, full of the big, rich life that brims the world in May—ah, almost fuller than they could hold sometimes—they passed with existence along to their appointed end.

“We began so long ago, I simply can’t remember it,” she sighed.

Yet the sun they watched had not left a half degree behind him since they met.

“There was no beginning,” he reproved her, smiling, “and there will never be any end.”

And the wind spread their happiness like perfume everywhere until the whole white lawn of daisies lay singing their rapture to the sunshine.

The minute underworld of grass and stalks seemed of a sudden to grow large. Yet till now they had not realised it as “large”—but simply natural. A beetle, big and broad as a Newfoundland dog, went lumbering past them, brushing its polished back against their trembling necks. Yet, till now, they had not thought of it as “big”—but simply normal. Its footsteps made a grating sound like the gardeners’ nailed boots upon the gravel paths. It was strange and startling. Something was different, something was changing. They realised dimly that there was another world somewhere, a world they had left behind long, long ago, forgotten. Something was slipping from them, as sleep slips from the skin and eyes in the early morning when the bath comes “pinging” upon the floor. What did it mean? Big and little, far and near, above, below, inside and outside—all were mixed together in a falling rush.

They themselves were changing.

They looked up. They saw an enormous thing rising behind them with vast caverns of square outline opening in its sides—a house. They saw huge, towering shapes whose tops were in the clouds—the familiar lime-trees. Big and tiny were mixed together.

And that was wrong. For either the forest of grass was as big as themselves—in which case they still were daisies; or else it was tiny and far below them—in which case they were hurrying humans again. There was this odd confusion while consciousness swung home to its appointed centre and Adventure brought them back towards the old, dull starting place again.

There came an ominous and portentous sound that rushed towards them through the air and through the solid ground as well. They heard it and grew pale with terror. Across the entire lawn it rumbled nearer, growing in volume awfully. The very earth seemed breaking into bits about them. And then they knew.

It was the End of the World that their prophets had long foretold.

It crashed upon them before they had time to think. The roar was appalling. The whole lawn trembled. The daisies bowed their little faces in a crowd. They had no time even to close their innocent eyes. Before a quarter of their sweet and happy life was known, the End swept them from the world, unsung and unlamented. Two of them who had planned Eternity together fell side by side before one terrible stroke.

“I do believe—” said Jinny, brushing her tumbled hair out of her eyes.

“Not possible!” exclaimed Uncle Henry, sitting up and stretching himself just like a dog. “It’s a thing I never do, never, never!”

They stared at each other with suspiciously sleepy eyes.

“Promise,” she whispered presently, “promise never to tell the others!”

“I promise faithfully,” he answered. “But we’d better get up or we shall have our heads cut off like—all the other daisies.”

He pulled her to her feet—out of the way of the heavy mowing machine which the gardener was pushing with a whirring, droning noise across the lawn.

The Damned

I

I’m over forty, Frances, and rather set in my ways,” I said good-naturedly, ready to yield if she insisted that our going together on the visit involved her happiness. “My work is rather heavy just now too, as you know. The question is, could I work there—with a lot of unassorted people in the house?”

“Mabel doesn’t mention any other people, Bill,” was my sister’s rejoinder. “I gather she’s alone—as well as lonely.”

By the way she looked sideways out of the window at nothing, it was obvious she was disappointed, but to my surprise she did not urge the point; and as I glanced at Mrs. Franklyn’s invitation lying upon her sloping lap, the neat, childish handwriting conjured up a mental picture of the banker’s widow, with her timid, insignificant personality, her pale grey eyes and her expression as of a backward child. I thought, too, of the roomy country mansion her late husband had altered to suit his particular needs, and of my visit to it a few years ago when its barren spaciousness suggested a wing of Kensington Museum fitted up temporarily as a place to eat and sleep in. Comparing it mentally with the poky Chelsea flat where I and my sister kept impecunious house, I realised other points as well. Unworthy details flashed across me to entice: the fine library, the organ, the quiet workroom I should have, perfect service, the delicious cup of early tea, and hot baths at any moment of the day—without a geyser!

“It’s a longish visit, a month—isn’t it?” I hedged, smiling at the details that seduced me, and ashamed of my man’s selfishness, yet knowing that Frances expected it of me. “There are points about it, I admit. If you’re set on my going with you, I could manage it all right.”

I spoke at length in this way because my sister made no answer. I saw her tired eyes gazing into the dreariness of Oakley Street and felt a pang strike through me. After a pause, in which again she said no word, I added: “So, when you write the letter, you might hint, perhaps, that I usually work all the morning, and—er—am not a very lively visitor! Then she’ll understand, you see.” And I half-rose to return to my diminutive study, where I was slaving, just then, at an absorbing article on Comparative Aesthetic Values in the Blind and Deaf.

But Frances did not move. She kept her grey eyes upon Oakley Street where the evening mist from the river drew mournful perspectives into view. It was late October. We heard the omnibuses thundering across the bridge. The monotony of that broad, characterless street seemed more than usually depressing. Even in June sunshine it was dead, but with autumn its melancholy soaked into every house between King’s Road and the Embankment. It washed thought into the past, instead of inviting it hopefully towards the future. For me, its easy width was an avenue through which nameless slums across the river sent creeping messages of depression, and I always regarded it as Winter’s main entrance into London—fog, slush, gloom trooped down it every November, waving their forbidding banners till March came to rout them. Its one claim upon my love was that the south wind swept sometimes unobstructed up it, soft with suggestions of the sea. These lugubrious thoughts I naturally kept to myself, though I never ceased to regret the little flat whose cheapness had seduced us. Now, as I watched my sister’s impassive face, I realised that perhaps she, too, felt as I felt, yet, brave woman, without betraying it.

“And, look here, Fanny,” I said, putting a hand upon her shoulder as I crossed the room, “it would be the very thing for you. You’re worn out with catering and housekeeping. Mabel is your oldest friend, besides, and you’ve hardly seen her since he died—”

“She’s been abroad for a year, Bill, and only just came back,” my sister interposed. “She came back rather unexpectedly, though I never thought she would go there to live—” She stopped abruptly. Clearly, she was only speaking half her mind. “Probably,” she went on, “Mabel wants to pick up old links again.”

“Naturally,” I put in, “yourself chief among them.” The veiled reference to the house I let pass. It involved discussing the dead man for one thing.

“I feel I ought to go anyhow,” she resumed, “and of course it would be jollier if you came too. You’d get in such a muddle here by yourself, and eat wrong things, and forget to air the rooms, and—oh, everything!” She looked up laughing. “Only,” she added, “there’s the British Museum—?”

“But there’s a big library there,” I answered, “and all the books of reference I could possibly want. It was of you I was thinking. You could take up your painting again; you always sell half of what you paint. It would be a splendid rest too, and Sussex is a jolly country to walk in. By all means, Fanny, I advise—”

Our eyes met, as I stammered in my attempts to avoid expressing the thought that hid in both our minds. My sister had a weakness for dabbling in the various “new” theories of the day, and Mabel, who before her marriage had belonged to foolish societies for investigating the future life to the neglect of the present one, had fostered this undesirable tendency. Her amiable, impressionable temperament was open to every psychic wind that blew. I deplored, detested the whole business. But even more than this I abhorred the later influence that Mr. Franklyn had steeped his wife in, capturing her body and soul in his sombre doctrines. I had dreaded lest my sister also might be caught.

“Now that she is alone again—”

I stopped short. Our eyes now made pretence impossible, for the truth had slipped out inevitably, stupidly, although unexpressed in definite language. We laughed, turning our faces a moment to look at other things in the room. Frances picked up a book and examined its cover as though she had made an important discovery, while I took my case out and lit a cigarette I did not want to smoke. We left the matter there. I went out of the room before further explanation could cause tension. Disagreements grow into discord from such tiny things—wrong adjectives, or a chance inflection of the voice. Frances had a right to her views of life as much as I had. At least, I reflected comfortably, we had separated upon an agreement this time, recognised mutually, though not actually stated.

And this point of meeting was, oddly enough, our way of regarding some one who was dead. For we had both disliked the husband with a great dislike, and during his three years’ married life had only been to the house once—for a weekend visit; arriving late on Saturday, we had left after an early breakfast on Monday morning. Ascribing my sister’s dislike to a natural jealousy at losing her old friend, I said merely that he displeased me. Yet we both knew that the real emotion lay much deeper. Frances, loyal, honourable creature, had kept silence; and beyond saying that house and grounds—he altered one and laid out the other—distressed her as an expression of his personality somehow (‘distressed’ was the word she used), no further explanation had passed her lips.

Our dislike of his personality was easily accounted for—up to a point, since both of us shared the artist’s point of view that a creed, cut to measure and carefully dried, was an ugly thing, and that a dogma to which believers must subscribe or perish everlastingly was a barbarism resting upon cruelty. But while my own dislike was purely due to an abstract worship of Beauty, my sister’s had another twist in it, for with her “new” tendencies, she believed that all religions were an aspect of truth and that no one, even the lowest wretch, could escape “heaven” in the long run.

Samuel Franklyn, the rich banker, was a man universally respected and admired, and the marriage, though Mabel was fifteen years his junior, won general applause; his bride was an heiress in her own right—breweries—and the story of her conversion at a revivalist meeting where Samuel Franklyn had spoken fervidly of heaven, and terrifyingly of sin, hell and damnation, even contained a touch of genuine romance. She was a brand snatched from the burning; his detailed eloquence had frightened her into heaven; salvation came in the nick of time; his words had plucked her from the edge of that lake of fire and brimstone where their worm dieth not and the fire is not quenched. She regarded him as a hero, sighed her relief upon his saintly shoulder, and accepted the peace he offered her with a grateful resignation.

For her husband was a “religious man” who successfully combined great riches with the glamour of winning souls. He was a portly figure, though tall, with masterful, big hands, the fingers rather thick and red; and his dignity, that just escaped being pompous, held in it something that was implacable. A convinced assurance, almost remorseless, gleamed in his eyes when he preached especially, and his threats of hell fire must have scared souls stronger than the timid, receptive Mabel whom he married. He clad himself in long frock-coats that buttoned unevenly, big square boots, and trousers that invariably bagged at the knee and were a little short; he wore low collars, spats occasionally, and a tall black hat that was not of silk. His voice was alternately hard and unctuous; and he regarded theatres, ballrooms and racecourses as the vestibule of that brimstone lake of whose geography he was as positive as of his great banking offices in the City. A philanthropist up to the hilt, however, no one ever doubted his complete sincerity; his convictions were ingrained, his faith borne out by his life—as witness his name upon so many admirable Societies, as treasurer, patron, or heading the donation list. He bulked large in the world of doing good, a broad and stately stone in the rampart against evil. And his heart was genuinely kind and soft for others—who believed as he did.

Yet, in spite of this true sympathy with suffering and his desire to help, he was narrow as a telegraph wire and unbending as a church pillar; he was intensely selfish; intolerant as an officer of the Inquisition, his bourgeois soul constructed a revolting scheme of heaven that was reproduced in miniature in all he did and planned. Faith was the sine qua non of salvation, and by “faith” he meant belief in his own particular view of things—“which faith, except every one do keep whole and undefiled, without doubt he shall perish everlastingly.” All the world but his own small, exclusive sect must be damned eternally—a pity, but alas, inevitable. He was right.

Yet he prayed without ceasing, and gave heavily to the poor—the only thing he could not give being big ideas to his provincial and suburban deity. Pettier than an insect, and more obstinate than a mule, he had also the superior, sleek humility of a “chosen one.” He was churchwarden too. He read the Lessons in a “place of worship,” either chilly or overheated, where neither organ, vestments, nor lighted candles were permitted, but where the odour of hair-wash on the boys’ heads in the back rows pervaded the entire building.

This portrait of the banker, who accumulated riches both on earth and in heaven, may possibly be overdrawn, however, because Frances and I were “artistic temperaments” that viewed the type with a dislike and distrust amounting to contempt. The majority considered Samuel Franklyn a worthy man and a good citizen. The majority, doubtless, held the saner view. A few years more, and he certainly would have been made a baronet. He relieved much suffering in the world, as assuredly as he caused many souls the agonies of torturing fear by his emphasis upon damnation. Had there been one point of beauty in him, we might have been more lenient; only we found it not, and, I admit, took little pains to search. I shall never forget the look of dour forgiveness with which he heard our excuses for missing Morning Prayers that Sunday morning of our single visit to The Towers. My sister learned that a change was made soon afterwards, prayers being “conducted” after breakfast instead of before.

The Towers stood solemnly upon a Sussex hill amid park-like modern grounds, but the house cannot better be described—it would be so wearisome for one thing—than by saying that it was a cross between an overgrown, pretentious Norwood villa and one of those saturnine Institutes for cripples the train passes as it slinks ashamed through South London into Surrey. It was “wealthily” furnished and at first sight imposing, but on closer acquaintance revealed a meagre personality, barren and austere. One looked for Rules and Regulations on the walls, all signed By Order. The place was a prison that shut out “the world.” There was, of course, no billiard-room, no smoking-room, no room for play of any kind, and the great hall at the back, once a chapel which might have been used for dancing, theatricals, or other innocent amusements, was consecrated in his day to meetings of various kinds, chiefly brigades, temperance or missionary societies. There was a harmonium at one end—on the level floor—a raised dais or platform at the other, and a gallery above for the servants, gardeners and coachmen. It was heated with hot-water pipes, and hung with Doré’s pictures, though these latter were soon removed and stored out of sight in the attics as being too unspiritual. In polished, shiny wood, it was a representation in miniature of that poky exclusive Heaven he took about with him, externalising it in all he did and planned, even in the grounds about the house.

Changes in The Towers, Frances told me, had been made during Mabel’s year of widowhood abroad—an organ put into the big hall, the library made liveable and recatalogued—when it was permissible to suppose she had found her soul again and returned to her normal, healthy views of life, which included enjoyment and play, literature, music and the arts, without, however, a touch of that trivial thoughtlessness usually termed worldliness. Mrs. Franklyn, as I remembered her, was a quiet little woman, shallow, perhaps, and easily influenced, but sincere as a dog and thorough in her faithful friendships. Her tastes at heart were catholic, and that heart was simple and unimaginative. That she took up with the various movements of the day was sign merely that she was searching in her limited way for a belief that should bring her peace. She was, in fact, a very ordinary woman, her calibre a little less than that of Frances. I knew they used to discuss all kinds of theories together, but as these discussions never resulted in action, I had come to regard her as harmless. Still, I was not sorry when she married, and I did not welcome now a renewal of the former intimacy. The philanthropist had given her no children, or she would have made a good and sensible mother. No doubt she would marry again.

“Mabel mentions that she’s been alone at The Towers since the end of August,” Frances told me at teatime; “and I’m sure she feels out of it and lonely. It would be a kindness to go. Besides, I always liked her.”

I agreed. I had recovered from my attack of selfishness. I expressed my pleasure.

“You’ve written to accept,” I said, half statement and half question.

Frances nodded. “I thanked for you,” she added quietly, “explaining that you were not free at the moment, but that later, if not inconvenient, you might come down for a bit and join me.”

I stared. Frances sometimes had this independent way of deciding things. I was convicted, and punished into the bargain.

Of course there followed argument and explanation, as between brother and sister who were affectionate, but the recording of our talk could be of little interest. It was arranged thus, Frances and I both satisfied. Two days later she departed for The Towers, leaving me alone in the flat with everything planned for my comfort and good behaviour—she was rather a tyrant in her quiet way—and her last words as I saw her off from Charing Cross rang in my head for a long time after she was gone:

“I’ll write and let you know, Bill. Eat properly, mind, and let me know if anything goes wrong.”

She waved her small gloved hand, nodded her head till the feather brushed the window, and was gone.

II

After the note announcing her safe arrival a week of silence passed, and then a letter came; there were various suggestions for my welfare, and the rest was the usual rambling information and description Frances loved, generously italicised.

“… and we are quite alone,” she went on in her enormous handwriting that seemed such a waste of space and labour, “though some others are coming presently, I believe. You could work here to your heart’s content. Mabel quite understands, and says she would love to have you when you feel free to come. She has changed a bit—back to her old natural self: she never mentions him. The place has changed too in certain ways: it has more cheerfulness, I think. She has put it in, this cheerfulness, spaded it in, if you know what I mean; but it lies about uneasily and is not natural—quite. The organ is a beauty. She must be very rich now, but she’s as gentle and sweet as ever. Do you know, Bill, I think he must have frightened her into marrying him. I get the impression she was afraid of him.” This last sentence was inked out, but I read it through the scratching; the letters being too big to hide. “He had an inflexible will beneath all that oily kindness which passed for spiritual. He was a real personality, I mean. I’m sure he’d have sent you and me cheerfully to the stake in another century—for our own good. Isn’t it odd she never speaks of him, even to me?” This, again, was stroked through, though without the intention to obliterate—merely because it was repetition, probably. “The only reminder of him in the house now is a big copy of the presentation portrait that stands on the stairs of the Multitechnic Institute at Peckham—you know—that life-size one with his fat hand sprinkled with rings resting on a thick Bible and the other slipped between the buttons of a tight frock-coat. It hangs in the dining-room and rather dominates our meals. I wish Mabel would take it down. I think she’d like to, if she dared. There’s not a single photograph of him anywhere, even in her own room. Mrs. Marsh is here—you remember her, his housekeeper, the wife of the man who got penal servitude for killing a baby or something—you said she robbed him and justified her stealing because the story of the unjust steward was in the Bible! How we laughed over that! She’s just the same too, gliding about all over the house and turning up when least expected.”

Other reminiscences filled the next two sides of the letter, and ran, without a trace of punctuation, into instructions about a Salamander stove for heating my workroom in the flat; these were followed by things I was to tell the cook, and by requests for several articles she had forgotten and would like sent after her, two of them blouses, with descriptions so lengthy and contradictory that I sighed as I read them—“unless you come down soon, in which case perhaps you wouldn’t mind bringing them; not the mauve one I wear in the evening sometimes, but the pale blue one with lace round the collar and the crinkly front. They’re in the cupboard—or the drawer, I’m not sure which—of my bedroom. Ask Annie if you’re in doubt. Thanks most awfully. Send a telegram, remember, and we’ll meet you in the motor any time. I don’t quite know if I shall stay the whole month—alone. It all depends. …” And she closed the letter, the italicised words increasing recklessly towards the end, with a repetition that Mabel would love to have me “for myself,” as also to have a “man in the house,” and that I only had to telegraph the day and the train. … This letter, coming by the second post, interrupted me in a moment of absorbing work, and, having read it through to make sure there was nothing requiring instant attention, I threw it aside and went on with my notes and reading. Within five minutes, however, it was back at me again. That restless thing called “between the lines” fluttered about my mind. My interest in the Balkan States—political article that had been “ordered”—faded. Somewhere, somehow I felt disquieted, disturbed. At first I persisted in my work, forcing myself to concentrate, but soon found that a layer of new impressions floated between the article and my attention. It was like a shadow, though a shadow that dissolved upon inspection. Once or twice I glanced up, expecting to find some one in the room, that the door had opened unobserved and Annie was waiting for instructions. I heard the ’buses thundering across the bridge. I was aware of Oakley Street. Montenegro and the blue Adriatic melted into the October haze along that depressing Embankment that aped a river bank, and sentences from the letter flashed before my eyes and stung me. Picking it up and reading it through more carefully, I rang the bell and told Annie to find the blouses and pack them for the post, showing her finally the written description, and resenting the superior smile with which she at once interrupted, “I know them, sir,” and disappeared.

But it was not the blouses: it was that exasperating thing “between the lines” that put an end to my work with its elusive teasing nuisance. The first sharp impression is alone of value in such a case, for once analysis begins the imagination constructs all kinds of false interpretation. The more I thought, the more I grew fuddled. The letter, it seemed to me, wanted to say another thing; instead the eight sheets conveyed it merely. It came to the edge of disclosure, then halted. There was something on the writer’s mind, and I felt uneasy. Studying the sentences brought, however, no revelation, but increased confusion only; for while the uneasiness remained, the first clear hint had vanished. In the end I closed my books and went out to look up another matter at the British Museum Library. Perhaps I should discover it that way—by turning the mind in a totally new direction. I lunched at the Express Dairy in Oxford Street close by, and telephoned to Annie that I would be home to tea at five.

And at tea, tired physically and mentally after breathing the exhausted air of the Rotunda for five hours, my mind suddenly delivered up its original impression, vivid and clear-cut; no proof accompanied the revelation; it was mere presentiment, but convincing. Frances was disturbed in her mind, her orderly, sensible, housekeeping mind; she was uneasy, even perhaps afraid; something in the house distressed her, and she had need of me. Unless I went down, her time of rest and change, her quite necessary holiday, in fact, would be spoilt. She was too unselfish to say this, but it ran everywhere between the lines. I saw it clearly now. Mrs. Franklyn, moreover—and that meant Frances too—would like a “man in the house.” It was a disagreeable phrase, a suggestive way of hinting something she dared not state definitely. The two women in that great, lonely barrack of a house were afraid.

My sense of duty, affection, unselfishness, whatever the composite emotion may be termed, was stirred; also my vanity. I acted quickly, lest reflection should warp clear, decent judgment. “Annie,” I said, when she answered the bell, “you need not send those blouses by the post. I’ll take them down tomorrow when I go. I shall be away a week or two, possibly longer.” And, having looked up a train, I hastened out to telegraph before I could change my fickle mind.

But no desire came that night to change my mind. I was doing the right, the necessary thing. I was even in something of a hurry to get down to The Towers as soon as possible. I chose an early afternoon train.

III

A telegram had told me to come to a town ten miles from the house, so I was saved the crawling train to the local station, and travelled down by an express. As soon as we left London the fog cleared off, and an autumn sun, though without heat in it, painted the landscape with golden browns and yellows. My spirits rose as I lay back in the luxurious motor and sped between the woods and hedges. Oddly enough, my anxiety of overnight had disappeared. It was due, no doubt, to that exaggeration of detail which reflection in loneliness brings. Frances and I had not been separated for over a year, and her letters from The Towers told so little. It had seemed unnatural to be deprived of those intimate particulars of mood and feeling I was accustomed to. We had such confidence in one another, and our affection was so deep. Though she was but five years younger than myself, I regarded her as a child. My attitude was fatherly. In return, she certainly mothered me with a solicitude that never cloyed. I felt no desire to marry while she was still alive. She painted in watercolours with a reasonable success, and kept house for me; I wrote, reviewed books and lectured on aesthetics; we were a humdrum couple of quasi-artists, well satisfied with life, and all I feared for her was that she might become a suffragette or be taken captive by one of these wild theories that caught her imagination sometimes, and that Mabel, for one, had fostered. As for myself, no doubt she deemed me a trifle solid or stolid—I forget which word she preferred—but on the whole there was just sufficient difference of opinion to make intercourse suggestive without monotony, and certainly without quarrelling. Drawing in deep draughts of the stinging autumn air, I felt happy and exhilarated. It was like going for a holiday, with comfort at the end of the journey instead of bargaining for centimes.

But my heart sank noticeably the moment the house came into view. The long drive, lined with hostile monkey trees and formal wellingtonias that were solemn and sedate, was mere extension of the miniature approach to a thousand semidetached suburban “residences”; and the appearance of The Towers, as we turned the corner with a rush, suggested a commonplace climax to a story that had begun interestingly, almost thrillingly. A villa had escaped from the shadow of the Crystal Palace, thumped its way down by night, grown suddenly monstrous in a shower of rich rain, and settled itself insolently to stay. Ivy climbed about the opulent redbrick walls, but climbed neatly and with disfiguring effect, sham as on a prison or—the simile made me smile—an orphan asylum. There was no hint of the comely roughness of untidy ivy on a ruin. Clipped, trained and precise it was, as on a brand-new protestant church. I swear there was not a bird’s nest nor a single earwig in it anywhere. About the porch it was particularly thick, smothering a seventeenth-century lamp with a contrast that was quite horrible. Extensive glasshouses spread away on the farther side of the house; the numerous towers to which the building owed its name seemed made to hold school bells; and the windowsills, thick with potted flowers, made me think of the desolate suburbs of Brighton or Bexhill. In a commanding position upon the crest of a hill, it overlooked miles of undulating, wooded country southwards to the Downs, but behind it, to the north, thick banks of ilex, holly and privet protected it from the cleaner and more stimulating winds. Hence, though highly placed, it was shut in. Three years had passed since I last set eyes upon it, but the unsightly memory I had retained was justified by the reality. The place was deplorable.

It is my habit to express my opinions audibly sometimes, when impressions are strong enough to warrant it; but now I only sighed “Oh, dear,” as I extricated my legs from many rugs and went into the house. A tall parlourmaid, with the bearing of a grenadier, received me, and standing behind her was Mrs. Marsh, the housekeeper, whom I remembered because her untidy back hair had suggested to me that it had been burnt. I went at once to my room, my hostess already dressing for dinner, but Frances came in to see me just as I was struggling with my black tie that had got tangled like a bootlace. She fastened it for me in a neat, effective bow, and while I held my chin up for the operation, staring blankly at the ceiling, the impression came—I wondered, was it her touch that caused it?—that something in her trembled. Shrinking perhaps is the truer word. Nothing in her face or manner betrayed it, nor in her pleasant, easy talk while she tidied my things and scolded my slovenly packing, as her habit was, questioning me about the servants at the flat. The blouses, though right, were crumpled, and my scolding was deserved. There was no impatience even. Yet somehow or other the suggestion of a shrinking reserve and holding back reached my mind. She had been lonely, of course, but it was more than that; she was glad that I had come, yet for some reason unstated she could have wished that I had stayed away. We discussed the news that had accumulated during our brief separation, and in doing so the impression, at best exceedingly slight, was forgotten. My chamber was large and beautifully furnished; the hall and dining-room of our flat would have gone into it with a good remainder; yet it was not a place I could settle down in for work. It conveyed the idea of impermanence, making me feel transient as in a hotel bedroom. This, of course, was the fact. But some rooms convey a settled, lasting hospitality even in a hotel; this one did not; and as I was accustomed to work in the room I slept in, at least when visiting, a slight frown must have crept between my eyes.

“Mabel has fitted a workroom for you just out of the library,” said the clairvoyant Frances. “No one will disturb you there, and you’ll have fifteen thousand books all catalogued within easy reach. There’s a private staircase too. You can breakfast in your room and slip down in your dressing-gown if you want to.” She laughed. My spirits took a turn upwards as absurdly as they had gone down.

“And how are you?” I asked, giving her a belated kiss. “It’s jolly to be together again. I did feel rather lost without you, I’ll admit.”

“That’s natural,” she laughed. “I’m so glad.”

She looked well and had country colour in her cheeks. She informed me that she was eating and sleeping well, going out for little walks with Mabel, painting bits of scenery again, and enjoying a complete change and rest; and yet, for all her brave description, the words somehow did not quite ring true. Those last words in particular did not ring true. There lay in her manner, just out of sight, I felt, this suggestion of the exact reverse—of unrest, shrinking, almost of anxiety. Certain small strings in her seemed over-tight. “Keyed-up” was the slang expression that crossed my mind. I looked rather searchingly into her face as she was telling me this.

“Only—the evenings,” she added, noticing my query, yet rather avoiding my eyes, “the evenings are—well, rather heavy sometimes, and I find it difficult to keep awake.”

“The strong air after London makes you drowsy,” I suggested, “and you like to get early to bed.”

Frances turned and looked at me for a moment steadily. “On the contrary, Bill, I dislike going to bed—here. And Mabel goes so early.” She said it lightly enough, fingering the disorder upon my dressing-table in such a stupid way that I saw her mind was working in another direction altogether. She looked up suddenly with a kind of nervousness from the brush and scissors. “Billy,” she said abruptly, lowering her voice, “isn’t it odd, but I hate sleeping alone here? I can’t make it out quite; I’ve never felt such a thing before in my life. Do you—think it’s all nonsense?” And she laughed, with her lips but not with her eyes; there was a note of defiance in her I failed to understand.

“Nothing a nature like yours feels strongly is nonsense, Frances,” I replied soothingly.

But I, too, answered with my lips only, for another part of my mind was working elsewhere, and among uncomfortable things. A touch of bewilderment passed over me. I was not certain how best to continue. If I laughed she would tell me no more, yet if I took her too seriously the strings would tighten further. Instinctively, then, this flashed rapidly across me: that something of what she felt, I had also felt, though interpreting it differently. Vague it was, as the coming of rain or storm that announce themselves hours in advance with their hint of faint, unsettling excitement in the air. I had been but a short hour in the house—big, comfortable, luxurious house—but had experienced this sense of being unsettled, unfixed, fluctuating—a kind of impermanence that transient lodgers in hotels must feel, but that a guest in a friend’s home ought not to feel, be the visit short or long. To Frances, an impressionable woman, the feeling had come in the terms of alarm. She disliked sleeping alone, while yet she longed to sleep. The precise idea in my mind evaded capture, merely brushing through me, three-quarters out of sight; I realised only that we both felt the same thing, and that neither of us could get at it clearly. Degrees of unrest we felt, but the actual thing did not disclose itself. It did not happen.

I felt strangely at sea for a moment. Frances would interpret hesitation as endorsement, and encouragement might be the last thing that could help her.

“Sleeping in a strange house,” I answered at length, “is often difficult at first, and one feels lonely. After fifteen months in our tiny flat one feels lost and uncared-for in a big house. It’s an uncomfortable feeling—I know it well. And this is a barrack, isn’t it? The masses of furniture only make it worse. One feels in storage somewhere underground—the furniture doesn’t furnish. One must never yield to fancies, though—”

Frances looked away towards the windows; she seemed disappointed a little.

“After our thickly-populated Chelsea,” I went on quickly, “it seems isolated here.”

But she did not turn back, and clearly I was saying the wrong thing. A wave of pity rushed suddenly over me. Was she really frightened, perhaps? She was imaginative, I knew, but never moody; common sense was strong in her, though she had her times of hypersensitiveness. I caught the echo of some unreasoning, big alarm in her. She stood there, gazing across my balcony towards the sea of wooded country that spread dim and vague in the obscurity of the dusk. The deepening shadows entered the room, I fancied, from the grounds below. Following her abstracted gaze a moment, I experienced a curious sharp desire to leave, to escape. Out yonder was wind and space and freedom. This enormous building was oppressive, silent, still. Great catacombs occurred to me, things beneath the ground, imprisonment and capture. I believe I even shuddered a little.

I touched her shoulder. She turned round slowly, and we looked with a certain deliberation into each other’s eyes.

“Fanny,” I asked, more gravely than I intended, “you are not frightened, are you? Nothing has happened, has it?”

She replied with emphasis, “Of course not! How could it—I mean, why should I?” She stammered, as though the wrong sentence flustered her a second. “It’s simply—that I have this ter—this dislike of sleeping alone.”

Naturally, my first thought was how easy it would be to cut our visit short. But I did not say this. Had it been a true solution, Frances would have said it for me long ago.

“Wouldn’t Mabel double-up with you?” I said instead, “or give you an adjoining room, so that you could leave the door between you open? There’s space enough, heaven knows.”

And then, as the gong sounded in the hall below for dinner, she said, as with an effort, this thing:

“Mabel did ask me—on the third night—after I had told her. But I declined.”

“You’d rather be alone than with her?” I asked, with a certain relief.

Her reply was so gravely given, a child would have known there was more behind it: “Not that; but that she did not really want it.”

I had a moment’s intuition and acted on it impulsively. “She feels it too, perhaps, but wishes to face it by herself—and get over it?”

My sister bowed her head, and the gesture made me realise of a sudden how grave and solemn our talk had grown, as though some portentous thing were under discussion. It had come of itself—indefinite as a gradual change of temperature. Yet neither of us knew its nature, for apparently neither of us could state it plainly. Nothing happened, even in our words.

“That was my impression,” she said, “—that if she yields to it she encourages it. And a habit forms so easily. Just think,” she added with a faint smile that was the first sign of lightness she had yet betrayed, “what a nuisance it would be—everywhere—if everybody was afraid of being alone—like that.”

I snatched readily at the chance. We laughed a little, though it was a quiet kind of laughter that seemed wrong. I took her arm and led her towards the door.

“Disastrous, in fact,” I agreed.

She raised her voice to its normal pitch again, as I had done. “No doubt it will pass,” she said, “now that you have come. Of course, it’s chiefly my imagination.” Her tone was lighter, though nothing could convince me that the matter itself was light—just then. “And in any case,” tightening her grip on my arm as we passed into the bright enormous corridor and caught sight of Mrs. Franklyn waiting in the cheerless hall below, “I’m very glad you’re here, Bill, and Mabel, I know, is too.”

“If it doesn’t pass,” I just had time to whisper with a feeble attempt at jollity, “I’ll come at night and snore outside your door. After that you’ll be so glad to get rid of me that you won’t mind being alone.”

“That’s a bargain,” said Frances.

I shook my hostess by the hand, made a banal remark about the long interval since last we met, and walked behind them into the great dining-room, dimly lit by candles, wondering in my heart how long my sister and I should stay, and why in the world we had ever left our cosy little flat to enter this desolation of riches and false luxury at all. The unsightly picture of the late Samuel Franklyn, Esq., stared down upon me from the farther end of the room above the mighty mantelpiece. He looked, I thought, like some pompous Heavenly Butler who denied to all the world, and to us in particular, the right of entry without presentation cards signed by his hand as proof that we belonged to his own exclusive set. The majority, to his deep grief, and in spite of all his prayers on their behalf, must burn and “perish everlastingly.”

IV

With the instinct of the healthy bachelor I always try to make myself a nest in the place I live in, be it for long or short. Whether visiting, in lodging-house, or in hotel, the first essential is this nest—one’s own things built into the walls as a bird builds in its feathers. It may look desolate and uncomfortable enough to others, because the central detail is neither bed nor wardrobe, sofa nor armchair, but a good solid writing-table that does not wriggle, and that has wide elbow-room. And The Towers is vividly described for me by the single fact that I could not “nest” there. I took several days to discover this, but the first impression of impermanence was truer than I knew. The feathers of the mind refused here to lie one way. They ruffled, pointed and grew wild.

Luxurious furniture does not mean comfort; I might as well have tried to settle down in the sofa and armchair department of a big shop. My bedroom was easily managed; it was the private workroom, prepared especially for my reception, that made me feel alien and outcast. Externally, it was all one could desire: an antechamber to the great library, with not one, but two generous oak tables, to say nothing of smaller ones against the walls with capacious drawers. There were reading-desks, mechanical devices for holding books, perfect light, quiet as in a church, and no approach but across the huge adjoining room. Yet it did not invite.

“I hope you’ll be able to work here,” said my little hostess the next morning, as she took me in—her only visit to it while I stayed in the house—and showed me the ten-volume Catalogue. “It’s absolutely quiet and no one will disturb you.”

“If you can’t, Bill, you’re not much good,” laughed Frances, who was on her arm. “Even I could write in a study like this!”

I glanced with pleasure at the ample tables, the sheets of thick blotting-paper, the rulers, sealing-wax, paper-knives, and all the other immaculate paraphernalia. “It’s perfect,” I answered with a secret thrill, yet feeling a little foolish. This was for Gibbon or Carlyle, rather than for my pot-boiling insignificancies. “If I can’t write masterpieces here, it’s certainly not your fault,” and I turned with gratitude to Mrs. Franklyn. She was looking straight at me, and there was a question in her small pale eyes I did not understand. Was she noting the effect upon me, I wondered?

“You’ll write here—perhaps a story about the house,” she said; “Thompson will bring you anything you want; you only have to ring.” She pointed to the electric bell on the central table, the wire running neatly down the leg. “No one has ever worked here before, and the library has been hardly used since it was put in. So there’s no previous atmosphere to affect your imagination—er—adversely.”

We laughed. “Bill isn’t that sort,” said my sister; while I wished they would go out and leave me to arrange my little nest and set to work.

I thought, of course, it was the huge listening library that made me feel so inconsiderable—the fifteen thousand silent, staring books, the solemn aisles, the deep, eloquent shelves. But when the women had gone and I was alone, the beginning of the truth crept over me, and I felt that first hint of disconsolateness which later became an imperative No. The mind shut down, images ceased to rise and flow. I read, made copious notes, but I wrote no single line at The Towers. Nothing completed itself there. Nothing happened.

The morning sunshine poured into the library through ten long narrow windows; birds were singing; the autumn air, rich with a faint aroma of November melancholy that stung the imagination pleasantly, filled my antechamber. I looked out upon the undulating wooded landscape, hemmed in by the sweep of distant Downs, and I tasted a whiff of the sea. Rooks cawed as they floated above the elms, and there were lazy cows in the nearer meadows. A dozen times I tried to make my nest and settle down to work, and a dozen times, like a turning fastidious dog upon a hearthrug, I rearranged my chair and books and papers. The temptation of the Catalogue and shelves, of course, was accountable for much, yet not, I felt, for all. That was a manageable seduction. My work, moreover, was not of the creative kind that requires absolute absorption; it was the mere readable presentation of data I had accumulated. My notebooks were charged with facts ready to tabulate—facts, too, that interested me keenly. A mere effort of the will was necessary, and concentration of no difficult kind. Yet, somehow, it seemed beyond me: something for ever pushed the facts into disorder … and in the end I sat in the sunshine, dipping into a dozen books selected from the shelves outside, vexed with myself and only half-enjoying it. I felt restless. I wanted to be elsewhere.

And even while I read, attention wandered. Frances, Mabel, her late husband, the house and grounds, each in turn and sometimes all together, rose uninvited into the stream of thought, hindering any consecutive flow of work. In disconnected fashion came these pictures that interrupted concentration, yet presenting themselves as broken fragments of a bigger thing my mind already groped for unconsciously. They fluttered round this hidden thing of which they were aspects, fugitive interpretations, no one of them bringing complete revelation. There was no adjective, such as pleasant or unpleasant, that I could attach to what I felt, beyond that the result was unsettling. Vague as the atmosphere of a dream, it yet persisted, and I could not dissipate it. Isolated words or phrases in the lines I read sent questions scouring across my mind, sure sign that the deeper part of me was restless and ill at ease.

Rather trivial questions too—half-foolish interrogations, as of a puzzled or curious child: Why was my sister afraid to sleep alone, and why did her friend feel a similar repugnance, yet seek to conquer it? Why was the solid luxury of the house without comfort, its shelter without the sense of permanence? Why had Mrs. Franklyn asked us to come, artists, unbelieving vagabonds, types at the farthest possible remove from the saved sheep of her husband’s household? Had a reaction set in against the hysteria of her conversion? I had seen no signs of religious fervour in her; her atmosphere was that of an ordinary, high-minded woman, yet a woman of the world. Lifeless, though, a little, perhaps, now that I came to think about it: she had made no definite impression upon me of any kind. And my thoughts ran vaguely after this fragile clue.

Closing my book, I let them run. For, with this chance reflection came the discovery that I could not see her clearly—could not feel her soul, her personality. Her face, her small pale eyes, her dress and body and walk, all these stood before me like a photograph; but her Self evaded me. She seemed not there, lifeless, empty, a shadow—nothing. The picture was disagreeable, and I put it by. Instantly she melted out, as though light thought had conjured up a phantom that had no real existence. And at that very moment, singularly enough, my eye caught sight of her moving past the window, going silently along the gravel path. I watched her, a sudden new sensation gripping me. “There goes a prisoner,” my thought instantly ran, “one who wishes to escape, but cannot.”

What brought the outlandish notion, heaven only knows. The house was of her own choice, she was twice an heiress, and the world lay open at her feet. Yet she stayed—unhappy, frightened, caught. All this flashed over me, and made a sharp impression even before I had time to dismiss it as absurd. But a moment later explanation offered itself, though it seemed as farfetched as the original impression. My mind, being logical, was obliged to provide something, apparently. For Mrs. Franklyn, while dressed to go out, with thick walking-boots, a pointed stick, and a motor-cap tied on with a veil as for the windy lanes, was obviously content to go no farther than the little garden paths. The costume was a sham and a pretence. It was this, and her lithe, quick movements that suggested a caged creature—a creature tamed by fear and cruelty that cloaked themselves in kindness—pacing up and down, unable to realise why it got no farther, but always met the same bars in exactly the same place. The mind in her was barred.

I watched her go along the paths and down the steps from one terrace to another, until the laurels hid her altogether; and into this mere imagining of a moment came a hint of something slightly disagreeable, for which my mind, search as it would, found no explanation at all. I remembered then certain other little things. They dropped into the picture of their own accord. In a mind not deliberately hunting for clues, pieces of a puzzle sometimes come together in this way, bringing revelation, so that for a second there flashed across me, vanishing instantly again before I could consider it, a large, distressing thought that I can only describe vaguely as a Shadow. Dark and ugly, oppressive certainly it might be described, with something torn and dreadful about the edges that suggested pain and strife and terror. The interior of a prison with two rows of occupied condemned cells, seen years ago in New York, sprang to memory after it—the connection between the two impossible to surmise even. But the “certain other little things” mentioned above were these: that Mrs. Franklyn, in last night’s dinner talk, had always referred to “this house,” but never called it “home”; and had emphasised unnecessarily, for a well-bred woman, our “great kindness” in coming down to stay so long with her. Another time, in answer to my futile compliment about the “stately rooms,” she said quietly, “It is an enormous house for so small a party; but I stay here very little, and only till I get it straight again.” The three of us were going up the great staircase to bed as this was said, and, not knowing quite her meaning, I dropped the subject. It edged delicate ground, I felt. Frances added no word of her own. It now occurred to me abruptly that “stay” was the word made use of, when “live” would have been more natural. How insignificant to recall! Yet why did they suggest themselves just at this moment? … And, on going to Frances’s room to make sure she was not nervous or lonely, I realised abruptly, that Mrs. Franklyn, of course, had talked with her in a confidential sense that I, as a mere visiting brother, could not share. Frances had told me nothing. I might easily have wormed it out of her, had I not felt that for us to discuss further our hostess and her house merely because we were under the roof together, was not quite nice or loyal.

“I’ll call you, Bill, if I’m scared,” she had laughed as we parted, my room being just across the big corridor from her own. I had fallen asleep, thinking what in the world was meant by “getting it straight again.”

And now in my antechamber to the library, on the second morning, sitting among piles of foolscap and sheets of spotless blotting-paper, all useless to me, these slight hints came back and helped to frame the big, vague Shadow I have mentioned. Up to the neck in this Shadow, almost drowned, yet just treading water, stood the figure of my hostess in her walking costume. Frances and I seemed swimming to her aid. The Shadow was large enough to include both house and grounds, but farther than that I could not see. … Dismissing it, I fell to reading my purloined book again. Before I turned another page, however, another startling detail leaped out at me: the figure of Mrs. Franklyn in the Shadow was not living. It floated helplessly, like a doll or puppet that has no life in it. It was both pathetic and dreadful.

Any one who sits in reverie thus, of course, may see similar ridiculous pictures when the will no longer guides construction. The incongruities of dreams are thus explained. I merely record the picture as it came. That it remained by me for several days, just as vivid dreams do, is neither here nor there. I did not allow myself to dwell upon it. The curious thing, perhaps, is that from this moment I date my inclination, though not yet my desire, to leave. I purposely say “to leave.” I cannot quite remember when the word changed to that aggressive, frantic thing which is escape.

V

We were left delightfully to ourselves in this pretentious country mansion with the soul of a villa. Frances took up her painting again, and, the weather being propitious, spent hours out of doors, sketching flowers, trees and nooks of woodland, garden, even the house itself where bits of it peered suggestively across the orchards. Mrs. Franklyn seemed always busy about something or other, and never interfered with us except to propose motoring, tea in another part of the lawn, and so forth. She flitted everywhere, preoccupied, yet apparently doing nothing. The house engulfed her rather. No visitors called. For one thing, she was not supposed to be back from abroad yet; and for another, I think, the neighbourhood—her husband’s neighbourhood—was puzzled by her sudden cessation from good works. Brigades and temperance societies did not ask to hold their meetings in the big hall, and the vicar arranged the school-treats in another’s field without explanation. The full-length portrait in the dining-room, and the presence of the housekeeper with the “burnt” back-hair, indeed, were the only reminders of the man who once had lived here. Mrs. Marsh retained her place in silence, well-paid sinecure as it doubtless was, yet with no hint of that suppressed disapproval one might have expected from her. Indeed there was nothing positive to disapprove, since nothing “worldly” entered grounds or building. In her master’s lifetime she had been another “brand snatched from the burning,” and it had then been her custom to give vociferous “testimony” at the revival meetings where he adorned the platform and led in streams of prayer. I saw her sometimes on the stairs, hovering, wandering, half-watching and half-listening, and the idea came to me once that this woman somehow formed a link with the departed influence of her bigoted employer. She, alone among us, belonged to the house, and looked at home there. When I saw her talking—oh, with such correct and respectful mien—to Mrs. Franklyn, I had the feeling that for all her unaggressive attitude, she yet exerted some influence that sought to make her mistress stay in the building for ever—live there. She would prevent her escape, prevent her “getting it straight again,” thwart somehow her will to freedom, if she could. The idea in me was of the most fleeting kind. But another time, when I came down late at night to get a book from the library antechamber, and found her sitting in the hall—alone—the impression left upon me was the reverse of fleeting. I can never forget the vivid, disagreeable effect it produced upon me. What was she doing there at half-past eleven at night, all alone in the darkness? She was sitting upright, stiff, in a big chair below the clock. It gave me a turn. It was so incongruous and odd. She rose quietly as I turned the corner of the stairs, and asked me respectfully, her eyes cast down as usual, whether I had finished with the library, so that she might lock up. There was no more to it than that; but the picture stayed with me—unpleasantly.

These various impressions came to me at odd moments, of course, and not in a single sequence as I now relate them. I was hard at work before three days were past, not writing, as explained, but reading, making notes, and gathering material from the library for future use. It was in chance moments that these curious flashes came, catching me unawares with a touch of surprise that sometimes made me start. For they proved that my under-mind was still conscious of the Shadow, and that far away out of sight lay the cause of it that left me with a vague unrest, unsettled, seeking to “nest” in a place that did not want me. Only when this deeper part knows harmony, perhaps, can good brain work result, and my inability to write was thus explained. Certainly, I was always seeking for something here I could not find—an explanation that continually evaded me. Nothing but these trivial hints offered themselves. Lumped together, however, they had the effect of defining the Shadow a little. I became more and more aware of its very real existence. And, if I have made little mention of Frances and my hostess in this connection, it is because they contributed at first little or nothing towards the discovery of what this story tries to tell. Our life was wholly external, normal, quiet, and uneventful; conversation banal—Mrs. Franklyn’s conversation in particular. They said nothing that suggested revelation. Both were in this Shadow, and both knew that they were in it, but neither betrayed by word or act a hint of interpretation. They talked privately, no doubt, but of that I can report no details.

And so it was that, after ten days of a very commonplace visit, I found myself looking straight into the face of a Strangeness that defied capture at close quarters. “There’s something here that never happens,” were the words that rose in my mind, “and that’s why none of us can speak of it.” And as I looked out of the window and watched the vulgar blackbirds, with toes turned in, boring out their worms, I realised sharply that even they, as indeed everything large and small in the house and grounds, shared this strangeness, and were twisted out of normal appearance because of it. Life, as expressed in the entire place, was crumpled, dwarfed, emasculated. God’s meanings here were crippled, His love of joy was stunted. Nothing in the garden danced or sang. There was hate in it. “The Shadow,” my thought hurried on to completion, “is a manifestation of hate; and hate is the Devil.” And then I sat back frightened in my chair, for I knew that I had partly found the truth.

Leaving my books I went out into the open. The sky was overcast, yet the day by no means gloomy, for a soft, diffused light oozed through the clouds and turned all things warm and almost summery. But I saw the grounds now in their nakedness because I understood. Hate means strife, and the two together weave the robe that terror wears. Having no so-called religious beliefs myself, nor belonging to any set of dogmas called a creed, I could stand outside these feelings and observe. Yet they soaked into me sufficiently for me to grasp sympathetically what others, with more cabined souls (I flattered myself), might feel. That picture in the dining-room stalked everywhere, hid behind every tree, peered down upon me from the peaked ugliness of the bourgeois towers, and left the impress of its powerful hand upon every bed of flowers. “You must not do this, you must not do that,” went past me through the air. “You must not leave these narrow paths,” said the rigid iron railings of black. “You shall not walk here,” was written on the lawns. “Keep to the steps,” “Don’t pick the flowers; make no noise of laughter, singing, dancing,” was placarded all over the rose-garden, and “Trespassers will be—not prosecuted but—destroyed” hung from the crest of monkey-tree and holly. Guarding the ends of each artificial terrace stood gaunt, implacable policemen, warders, gaolers. “Come with us,” they chanted, “or be damned eternally.”

I remember feeling quite pleased with myself that I had discovered this obvious explanation of the prison-feeling the place breathed out. That the posthumous influence of heavy old Samuel Franklyn might be an inadequate solution did not occur to me. By “getting the place straight again,” his widow, of course, meant forgetting the glamour of fear and foreboding his depressing creed had temporarily forced upon her; and Frances, delicately-minded being, did not speak of it because it was the influence of the man her friend had loved. I felt lighter; a load was lifted from me. “To trace the unfamiliar to the familiar,” came back a sentence I had read somewhere, “is to understand.” It was a real relief. I could talk with Frances now, even with my hostess, no danger of treading clumsily. For the key was in my hands. I might even help to dissipate the Shadow, “to get it straight again.” It seemed, perhaps, our long invitation was explained!

I went into the house laughing—at myself a little. “Perhaps after all the artist’s outlook, with no hard and fast dogmas, is as narrow as the others! How small humanity is! And why is there no possible and true combination of all outlooks?”

The feeling of “unsettling” was very strong in me just then, in spite of my big discovery which was to clear everything up. And at that moment I ran into Frances on the stairs, with a portfolio of sketches under her arm.

It came across me then abruptly that, although she had worked a great deal since we came, she had shown me nothing. It struck me suddenly as odd, unnatural. The way she tried to pass me now confirmed my newborn suspicion that—well, that her results were hardly what they ought to be.

“Stand and deliver!” I laughed, stepping in front of her. “I’ve seen nothing you’ve done since you’ve been here, and as a rule you show me all your things. I believe they are atrocious and degrading!” Then my laughter froze.

She made a sly gesture to slip past me, and I almost decided to let her go, for the expression that flashed across her face shocked me. She looked uncomfortable and ashamed; the colour came and went a moment in her cheeks, making me think of a child detected in some secret naughtiness. It was almost fear.

“It’s because they’re not finished then?” I said, dropping the tone of banter, “or because they’re too good for me to understand?” For my criticism of painting, she told me, was crude and ignorant sometimes. “But you’ll let me see them later, won’t you?”

Frances, however, did not take the way of escape I offered. She changed her mind. She drew the portfolio from beneath her arm instead. “You can see them if you really want to, Bill,” she said quietly, and her tone reminded me of a nurse who says to a boy just grown out of childhood, “you are old enough now to look upon horror and ugliness—only I don’t advise it.”

“I do want to,” I said, and made to go downstairs with her. But, instead, she said in the same low voice as before, “Come up to my room, we shall be undisturbed there.” So I guessed that she had been on her way to show the paintings to our hostess, but did not care for us all three to see them together. My mind worked furiously.

“Mabel asked me to do them,” she explained in a tone of submissive horror, once the door was shut, “in fact, she begged it of me. You know how persistent she is in her quiet way. I—er—had to.”

She flushed and opened the portfolio on the little table by the window, standing behind me as I turned the sketches over—sketches of the grounds and trees and garden. In the first moment of inspection, however, I did not take in clearly why my sister’s sense of modesty had been offended. For my attention flashed a second elsewhere. Another bit of the puzzle had dropped into place, defining still further the nature of what I called “the Shadow.” Mrs. Franklyn, I now remembered, had suggested to me in the library that I might perhaps write something about the place, and I had taken it for one of her banal sentences and paid no further attention. I realised now that it was said in earnest. She wanted our interpretations, as expressed in our respective “talents,” painting and writing. Her invitation was explained. She left us to ourselves on purpose.

“I should like to tear them up,” Frances was whispering behind me with a shudder, “only I promised—” She hesitated a moment.

“Promised not to?” I asked with a queer feeling of distress, my eyes glued to the papers.

“Promised always to show them to her first,” she finished so low I barely caught it.

I have no intuitive, immediate grasp of the value of paintings; results come to me slowly, and though every one believes his own judgment to be good, I dare not claim that mine is worth more than that of any other layman. Frances had too often convicted me of gross ignorance and error. I can only say that I examined these sketches with a feeling of amazement that contained revulsion, if not actually horror and disgust. They were outrageous. I felt hot for my sister, and it was a relief to know she had moved across the room on some pretence or other, and did not examine them with me. Her talent, of course, is mediocre, yet she has her moments of inspiration—moments, that is to say, when a view of Beauty not normally her own flames divinely through her. And these interpretations struck me forcibly as being thus “inspired”—not her own. They were uncommonly well done; they were also atrocious. The meaning in them, however, was never more than hinted. There the unholy skill and power came in: they suggested so abominably, leaving most to the imagination. To find such significance in a bourgeois villa garden, and to interpret it with such delicate yet legible certainty, was a kind of symbolism that was sinister, even diabolical. The delicacy was her own, but the point of view was another’s. And the word that rose in my mind was not the gross description of “impure,” but the more fundamental qualification—“un-pure.”

In silence I turned the sketches over one by one, as a boy hurries through the pages of an evil book lest he be caught.

“What does Mabel do with them?” I asked presently in a low tone, as I neared the end. “Does she keep them?”

“She makes notes about them in a book and then destroys them,” was the reply from the end of the room. I heard a sigh of relief. “I’m glad you’ve seen them, Bill. I wanted you to—but was afraid to show them. You understand?”

“I understand,” was my reply, though it was not a question intended to be answered. All I understood really was that Mabel’s mind was as sweet and pure as my sister’s, and that she had some good reason for what she did. She destroyed the sketches, but first made notes! It was an interpretation of the place she sought. Brother-like, I felt resentment, though, that Frances should waste her time and talent, when she might be doing work that she could sell. Naturally, I felt other things as well. …

“Mabel pays me five guineas for each one,” I heard. “Absolutely insists.”

I stared at her stupidly a moment, bereft of speech or wit.

“I must either accept, or go away,” she went on calmly, but a little white. “I’ve tried everything. There was a scene the third day I was here—when I showed her my first result. I wanted to write to you, but hesitated—”

“It’s unintentional, then, on your part—forgive my asking it, Frances, dear?” I blundered, hardly knowing what to think or say. “Between the lines” of her letter came back to me. “I mean, you make the sketches in your ordinary way and—the result comes out of itself, so to speak?”

She nodded, throwing her hands out like a Frenchman. “We needn’t keep the money for ourselves, Bill. We can give it away, but—I must either accept or leave,” and she repeated the shrugging gesture. She sat down on the chair facing me, staring helplessly at the carpet.

“You say there was a scene?” I went on presently. “She insisted?”

“She begged me to continue,” my sister replied very quietly. “She thinks—that is, she has an idea or theory that there’s something about the place—something she can’t get at quite.” Frances stammered badly. She knew I did not encourage her wild theories.

“Something she feels—yes,” I helped her, more than curious.

“Oh, you know what I mean, Bill,” she said desperately. “That the place is saturated with some influence that she is herself too positive or too stupid to interpret. She’s trying to make herself negative and receptive, as she calls it, but can’t, of course, succeed. Haven’t you noticed how dull and impersonal and insipid she seems, as though she had no personality? She thinks impressions will come to her that way. But they don’t—”

“Naturally.”

“So she’s trying me—us—what she calls the sensitive and impressionable artistic temperament. She says that until she is sure exactly what this influence is, she can’t fight it, turn it out, ‘get the house straight,’ as she phrases it.”

Remembering my own singular impressions, I felt more lenient than I might otherwise have done. I tried to keep impatience out of my voice.

“And this influence, what—whose is it?”

We used the pronoun that followed in the same breath, for I answered my own question at the same moment as she did:

“His.” Our heads nodded involuntarily towards the floor, the dining-room being directly underneath.

And my heart sank, my curiosity died away on the instant, I felt bored. A commonplace haunted house was the last thing in the world to amuse or interest me. The mere thought exasperated, with its suggestions of imagination, overwrought nerves, hysteria, and the rest. Mingled with my other feelings was certainly disappointment. To see a figure or feel a “presence,” and report from day to day strange incidents to each other would be a form of weariness I could never tolerate.

“But really, Frances,” I said firmly, after a moment’s pause, “it’s too farfetched, this explanation. A curse, you know, belongs to the ghost stories of early Victorian days.” And only my positive conviction that there was something after all worth discovering, and that it most certainly was not this, prevented my suggesting that we terminate our visit forthwith, or as soon as we decently could. “This is not a haunted house, whatever it is,” I concluded somewhat vehemently, bringing my hand down upon her odious portfolio.

My sister’s reply revived my curiosity sharply.

“I was waiting for you to say that. Mabel says exactly the same. He is in it—but it’s something more than that alone, something far bigger and more complicated.” Her sentence seemed to indicate the sketches, and though I caught the inference I did not take it up, having no desire to discuss them with her just then, indeed, if ever.

I merely stared at her and listened. Questions, I felt sure, would be of little use. It was better she should say her thought in her own way.

“He is one influence, the most recent,” she went on slowly, and always very calmly, “but there are others—deeper layers, as it were—underneath. If his were the only one, something would happen. But nothing ever does happen. The others hinder and prevent—as though each were struggling to predominate.”

I had felt it already myself. The idea was rather horrible. I shivered.

“That’s what is so ugly about it—that nothing ever happens,” she said. “There is this endless anticipation—always on the dry edge of a result that never materialises. It is torture. Mabel is at her wits’ end, you see. And when she begged me—what I felt about my sketches—I mean—” She stammered badly as before.

I stopped her. I had judged too hastily. That queer symbolism in her paintings, pagan and yet not innocent, was, I understood, the result of mixture. I did not pretend to understand, but at least I could be patient. I consequently held my peace. We did talk on a little longer, but it was more general talk that avoided successfully our hostess, the paintings, wild theories, and him—until at length the emotion Frances had hitherto so successfully kept under burst vehemently forth again. It had hidden between her calm sentences, as it had hidden between the lines of her letter. It swept her now from head to foot, packed tight in the thing she then said.

“Then, Bill, if it is not an ordinary haunted house,” she asked, “what is it?”

The words were commonplace enough. The emotion was in the tone of her voice that trembled; in the gesture she made, leaning forward and clasping both hands upon her knees, and in the slight blanching of her cheeks as her brave eyes asked the question and searched my own with anxiety that bordered upon panic. In that moment she put herself under my protection. I winced.

“And why,” she added, lowering her voice to a still and furtive whisper, “does nothing ever happen? If only,”—this with great emphasis—“something would happen—break this awful tension—bring relief. It’s the waiting I cannot stand.” And she shivered all over as she said it, a touch of wildness in her eyes.

I would have given much to have made a true and satisfactory answer. My mind searched frantically for a moment, but in vain. There lay no sufficient answer in me. I felt what she felt, though with differences. No conclusive explanation lay within reach. Nothing happened. Eager as I was to shoot the entire business into the rubbish heap where ignorance and superstition discharge their poisonous weeds, I could not honestly accomplish this. To treat Frances as a child, and merely “explain away” would be to strain her confidence in my protection, so affectionately claimed. It would further be dishonest to myself—weak, besides—to deny that I had also felt the strain and tension even as she did. While my mind continued searching, I returned her stare in silence; and Frances then, with more honesty and insight than my own, gave suddenly the answer herself—an answer whose truth and adequacy, so far as they went, I could not readily gainsay:

“I think, Bill, because it is too big to happen here—to happen anywhere, indeed, all at once—and too awful!”

To have tossed the sentence aside as nonsense, argued it away, proved that it was really meaningless, would have been easy—at any other time or in any other place; and, had the past week brought me none of the vivid impressions it had brought me, this is doubtless what I should have done. My narrowness again was proved. We understand in others only what we have in ourselves. But her explanation, in a measure, I knew was true. It hinted at the strife and struggle that my notion of a Shadow had seemed to cover thinly.

“Perhaps,” I murmured lamely, waiting in vain for her to say more. “But you said just now that you felt the thing was ‘in layers,’ as it were. Do you mean each one—each influence—fighting for the upper hand?”

I used her phraseology to conceal my own poverty. Terminology, after all, was nothing, provided we could reach the idea itself.

Her eyes said yes. She had her clear conception, arrived at independently, as was her way. And, unlike her sex, she kept it clear, unsmothered by too many words.

“One set of influences gets at me, another gets at you. It’s according to our temperaments, I think.” She glanced significantly at the vile portfolio. “Sometimes they are mixed—and therefore false. There has always been in me, more than in you, the pagan thing, perhaps, though never, thank God, like that.”

The frank confession of course invited my own, as it was meant to do. Yet it was difficult to find the words.

“What I have felt in this place, Frances, I honestly can hardly tell you, because—er—my impressions have not arranged themselves in any definite form I can describe. The strife, the agony of vainly-sought escape, and the unrest—a sort of prison atmosphere—this I have felt at different times and with varying degrees of strength. But I find, as yet, no final label to attach. I couldn’t say pagan, Christian, or anything like that, I mean, as you do. As with the blind and deaf, you may have an intensification of certain senses denied to me, or even another sense altogether in embryo—”

“Perhaps,” she stopped me, anxious to keep to the point, “you feel it as Mabel does. She feels the whole thing complete.”

“That also is possible,” I said very slowly. I was thinking behind my words. Her odd remark that it was “big and awful” came back upon me as true. A vast sensation of distress and discomfort swept me suddenly. Pity was in it, and a fierce contempt, a savage, bitter anger as well. Fury against some sham authority was part of it.

“Frances,” I said, caught unawares, and dropping all pretence, “what in the world can it be?” I looked hard at her. For some minutes neither of us spoke.

“Have you felt no desire to interpret it?” she asked presently.

“Mabel did suggest my writing something about the house,” was my reply, “but I’ve felt nothing imperative. That sort of writing is not my line, you know. My only feeling,” I added, noticing that she waited for more, “is the impulse to explain, discover, get it out of me somehow, and so get rid of it. Not by writing, though—as yet.” And again I repeated my former question: “What in the world do you think it is?” My voice had become involuntarily hushed. There was awe in it.

Her answer, given with slow emphasis, brought back all my reserve: the phraseology provoked me rather:—

“Whatever it is, Bill, it is not of God.”

I got up to go downstairs. I believe I shrugged my shoulders, “Would you like to leave, Frances? Shall we go back to town?” I suggested this at the door, and hearing no immediate reply, I turned back to look. Frances was sitting with her head bowed over and buried in her hands. The attitude horribly suggested tears. No woman, I realised, can keep back the pressure of strong emotion as long as Frances had done, without ending in a fluid collapse. I waited a moment uneasily, longing to comfort, yet afraid to act—and in this way discovered the existence of the appalling emotion in myself, hitherto but half guessed. At all costs a scene must be prevented: it would involve such exaggeration and overstatement. Brutally, such is the weakness of the ordinary man, I turned the handle to go out, but my sister then raised her head. The sunlight caught her face, framed untidily in its auburn hair, and I saw her wonderful expression with a start. Pity, tenderness and sympathy shone in it like a flame. It was undeniable. There shone through all her features the imperishable love and yearning to sacrifice self for others which I have seen in only one type of human being. It was the great mother look.

“We must stay by Mabel and help her get it straight,” she whispered, making the decision for us both.

I murmured agreement. Abashed and half ashamed, I stole softly from the room and went out into the grounds. And the first thing clearly realised when alone was this: that the long scene between us was without definite result. The exchange of confidence was really nothing but hints and vague suggestion. We had decided to stay, but it was a negative decision not to leave rather than a positive action. All our words and questions, our guesses, inferences, explanations, our most subtle allusions and insinuations, even the odious paintings themselves, were without definite result. Nothing had happened.

VI

And instinctively, once alone, I made for the places where she had painted her extraordinary pictures; I tried to see what she had seen. Perhaps, now that she had opened my mind to another view, I should be sensitive to some similar interpretation—and possibly by way of literary expression. If I were to write about the place, I asked myself, how should I treat it? I deliberately invited an interpretation in the way that came easiest to me—writing.

But in this case there came no such revelation. Looking closely at the trees and flowers, the bits of lawn and terrace, the rose-garden and corner of the house where the flaming creeper hung so thickly, I discovered nothing of the odious, unpure thing her colour and grouping had unconsciously revealed. At first, that is, I discovered nothing. The reality stood there, commonplace and ugly, side by side with her distorted version of it that lay in my mind. It seemed incredible. I tried to force it, but in vain. My imagination, ploughed less deeply than hers, or to another pattern, grew different seed. Where I saw the gross soul of an overgrown suburban garden, inspired by the spirit of a vulgar, rich revivalist who loved to preach damnation, she saw this rush of pagan liberty and joy, this strange licence of primitive flesh which, tainted by the other, produced the adulterated, vile result.

Certain things, however, gradually then became apparent, forcing themselves upon me, willy nilly. They came slowly, but overwhelmingly. Not that facts had changed, or natural details altered in the grounds—this was impossible—but that I noticed for the first time various aspects I had not noticed before—trivial enough, yet for me, just then, significant. Some I remembered from previous days; others I saw now as I wandered to and fro, uneasy, uncomfortable—almost, it seemed, watched by some one who took note of my impressions. The details were so foolish, the total result so formidable. I was half aware that others tried hard to make me see. It was deliberate. My sister’s phrase, “one layer got at me, another gets at you,” flashed, undesired, upon me.

For I saw, as with the eyes of a child, what I can only call a goblin garden—house, grounds, trees, and flowers belonged to a goblin world that children enter through the pages of their fairy tales. And what made me first aware of it was the whisper of the wind behind me, so that I turned with a sudden start, feeling that something had moved closer. An old ash tree, ugly and ungainly, had been artificially trained to form an arbour at one end of the terrace that was a tennis lawn, and the leaves of it now went rustling together, swishing as they rose and fell. I looked at the ash tree, and felt as though I had passed that moment between doors into this goblin garden that crouched behind the real one. Below, at a deeper layer perhaps, lay hidden the one my sister had entered.

To deal with my own, however, I call it goblin, because an odd aspect of the quaint in it yet never quite achieved the picturesque. Grotesque, probably, is the truer word, for everywhere I noticed, and for the first time, this slight alteration of the natural due either to the exaggeration of some detail, or to its suppression, generally, I think, to the latter. Life everywhere appeared to me as blocked from the full delivery of its sweet and lovely message. Some counter influence stopped it—suppression; or sent it awry—exaggeration. The house itself, mere expression, of course, of a narrow, limited mind, was sheer ugliness; it required no further explanation. With the grounds and garden, so far as shape and general plan were concerned, this was also true; but that trees and flowers and other natural details should share the same deficiency perplexed my logical soul, and even dismayed it. I stood and stared, then moved about, and stood and stared again. Everywhere was this mockery of a sinister, unfinished aspect. I sought in vain to recover my normal point of view. My mind had found this goblin garden and wandered to and fro in it, unable to escape.

The change was in myself, of course, and so trivial were the details which illustrated it, that they sound absurd, thus mentioned one by one. For me, they proved it, is all I can affirm. The goblin touch lay plainly everywhere: in the forms of the trees, planted at neat intervals along the lawns; in this twisted ash that rustled just behind me; in the shadow of the gloomy wellingtonias, whose sweeping skirts obscured the grass; but especially, I noticed, in the tops and crests of them. For here, the delicate, graceful curves of last year’s growth seemed to shrink back into themselves. None of them pointed upwards. Their life had failed and turned aside just when it should have become triumphant. The character of a tree reveals itself chiefly at the extremities, and it was precisely here that they all drooped and achieved this hint of goblin distortion—in the growth, that is, of the last few years. What ought to have been fairy, joyful, natural, was instead uncomely to the verge of the grotesque. Spontaneous expression was arrested. My mind perceived a goblin garden, and was caught in it. The place grimaced at me.

With the flowers it was similar, though far more difficult to detect in detail for description. I saw the smaller vegetable growth as impish, half-malicious. Even the terraces sloped ill, as though their ends had sagged since they had been so lavishly constructed; their varying angles gave a queerly bewildering aspect to their sequence that was unpleasant to the eye. One might wander among their deceptive lengths and get lost—lost among open terraces!—with the house quite close at hand. Unhomely seemed the entire garden, unable to give repose, restlessness in it everywhere, almost strife, and discord certainly.

Moreover, the garden grew into the house, the house into the garden, and in both was this idea of resistance to the natural—the spirit that says No to joy. All over it I was aware of the effort to achieve another end, the struggle to burst forth and escape into free, spontaneous expression that should be happy and natural, yet the effort for ever frustrated by the weight of this dark shadow that rendered it abortive. Life crawled aside into a channel that was a cul-de-sac, then turned horribly upon itself. Instead of blossom and fruit, there were weeds. This approach of life I was conscious of—then dismal failure. There was no fulfilment. Nothing happened.

And so, through this singular mood, I came a little nearer to understand the unpure thing that had stammered out into expression through my sister’s talent. For the unpure is merely negative; it has no existence; it is but the cramped expression of what is true, stammering its way brokenly over false boundaries that seek to limit and confine. Great, full expression of anything is pure, whereas here was only the incomplete, unfinished, and therefore ugly. There was strife and pain and desire to escape. I found myself shrinking from house and grounds as one shrinks from the touch of the mentally arrested, those in whom life has turned awry. There was almost mutilation in it.

Past items, too, now flocked to confirm this feeling that I walked, liberty captured and half-maimed, in a monstrous garden. I remembered days of rain that refreshed the countryside, but left these grounds, cracked with the summer heat, unsatisfied and thirsty; and how the big winds, that cleaned the woods and fields elsewhere, crawled here with difficulty through the dense foliage that protected The Towers from the North and West and East. They were ineffective, sluggish currents. There was no real wind. Nothing happened. I began to realise—far more clearly than in my sister’s fanciful explanation about “layers”—that here were many contrary influences at work, mutually destructive of one another. House and grounds were not haunted merely; they were the arena of past thinking and feeling, perhaps of terrible, impure beliefs, each striving to suppress the others, yet no one of them achieving supremacy because no one of them was strong enough, no one of them was true. Each, moreover, tried to win me over, though only one was able to reach my mind at all. For some obscure reason—possibly because my temperament had a natural bias towards the grotesque—it was the goblin layer. With me, it was the line of least resistance. …

In my own thoughts this “goblin garden” revealed, of course, merely my personal interpretation. I felt now objectively what long ago my mind had felt subjectively. My work, essential sign of spontaneous life with me, had stopped dead; production had become impossible. I stood now considerably closer to the cause of this sterility. The Cause, rather, turned bolder, had stepped insolently nearer. Nothing happened anywhere; house, garden, mind alike were barren, abortive, torn by the strife of frustrate impulse, ugly, hateful, sinful. Yet behind it all was still the desire of life—desire to escape—accomplish. Hope—an intolerable hope—I became startlingly aware—crowned torture.

And, realising this, though in some part of me where Reason lost her hold, there rose upon me then another and a darker thing that caught me by the throat and made me shrink with a sense of revulsion that touched actual loathing. I knew instantly whence it came, this wave of abhorrence and disgust, for even while I saw red and felt revolt rise in me, it seemed that I grew partially aware of the layer next below the goblin. I perceived the existence of this deeper stratum. One opened the way for the other, as it were. There were so many, yet all interrelated; to admit one was to clear the way for all. If I lingered I should be caught—horribly. They struggled with such violence for supremacy among themselves, however, that this latest uprising was instantly smothered and crushed back, though not before a glimpse had been revealed to me, and the redness in my thoughts transferred itself to colour my surroundings thickly and appallingly—with blood. This lurid aspect drenched the garden, smeared the terraces, lent to the very soil a tinge as of sacrificial rites, that choked the breath in me, while it seemed to fix me to the earth my feet so longed to leave. It was so revolting that at the same time I felt a dreadful curiosity as of fascination—I wished to stay. Between these contrary impulses I think I actually reeled a moment, transfixed by a fascination of the Awful. Through the lighter goblin veil I felt myself sinking down, down, down into this turgid layer that was so much more violent and so much more ancient. The upper layer, indeed, seemed fairy by comparison with this terror born of the lust for blood, thick with the anguish of human sacrificial victims.

Upper! Then I was already sinking; my feet were caught; I was actually in it! What atavistic strain, hidden deep within me, had been touched into vile response, giving this flash of intuitive comprehension, I cannot say. The coatings laid on by civilisation are probably thin enough in all of us. I made a supreme effort. The sun and wind came back. I could almost swear I opened my eyes. Something very atrocious surged back into the depths, carrying with it a thought of tangled woods, of big stones standing in a circle, motionless white figures, the one form bound with ropes, and the ghastly gleam of the knife. Like smoke upon a battlefield, it rolled away. …

I was standing on the gravel path below the second terrace when the familiar goblin garden danced back again, doubly grotesque now, doubly mocking, yet, by way of contrast, almost welcome. My glimpse into the depths was momentary, it seems, and had passed utterly away. The common world rushed back with a sense of glad relief, yet ominous now for ever, I felt, for the knowledge of what its past had built upon. In street, in theatre, in the festivities of friends, in music-room or playing-field, even indeed in church—how could the memory of what I had seen and felt not leave its hideous trace? The very structure of my Thought, it seemed to me, was stained. What has been thought by others can never be obliterated until …

With a start my reverie broke and fled, scattered by a violent sound that I recognised for the first time in my life as wholly desirable. The returning motor meant that my hostess was back. Yet, so urgent had been my temporary obsession, that my first presentation of her was—well, not as I knew her now. Floating along with a face of anguished torture I saw Mabel, a mere effigy captured by others’ thinking, pass down into those depths of fire and blood that only just had closed beneath my feet. She dipped away. She vanished, her fading eyes turned to the last towards some saviour who had failed her. And that strange intolerable hope was in her face.

The mystery of the place was pretty thick about me just then. It was the fall of dusk, and the ghost of slanting sunshine was as unreal as though badly painted. The garden stood at attention all about me. I cannot explain it, but I can tell it, I think, exactly as it happened, for it remains vivid in me for ever—that, for the first time, something almost happened, myself apparently the combining link through which it pressed towards delivery.

I had already turned towards the house. In my mind were pictures—not actual thoughts—of the motor, tea on the verandah, my sister, Mabel—when there came behind me this tumultuous, awful rush—as I left the garden. The ugliness, the pain, the striving to escape, the whole negative and suppressed agony that was the Place, focused that second into a concentrated effort to produce a result. It was a blinding tempest of long-frustrate desire that heaved at me, surging appallingly behind me like an anguished mob. I was in the act of crossing the frontier into my normal self again, when it came, catching fearfully at my skirts. I might use an entire dictionary of descriptive adjectives yet come no nearer to it than this—the conception of a huge assemblage determined to escape with me, or to snatch me back among themselves. My legs trembled for an instant, and I caught my breath—then turned and ran as fast as possible up the ugly terraces.

At the same instant, as though the clanging of an iron gate cut short the unfinished phrase, I thought the beginning of an awful thing:

“The Damned …”

Like this it rushed after me from that goblin garden that had sought to keep me:

“The Damned!”

For there was sound in it. I know full well it was subjective, not actually heard at all; yet somehow sound was in it—a great volume, roaring and booming thunderously, far away, and below me. The sentence dipped back into the depths that gave it birth, unfinished. Its completion was prevented. As usual, nothing happened. But it drove behind me like a hurricane as I ran towards the house, and the sound of it I can only liken to those terrible undertones you may hear standing beside Niagara. They lie behind the mere crash of the falling flood, within it somehow, not audible to all—felt rather than definitely heard.

It seemed to echo back from the surface of those sagging terraces as I flew across their sloping ends, for it was somehow underneath them. It was in the rustle of the wind that stirred the skirts of the drooping wellingtonias. The beds of formal flowers passed it on to the creepers, red as blood, that crept over the unsightly building. Into the structure of the vulgar and forbidding house it sank away; The Towers took it home. The uncomely doors and windows seemed almost like mouths that had uttered the words themselves, and on the upper floors at that very moment I saw two maids in the act of closing them again.

And on the verandah, as I arrived breathless, and shaken in my soul, Frances and Mabel, standing by the tea-table, looked up to greet me. In the faces of both were clearly legible the signs of shock. They watched me coming, yet so full of their own distress that they hardly noticed the state in which I came. In the face of my hostess, however, I read another and a bigger thing than in the face of Frances. Mabel knew. She had experienced what I had experienced. She had heard that awful sentence I had heard, but heard it not for the first time; heard it, moreover, I verily believe, complete and to its dreadful end.

“Bill, did you hear that curious noise just now?” Frances asked it sharply before I could say a word. Her manner was confused; she looked straight at me; and there was a tremor in her voice she could not hide.

“There’s wind about,” I said, “wind in the trees and sweeping round the walls. It’s risen rather suddenly.” My voice faltered rather.

“No. It wasn’t wind,” she insisted, with a significance meant for me alone, but badly hidden. “It was more like distant thunder, we thought. How you ran too!” she added. “What a pace you came across the terraces!”

I knew instantly from the way she said it that they both had already heard the sound before and were anxious to know if I had heard it, and how. My interpretation was what they sought.

“It was a curiously deep sound, I admit. It may have been big guns at sea,” I suggested, “forts or cruisers practising. The coast isn’t so very far, and with the wind in the right direction—”

The expression on Mabel’s face stopped me dead.

“Like huge doors closing,” she said softly in her colourless voice, “enormous metal doors shutting against a mass of people clamouring to get out.” The gravity, the note of hopelessness in her tones, was shocking.

Frances had gone into the house the instant Mabel began to speak. “I’m cold,” she had said; “I think I’ll get a shawl.” Mabel and I were alone. I believe it was the first time we had been really alone since I arrived. She looked up from the teacups, fixing her pallid eyes on mine. She had made a question of the sentence.

“You hear it like that?” I asked innocently. I purposely used the present tense.

She changed her stare from one eye to the other; it was absolutely expressionless. My sister’s step sounded on the floor of the room behind us.

“If only—” Mabel began, then stopped, and my own feelings leaping out instinctively completed the sentence I felt was in her mind:

“⸺something would happen.”

She instantly corrected me. I had caught her thought, yet somehow phrased it wrongly.

“We could escape!” She lowered her tone a little, saying it hurriedly. The “we” amazed and horrified me; but something in her voice and manner struck me utterly dumb. There was ice and terror in it. It was a dying woman speaking—a lost and hopeless soul.

In that atrocious moment I hardly noticed what was said exactly, but I remember that my sister returned with a grey shawl about her shoulders, and that Mabel said, in her ordinary voice again, “It is chilly, yes; let’s have tea inside,” and that two maids, one of them the grenadier, speedily carried the loaded trays into the morning-room and put a match to the logs in the great open fireplace. It was, after all, foolish to risk the sharp evening air, for dusk was falling steadily, and even the sunshine of the day just fading could not turn autumn into summer. I was the last to come in. Just as I left the verandah a large black bird swooped down in front of me past the pillars; it dropped from overhead, swerved abruptly to one side as it caught sight of me, and flapped heavily towards the shrubberies on the left of the terraces, where it disappeared into the gloom. It flew very low, very close. And it startled me, I think because in some way it seemed like my Shadow materialised—as though the dark horror that was rising everywhere from house and garden, then settling back so thickly yet so imperceptibly upon us all, were incarnated in that whirring creature that passed between the daylight and the coming night.

I stood a moment, wondering if it would appear again, before I followed the others indoors, and as I was in the act of closing the windows after me, I caught a glimpse of a figure on the lawn. It was some distance away, on the other side of the shrubberies, in fact where the bird had vanished. But in spite of the twilight that half magnified, half obscured it, the identity was unmistakable. I knew the housekeeper’s stiff walk too well to be deceived. “Mrs. Marsh taking the air,” I said to myself. I felt the necessity of saying it, and I wondered why she was doing so at this particular hour. If I had other thoughts they were so vague, and so quickly and utterly suppressed, that I cannot recall them sufficiently to relate them here.

And, once indoors, it was to be expected that there would come explanation, discussion, conversation, at any rate, regarding the singular noise and its cause, some uttered evidence of the mood that had been strong enough to drive us all inside. Yet there was none. Each of us purposely, and with various skill, ignored it. We talked little, and when we did it was of anything in the world but that. Personally, I experienced a touch of that same bewilderment which had come over me during my first talk with Frances on the evening of my arrival, for I recall now the acute tension, and the hope, yet dread, that one or other of us must sooner or later introduce the subject. It did not happen, however; no reference was made to it even remotely. It was the presence of Mabel, I felt positive, that prohibited. As soon might we have discussed Death in the bedroom of a dying woman.

The only scrap of conversation I remember, where all was ordinary and commonplace, was when Mabel spoke casually to the grenadier asking why Mrs. Marsh had omitted to do something or other—what it was I forget—and that the maid replied respectfully that “Mrs. Marsh was very sorry, but her ’and still pained her.” I enquired, though so casually that I scarcely know what prompted the words, whether she had injured herself severely, and the reply, “She upset a lamp and burnt herself,” was said in a tone that made me feel my curiosity was indiscreet, “but she always has an excuse for not doing things she ought to do.” The little bit of conversation remained with me, and I remember particularly the quick way Frances interrupted and turned the talk upon the delinquencies of servants in general, telling incidents of her own at our flat with a volubility that perhaps seemed forced, and that certainly did not encourage general talk as it may have been intended to do. We lapsed into silence immediately she finished.

But for all our care and all our calculated silence, each knew that something had, in these last moments, come very close; it had brushed us in passing; it had retired; and I am inclined to think now that the large dark thing I saw, riding the dusk, probably bird of prey, was in some sense a symbol of it in my mind—that actually there had been no bird at all, I mean, but that my mood of apprehension and dismay had formed the vivid picture in my thoughts. It had swept past us, it had retreated, but it was now, at this moment, in hiding very close. And it was watching us.

Perhaps, too, it was mere coincidence that I encountered Mrs. Marsh, his housekeeper, several times that evening in the short interval between tea and dinner, and that on each occasion the sight of this gaunt, half-saturnine woman fed my prejudice against her. Once, on my way to the telephone, I ran into her just where the passage is somewhat jammed by a square table carrying the Chinese gong, a grandfather’s clock and a box of croquet mallets. We both gave way, then both advanced, then again gave way—simultaneously. It seemed impossible to pass. We stepped with decision to the same side, finally colliding in the middle, while saying those futile little things, half apology, half excuse, that are inevitable at such times. In the end she stood upright against the wall for me to pass, taking her place against the very door I wished to open. It was ludicrous.

“Excuse me—I was just going in—to telephone,” I explained. And she sidled off, murmuring apologies, but opening the door for me while she did so. Our hands met a moment on the handle. There was a second’s awkwardness—it was so stupid. I remembered her injury, and by way of something to say, I enquired after it. She thanked me; it was entirely healed now, but it might have been much worse; and there was something about the “mercy of the Lord” that I didn’t quite catch. While telephoning, however—a London call, and my attention focused on it—I realised sharply that this was the first time I had spoken with her; also, that I had—touched her.

It happened to be a Sunday, and the lines were clear. I got my connection quickly, and the incident was forgotten while my thoughts went up to London. On my way upstairs, then, the woman came back into my mind, so that I recalled other things about her—how she seemed all over the house, in unlikely places often; how I had caught her sitting in the hall alone that night; how she was for ever coming and going with her lugubrious visage and that untidy hair at the back that had made me laugh three years ago with the idea that it looked singed or burnt; and how the impression on my first arrival at The Towers was that this woman somehow kept alive, though its evidence was outwardly suppressed, the influence of her late employer and of his sombre teachings. Somewhere with her was associated the idea of punishment, vindictiveness, revenge. I remembered again suddenly my odd notion that she sought to keep her present mistress here, a prisoner in this bleak and comfortless house, and that really, in spite of her obsequious silence, she was intensely opposed to the change of thought that had reclaimed Mabel to a happier view of life.

All this in a passing second flashed in review before me, and I discovered, or at any rate reconstructed, the real Mrs. Marsh. She was decidedly in the Shadow. More, she stood in the forefront of it, stealthily leading an assault, as it were, against The Towers and its occupants, as though, consciously or unconsciously, she laboured incessantly to this hateful end.

I can only judge that some state of nervousness in me permitted the series of insignificant thoughts to assume this dramatic shape, and that what had gone before prepared the way and led her up at the head of so formidable a procession. I relate it exactly as it came to me. My nerves were doubtless somewhat on edge by now. Otherwise I should hardly have been a prey to the exaggeration at all. I seemed open to so many strange impressions.

Nothing else, perhaps, can explain my ridiculous conversation with her, when, for the third time that evening, I came suddenly upon the woman halfway down the stairs, standing by an open window as if in the act of listening. She was dressed in black, a black shawl over her square shoulders and black gloves on her big, broad hands. Two black objects, prayer-books apparently, she clasped, and on her head she wore a bonnet with shaking beads of jet. At first I did not know her, as I came running down upon her from the landing; it was only when she stood aside to let me pass that I saw her profile against the tapestry and recognised Mrs. Marsh. And to catch her on the front stairs, dressed like this, struck me as incongruous—impertinent. I paused in my dangerous descent. Through the opened window came the sound of bells—church bells—a sound more depressing to me than superstition, and as nauseating. Though the action was ill-judged, I obeyed the sudden prompting—was it a secret desire to attack, perhaps?—and spoke to her.

“Been to church, I suppose, Mrs. Marsh?” I said. “Or just going, perhaps?”

Her face, as she looked up a second to reply, was like an iron doll that moved its lips and turned its eyes, but made no other imitation of life at all.

“Some of us still goes, sir,” she said unctuously.

It was respectful enough, yet the implied judgment of the rest of the world made me almost angry. A deferential insolence lay behind the affected meekness.

“For those who believe no doubt it is helpful,” I smiled. “True religion brings peace and happiness, I’m sure—joy, Mrs. Marsh, joy!” I found keen satisfaction in the emphasis.

She looked at me like a knife. I cannot describe the implacable thing that shone in her fixed, stern eyes, nor the shadow of felt darkness that stole across her face. She glittered. I felt hate in her. I knew—she knew too—who was in the thoughts of us both at that moment.

She replied softly, never forgetting her place for an instant:

“There is joy, sir—in ’eaven—over one sinner that repenteth, and in church there goes up prayer to Gawd for those ’oo—well, for the others, sir, ’oo—”

She cut short her sentence thus. The gloom about her as she said it was like the gloom about a hearse, a tomb, a darkness of great hopeless dungeons. My tongue ran on of itself with a kind of bitter satisfaction:

“We must believe there are no others, Mrs. Marsh. Salvation, you know, would be such a failure if there were. No merciful, all-foreseeing God could ever have devised such a fearful plan—”

Her voice, interrupting me, seemed to rise out of the bowels of the earth:

“They rejected the salvation when it was hoffered to them, sir, on earth.”

“But you wouldn’t have them tortured for ever because of one mistake in ignorance,” I said, fixing her with my eye. “Come now, would you, Mrs. Marsh? No God worth worshipping could permit such cruelty. Think a moment what it means.”

She stared at me, a curious expression in her stupid eyes. It seemed to me as though the “woman” in her revolted, while yet she dared not suffer her grim belief to trip. That is, she would willingly have had it otherwise but for a terror that prevented.

“We may pray for them, sir, and we do—we may ’ope.” She dropped her eyes to the carpet.

“Good, good!” I put in cheerfully, sorry now that I had spoken at all. “That’s more hopeful, at any rate, isn’t it?”

She murmured something about Abraham’s bosom, and the “time of salvation not being for ever,” as I tried to pass her. Then a half gesture that she made stopped me. There was something more she wished to say—to ask. She looked up furtively. In her eyes I saw the “woman” peering out through fear.

“Per’aps, sir,” she faltered, as though lightning must strike her dead, “per’aps, would you think, a drop of cold water, given in His name, might moisten—?”

But I stopped her, for the foolish talk had lasted long enough.

“Of course,” I exclaimed, “of course. For God is love, remember, and love means charity, tolerance, sympathy, and sparing others pain,” and I hurried past her, determined to end the outrageous conversation for which yet I knew myself entirely to blame. Behind me, she stood stock-still for several minutes, half bewildered, half alarmed, as I suspected. I caught the fragment of another sentence, one word of it, rather—“punishment”—but the rest escaped me. Her arrogance and condescending tolerance exasperated me, while I was at the same time secretly pleased that I might have touched some string of remorse or sympathy in her after all. Her belief was iron; she dared not let it go; yet somewhere underneath there lurked the germ of a wholesome revulsion. She would help “them”—if she dared. Her question proved it.

Half ashamed of myself, I turned and crossed the hall quickly lest I should be tempted to say more, and in me was a disagreeable sensation as though I had just left the Incurable Ward of some great hospital. A reaction caught me as of nausea. Ugh! I wanted such people cleansed by fire. They seemed to me as centres of contamination whose vicious thoughts flowed out to stain God’s glorious world. I saw myself, Frances, Mabel too especially, on the rack, while that odious figure of cruelty and darkness stood over us and ordered the awful handles turned in order that we might be “saved”—forced, that is, to think and believe exactly as she thought and believed.

I found relief for my somewhat childish indignation by letting myself loose upon the organ then. The flood of Bach and Beethoven brought back the sense of proportion. It proved, however, at the same time that there had been this growth of distortion in me, and that it had been provided apparently by my closer contact—for the first time—with that funereal personality, the woman who, like her master, believed that all holding views of God that differed from her own, must be damned eternally. It gave me, moreover, some faint clue perhaps, though a clue I was unequal to following up, to the nature of the strife and terror and frustrate influence in the house. That housekeeper had to do with it. She kept it alive. Her thought was like a spell she waved above her mistress’s head.

VII

That night I was wakened by a hurried tapping at my door, and before I could answer, Frances stood beside my bed. She had switched on the light as she came in. Her hair fell straggling over her dressing-gown. Her face was deathly pale, its expression so distraught it was almost haggard. The eyes were very wide. She looked almost like another woman.

She was whispering at a great pace: “Bill, Bill, wake up, quick!”

“I am awake. What is it?” I whispered too. I was startled.

“Listen!” was all she said. Her eyes stared into vacancy.

There was not a sound in the great house. The wind had dropped, and all was still. Only the tapping seemed to continue endlessly in my brain. The clock on the mantelpiece pointed to half-past two.

“I heard nothing, Frances. What is it?” I rubbed my eyes; I had been very deeply asleep.

“Listen!” she repeated very softly, holding up one finger and turning her eyes towards the door she had left ajar. Her usual calmness had deserted her. She was in the grip of some distressing terror.

For a full minute we held our breath and listened. Then her eyes rolled round again and met my own, and her skin went even whiter than before.

“It woke me,” she said beneath her breath, and moving a step nearer to my bed. “It was the Noise.” Even her whisper trembled.

“The Noise!” The word repeated itself dully of its own accord. I would rather it had been anything in the world but that—earthquake, foreign cannon, collapse of the house above our heads! “The noise, Frances! Are you sure?” I was playing really for a little time.

“It was like thunder. At first I thought it was thunder. But a minute later it came again—from underground. It’s appalling.” She muttered the words, her voice not properly under control.

There was a pause of perhaps a minute, and then we both spoke at once. We said foolish, obvious things that neither of us believed in for a second. The roof had fallen in, there were burglars downstairs, the safes had been blown open. It was to comfort each other as children do that we said these things; also it was to gain further time.

“There’s some one in the house, of course,” I heard my voice say finally, as I sprang out of bed and hurried into dressing-gown and slippers. “Don’t be alarmed. I’ll go down and see,” and from the drawer I took a pistol it was my habit to carry everywhere with me. I loaded it carefully while Frances stood stock-still beside the bed and watched. I moved towards the open door.

“You stay here, Frances,” I whispered, the beating of my heart making the words uneven, “while I go down and make a search. Lock yourself in, girl. Nothing can happen to you. It was downstairs, you said?”

“Underneath,” she answered faintly, pointing through the floor.

She moved suddenly between me and the door.

“Listen! Hark!” she said, the eyes in her face quite fixed; “it’s coming again,” and she turned her head to catch the slightest sound. I stood there watching her, and while I watched her, shook. But nothing stirred. From the halls below rose only the whirr and quiet ticking of the numerous clocks. The blind by the open window behind us flapped out a little into the room as the draught caught it.

“I’ll come with you, Bill—to the next floor,” she broke the silence. “Then I’ll stay with Mabel—till you come up again.” The blind sank down with a long sigh as she said it.

The question jumped to my lips before I could repress it:

“Mabel is awake. She heard it too?”

I hardly know why horror caught me at her answer. All was so vague and terrible as we stood there playing the great game of this sinister house where nothing ever happened.

“We met in the passage. She was on her way to me.”

What shook in me, shook inwardly. Frances, I mean, did not see it. I had the feeling just then that the Noise was upon us, that any second it would boom and roar about our ears. But the deep silence held. I only heard my sister’s little whisper coming across the room in answer to my question:

“Then what is Mabel doing now?”

And her reply proved that she was yielding at last beneath the dreadful tension, for she spoke at once, unable longer to keep up the pretence. With a kind of relief, as it were, she said it out, looking helplessly at me like a child:

“She is weeping and gna—”

My expression must have stopped her. I believe I clapped both hands upon her mouth, though when I realised things clearly again, I found they were covering my own ears instead. It was a moment of unutterable horror. The revulsion I felt was actually physical. It would have given me pleasure to fire off all the five chambers of my pistol into the air above my head; the sound—a definite, wholesome sound that explained itself—would have been a positive relief. Other feelings, though, were in me too, all over me, rushing to and fro. It was vain to seek their disentanglement; it was impossible. I confess that I experienced, among them, a touch of paralysing fear—though for a moment only; it passed as sharply as it came, leaving me with a violent flush of blood to the face such as bursts of anger bring, followed abruptly by an icy perspiration over the entire body. Yet I may honestly avow that it was not ordinary personal fear I felt, nor any common dread of physical injury. It was, rather, a vast, impersonal shrinking—a sympathetic shrinking—from the agony and terror that countless others, somewhere, somehow, felt for themselves. The first sensation of a prison overwhelmed me in that instant, of bitter strife and frenzied suffering, and the fiery torture of the yearning to escape that was yet hopelessly uttered. … It was of incredible power. It was real. The vain, intolerable hope swept over me.

I mastered myself, though hardly knowing how, and took my sister’s hand. It was as cold as ice, as I led her firmly to the door and out into the passage. Apparently she noticed nothing of my so near collapse, for I caught her whisper as we went. “You are brave, Bill; splendidly brave.”

The upper corridors of the great sleeping house were brightly lit; on her way to me she had turned on every electric switch her hand could reach; and as we passed the final flight of stairs to the floor below, I heard a door shut softly and knew that Mabel had been listening—waiting for us. I led my sister up to it. She knocked, and the door was opened cautiously an inch or so. The room was pitch black. I caught no glimpse of Mabel standing there. Frances turned to me with a hurried whisper, “Billy, you will be careful, won’t you?” and went in. I just had time to answer that I would not be long, and Frances to reply, “You’ll find us here—” when the door closed and cut her sentence short before its end.

But it was not alone the closing door that took the final words. Frances—by the way she disappeared I knew it—had made a swift and violent movement into the darkness that was as though she sprang. She leaped upon that other woman who stood back among the shadows, for, simultaneously with the clipping of the sentence, another sound was also stopped—stifled, smothered, choked back lest I should also hear it. Yet not in time. I heard it—a hard and horrible sound that explained both the leap and the abrupt cessation of the whispered words.

I stood irresolute a moment. It was as though all the bones had been withdrawn from my body, so that I must sink and fall. That sound plucked them out, and plucked out my self-possession with them. I am not sure that it was a sound I had ever heard before, though children, I half remembered, made it sometimes in blind rages when they knew not what they did. In a grown up person certainly I had never known it. I associated it with animals rather—horribly. In the history of the world, no doubt, it has been common enough, alas, but fortunately today there can be but few who know it, or would recognise it even when heard. The bones shot back into my body the same instant, but red-hot and burning; the brief instant of irresolution passed; I was torn between the desire to break down the door and enter, and to run—run for my life from a thing I dared not face.

Out of the horrid tumult, then, I adopted neither course. Without reflection, certainly without analysis of what was best to do for my sister, myself or Mabel, I took up my action where it had been interrupted. I turned from the awful door and moved slowly towards the head of the stairs. But that dreadful little sound came with me. I believe my own teeth chattered. It seemed all over the house—in the empty halls that opened into the long passages towards the music-room, and even in the grounds outside the building. From the lawns and barren garden, from the ugly terraces themselves, it rose into the night, and behind it came a curious driving sound, incomplete, unfinished, as of wailing for deliverance, the wailing of desperate souls in anguish, the dull and dry beseeching of hopeless spirits in prison.

That I could have taken the little sound from the bedroom where I actually heard it, and spread it thus over the entire house and grounds, is evidence, perhaps, of the state my nerves were in. The wailing assuredly was in my mind alone. But the longer I hesitated, the more difficult became my task, and, gathering up my dressing-gown, lest I should trip in the darkness, I passed slowly down the staircase into the hall below. I carried neither candle nor matches; every switch in room and corridor was known to me. The covering of darkness was indeed rather comforting than otherwise, for if it prevented seeing, it also prevented being seen. The heavy pistol, knocking against my thigh as I moved, made me feel I was carrying a child’s toy, foolishly. I experienced in every nerve that primitive vast dread which is the Thrill of darkness. Merely the child in me was comforted by that pistol.

The night was not entirely black; the iron bars across the glass front door were visible, and, equally, I discerned the big, stiff wooden chairs in the hall, the gaping fireplace, the upright pillars supporting the staircase, the round table in the centre with its books and flower-vases, and the basket that held visitors’ cards. There, too, was the stick and umbrella stand and the shelf with railway guides, directory, and telegraph forms. Clocks ticked everywhere with sounds like quiet footfalls. Light fell here and there in patches from the floor above. I stood a moment in the hall, letting my eyes grow more accustomed to the gloom, while deciding on a plan of search. I made out the ivy trailing outside over one of the big windows … and then the tall clock by the front door made a grating noise deep down inside its body—it was the Presentation clock, large and hideous, given by the congregation of his church—and, dreading the booming strike it seemed to threaten, I made a quick decision. If others beside myself were about in the night, the sound of that striking might cover their approach.

So I tiptoed to the right, where the passage led towards the dining-room. In the other direction were the morning- and drawing-room, both little used, and various other rooms beyond that had been his, generally now kept locked. I thought of my sister, waiting upstairs with that frightened woman for my return. I went quickly, yet stealthily.

And, to my surprise, the door of the dining-room was open. It had been opened. I paused on the threshold, staring about me. I think I fully expected to see a figure blocked in the shadows against the heavy sideboard, or looming on the other side beneath his portrait. But the room was empty; I felt it empty. Through the wide bow-windows that gave on to the verandah came an uncertain glimmer that even shone reflected in the polished surface of the dinner-table, and again I perceived the stiff outline of chairs, waiting tenantless all round it, two larger ones with high carved backs at either end. The monkey-trees on the upper terrace, too, were visible outside against the sky, and the solemn crests of the wellingtonias on the terraces below. The enormous clock on the mantelpiece ticked very slowly, as though its machinery were running down, and I made out the pale round patch that was its face. Resisting my first inclination to turn the lights up—my hand had gone so far as to finger the friendly knob—I crossed the room so carefully that no single board creaked, nor a single chair, as I rested a hand upon its back, moved on the parquet flooring. I turned neither to the right nor left, nor did I once look back.

I went towards the long corridor, filled with priceless objets d’art, that led through various antechambers into the spacious music-room, and only at the mouth of this corridor did I next halt a moment in uncertainty. For this long corridor, lit faintly by high windows on the left from the verandah, was very narrow, owing to the mass of shelves and fancy tables it contained. It was not that I feared to knock over precious things as I went, but that, because of its ungenerous width, there would be no room to pass another person—if I met one. And the certainty had suddenly come upon me that somewhere in this corridor another person at this actual moment stood. Here, somehow, amid all this dead atmosphere of furniture and impersonal emptiness, lay the hint of a living human presence; and with such conviction did it come upon me, that my hand instinctively gripped the pistol in my pocket before I could even think. Either some one had passed along this corridor just before me, or some one lay waiting at its farther end—withdrawn or flattened into one of the little recesses, to let me pass. It was the person who had opened the door. And the blood ran from my heart as I realised it.

It was not courage that sent me on, but rather a strong impulsion from behind that made it impossible to retreat: the feeling that a throng pressed at my back, drawing nearer and nearer; that I was already half surrounded, swept, dragged, coaxed into a vast prison-house where there was wailing and gnashing of teeth, where their worm dieth not and their fire is not quenched. I can neither explain nor justify the storm of irrational emotion that swept me as I stood in that moment, staring down the length of the silent corridor towards the music-room at the far end, I can only repeat that no personal bravery sent me down it, but that the negative emotion of fear was swamped in this vast sea of pity and commiseration for others that surged upon me.

My senses, at least, were no whit confused; if anything, my brain registered impressions with keener accuracy than usual. I noticed, for instance, that the two swinging doors of baize that cut the corridor into definite lengths, making little rooms of the spaces between them, were both wide open—in the dim light no mean achievement. Also that the fronds of a palm plant, some ten feet in front of me, still stirred gently from the air of some one who had recently gone past them. The long green leaves waved to and fro like hands. Then I went stealthily forward down the narrow space, proud even that I had this command of myself, and so carefully that my feet made no sound upon the Japanese matting on the floor.

It was a journey that seemed timeless. I have no idea how fast or slow I went, but I remember that I deliberately examined articles on each side of me, peering with particular closeness into the recesses of wall and window. I passed the first baize doors, and the passage beyond them widened out to hold shelves of books; there were sofas and small reading-tables against the wall. It narrowed again presently, as I entered the second stretch. The windows here were higher and smaller, and marble statuettes of classical subjects lined the walls, watching me like figures of the dead. Their white and shining faces saw me, yet made no sign. I passed next between the second baize doors. They, too, had been fastened back with hooks against the wall. Thus all doors were open—had been recently opened.

And so, at length, I found myself in the final widening of the corridor which formed an antechamber to the music-room itself. It had been used formerly to hold the overflow of meetings. No door separated it from the great hall beyond, but heavy curtains hung usually to close it off, and these curtains were invariably drawn. They now stood wide. And here—I can merely state the impression that came upon me—I knew myself at last surrounded. The throng that pressed behind me, also surged in front: facing me in the big room, and waiting for my entry, stood a multitude; on either side of me, in the very air above my head, the vast assemblage paused upon my coming. The pause, however, was momentary, for instantly the deep, tumultuous movement was resumed that yet was silent as a cavern underground. I felt the agony that was in it, the passionate striving, the awful struggle to escape. The semidarkness held beseeching faces that fought to press themselves upon my vision, yearning yet hopeless eyes, lips scorched and dry, mouths that opened to implore but found no craved delivery in actual words, and a fury of misery and hate that made the life in me stop dead, frozen by the horror of vain pity. That intolerable, vain Hope was everywhere.

And the multitude, it came to me, was not a single multitude, but many; for, as soon as one huge division pressed too close upon the edge of escape, it was dragged back by another and prevented. The wild host was divided against itself. Here dwelt the Shadow I had “imagined” weeks ago, and in it struggled armies of lost souls as in the depths of some bottomless pit whence there is no escape. The layers mingled, fighting against themselves in endless torture. It was in this great Shadow I had clairvoyantly seen Mabel, but about its fearful mouth, I now was certain, hovered another figure of darkness, a figure who sought to keep it in existence, since to her thought were due those lampless depths of woe without escape. … Towards me the multitudes now surged.

It was a sound and a movement that brought me back into myself. The great clock at the farther end of the room just then struck the hour of three. That was the sound. And the movement—? I was aware that a figure was passing across the distant centre of the floor. Instantly I dropped back into the arena of my little human terror. My hand again clutched stupidly at the pistol butt. I drew back into the folds of the heavy curtain. And the figure advanced.

I remember every detail. At first it seemed to me enormous—this advancing shadow—far beyond human scale; but as it came nearer, I measured it, though not consciously, by the organ pipes that gleamed in faint colours, just above its gradual soft approach. It passed them, already halfway across the great room. I saw then that its stature was that of ordinary men. The prolonged booming of the clock died away. I heard the footfall, shuffling upon the polished boards. I heard another sound—a voice, low and monotonous, droning as in prayer. The figure was speaking. It was a woman. And she carried in both hands before her a small object that faintly shimmered—a glass of water. And then I recognised her.

There was still an instant’s time before she reached me, and I made use of it. I shrank back, flattening myself against the wall. Her voice ceased a moment, as she turned and carefully drew the curtains together behind her, closing them with one hand. Oblivious of my presence, though she actually touched my dressing-gown with the hand that pulled the cords, she resumed her dreadful, solemn march, disappearing at length down the long vista of the corridor like a shadow. But as she passed me, her voice began again, so that I heard each word distinctly as she uttered it, her head aloft, her figure upright, as though she moved at the head of a procession:

“A drop of cold water, given in His name, shall moisten their burning tongues.”

It was repeated monotonously over and over again, droning down into the distance as she went, until at length both voice and figure faded into the shadows at the farther end.

For a time, I have no means of measuring precisely, I stood in that dark corner, pressing my back against the wall, and would have drawn the curtains down to hide me had I dared to stretch an arm out. The dread that presently the woman would return passed gradually away. I realised that the air had emptied, the crowd her presence had stirred into activity had retreated; I was alone in the gloomy under-spaces of the odious building. … Then I remembered suddenly again the terrified women waiting for me on that upper landing; and realised that my skin was wet and freezing cold after a profuse perspiration. I prepared to retrace my steps. I remember the effort it cost me to leave the support of the wall and covering darkness of my corner, and step out into the grey light of the corridor. At first I sidled, then, finding this mode of walking impossible, turned my face boldly and walked quickly, regardless that my dressing-gown set the precious objects shaking as I passed. A wind that sighed mournfully against the high, small windows seemed to have got inside the corridor as well; it felt so cold; and every moment I dreaded to see the outline of the woman’s figure as she waited in recess or angle against the wall for me to pass.

Was there another thing I dreaded even more? I cannot say. I only know that the first baize doors had swung-to behind me, and the second ones were close at hand, when the great dim thunder caught me, pouring up with prodigious volume so that it seemed to roll out from another world. It shook the very bowels of the building. I was closer to it than that other time, when it had followed me from the goblin garden. There was strength and hardness in it, as of metal reverberation. Some touch of numbness, almost of paralysis, must surely have been upon me that I felt no actual terror, for I remember even turning and standing still to hear it better. “That is the Noise,” my thought ran stupidly, and I think I whispered it aloud; “the Doors are closing.”

The wind outside against the windows was audible, so it cannot have been really loud, yet to me it was the biggest, deepest sound I have ever heard, but so far away, with such awful remoteness in it, that I had to doubt my own ears at the same time. It seemed underground—the rumbling of earthquake gates that shut remorselessly within the rocky Earth—stupendous ultimate thunder. They were shut off from help again. The doors had closed.

I felt a storm of pity, an agony of bitter, futile hate sweep through me. My memory of the figure changed then. The Woman with the glass of cooling water had stepped down from Heaven; but the Man—or was it Men?—who smeared this terrible layer of belief and Thought upon the world! …

I crossed the dining-room—it was fancy, of course, that held my eyes from glancing at the portrait for fear I should see it smiling approval—and so finally reached the hall, where the light from the floor above seemed now quite bright in comparison. All the doors I closed carefully behind me; but first I had to open them. The woman had closed every one. Up the stairs, then, I actually ran, two steps at a time. My sister was standing outside Mabel’s door. By her face I knew that she had also heard. There was no need to ask. I quickly made my mind up.

“There’s nothing,” I said, and detailed briefly my tour of search. “All is quiet and undisturbed downstairs.” May God forgive me!

She beckoned to me, closing the door softly behind her. My heart beat violently a moment, then stood still.

“Mabel,” she said aloud.

It was like the sentence of a judge, that one short word.

I tried to push past her and go in, but she stopped me with her arm. She was wholly mistress of herself, I saw.

“Hush!” she said in a lower voice. “I’ve got her round again with brandy. She’s sleeping quietly now. We won’t disturb her.”

She drew me farther out into the landing, and as she did so, the clock in the hall below struck half-past three. I had stood, then, thirty minutes in the corridor below. “You’ve been such a long time,” she said simply. “I feared for you,” and she took my hand in her own that was cold and clammy.

VIII

And then, while that dreadful house stood listening about us in the early hours of this chill morning upon the edge of winter, she told me, with laconic brevity, things about Mabel that I heard as from a distance. There was nothing so unusual or tremendous in the short recital, nothing indeed I might not have already guessed for myself. It was the time and scene, the inference, too, that made it so afflicting: the idea that Mabel believed herself so utterly and hopelessly lost—beyond recovery damned.

That she had loved him with so passionate a devotion that she had given her soul into his keeping, this certainly I had not divined—probably because I had never thought about it one way or the other. He had “converted” her, I knew, but that she had subscribed wholeheartedly to that most cruel and ugly of his dogmas—this was new to me, and came with a certain shock as I heard it. In love, of course, the weaker nature is receptive to all manner of suggestion. This man had “suggested” his pet brimstone lake so vividly that she had listened and believed. He had frightened her into heaven; and his heaven, a definite locality in the skies, had its foretaste here on earth in miniature—The Towers, house and garden. Into his dolorous scheme of a handful saved and millions damned, his enclosure, as it were, of sheep and goats, he had swept her before she was aware of it. Her mind no longer was her own. And it was Mrs. Marsh who kept the thought-stream open, though tempered, as she deemed, with that touch of craven, superstitious mercy.

But what I found it difficult to understand, and still more difficult to accept, was that, during her year abroad, she had been so haunted with a secret dread of that hideous after-death that she had finally revolted and tried to recover that clearer state of mind she had enjoyed before the religious bully had stunned her—yet had tried in vain. She had returned to The Towers to find her soul again, only to realise that it was lost eternally. The cleaner state of mind lay then beyond recovery. In the reaction that followed the removal of his terrible “suggestion,” she felt the crumbling of all that he had taught her, but searched in vain for the peace and beauty his teachings had destroyed. Nothing came to replace these. She was empty, desolate, hopeless; craving her former joy and carelessness, she found only hate and diabolical calculation. This man, whom she had loved to the point of losing her soul for him, had bequeathed to her one black and fiery thing—the terror of the damned. His thinking wrapped her in this iron garment that held her fast.

All this Frances told me, far more briefly than I have here repeated it. In her eyes and gestures and laconic sentences lay the conviction of great beating issues and of menacing drama my own description fails to recapture. It was all so incongruous and remote from the world I lived in that more than once a smile, though a smile of pity, fluttered to my lips; but a glimpse of my face in the mirror showed rather the leer of a grimace. There was no real laughter anywhere that night. The entire adventure seemed so incredible, here, in this twentieth century—but yet delusion, that feeble word, did not occur once in the comments my mind suggested though did not utter. I remembered that forbidding Shadow too; my sister’s watercolours; the vanished personality of our hostess; the inexplicable, thundering Noise, and the figure of Mrs. Marsh in her midnight ritual that was so childish yet so horrible. I shivered in spite of my own “emancipated” cast of mind.

“There is no Mabel,” were the words with which my sister sent another shower of ice down my spine. “He has killed her in his lake of fire and brimstone.”

I stared at her blankly, as in a nightmare where nothing true or possible ever happened.

“He killed her in his lake of fire and brimstone,” she repeated more faintly.

A desperate effort was in me to say the strong, sensible thing which should destroy the oppressive horror that grew so stiflingly about us both, but again the mirror drew the attempted smile into the merest grin, betraying the distortion that was everywhere in the place.

“You mean,” I stammered beneath my breath, “that her faith has gone, but that the terror has remained?” I asked it, dully groping. I moved out of the line of the reflection in the glass.

She bowed her head as though beneath a weight; her skin was the pallor of grey ashes.

“You mean,” I said louder, “that she has lost her—mind?”

“She is terror incarnate,” was the whispered answer. “Mabel has lost her soul. Her soul is—there!” She pointed horribly below. “She is seeking it … ?”

The word “soul” stung me into something of my normal self again.

“But her terror, poor thing, is not—cannot be—transferable to us!” I exclaimed more vehemently. “It certainly is not convertible into feelings, sights and—even sounds!”

She interrupted me quickly, almost impatiently, speaking with that conviction by which she conquered me so easily that night.

“It is her terror that has revived ‘the Others.’ It has brought her into touch with them. They are loose and driving after her. Her efforts at resistance have given them also hope—that escape, after all, is possible. Day and night they strive.”

“Escape! Others!” The anger fast rising in me dropped of its own accord at the moment of birth. It shrank into a shuddering beyond my control. In that moment, I think, I would have believed in the possibility of anything and everything she might tell me. To argue or contradict seemed equally futile.

“His strong belief, as also the beliefs of others who have preceded him,” she replied, so sure of herself that I actually turned to look over my shoulder, “have left their shadow like a thick deposit over the house and grounds. To them, poor souls imprisoned by thought, it was hopeless as granite walls—until her resistance, her effort to dissipate it—let in light. Now, in their thousands, they are flocking to this little light, seeking escape. Her own escape, don’t you see, may release them all!”

It took my breath away. Had his predecessors, former occupants of this house, also preached damnation of all the world but their own exclusive sect? Was this the explanation of her obscure talk of “layers,” each striving against the other for domination? And if men are spirits, and these spirits survive, could strong Thought thus determine their condition even afterwards?

So many questions flooded into me that I selected no one of them, but stared in uncomfortable silence, bewildered, out of my depth, and acutely, painfully distressed. There was so odd a mixture of possible truth and incredible, unacceptable explanation in it all; so much confirmed, yet so much left darker than before. What she said did, indeed, offer a quasi-interpretation of my own series of abominable sensations—strife, agony, pity, hate, escape—but so farfetched that only the deep conviction in her voice and attitude made it tolerable for a second even. I found myself in a curious state of mind. I could neither think clearly nor say a word to refute her amazing statements, whispered there beside me in the shivering hours of the early morning with only a wall between ourselves and—Mabel. Close behind her words I remember this singular thing, however—that an atmosphere as of the Inquisition seemed to rise and stir about the room, beating awful wings of black above my head.

Abruptly, then, a moment’s common sense returned to me. I faced her.

“And the Noise?” I said aloud, more firmly, “the roar of the closing doors? We have all heard that! Is that subjective too?”

Frances looked sideways about her in a queer fashion that made my flesh creep again. I spoke brusquely, almost angrily. I repeated the question, and waited with anxiety for her reply.

“What noise?” she asked, with the frank expression of an innocent child. “What closing doors?”

But her face turned from grey to white, and I saw that drops of perspiration glistened on her forehead. She caught at the back of a chair to steady herself, then glanced about her again with that sidelong look that made my blood run cold. I understood suddenly then. She did not take in what I said. I knew now. She was listening—for something else.

And the discovery revived in me a far stronger emotion than any mere desire for immediate explanation. Not only did I not insist upon an answer, but I was actually terrified lest she would answer. More, I felt in me a terror lest I should be moved to describe my own experiences below-stairs, thus increasing their reality and so the reality of all. She might even explain them too!

Still listening intently, she raised her head and looked me in the eyes. Her lips opened to speak. The words came to me from a great distance, it seemed, and her voice had a sound like a stone that drops into a deep well, its fate though hidden, known.

“We are in it with her, too, Bill. We are in it with her. Our interpretations vary—because we are—in parts of it only. Mabel is in it—all.”

The desire for violence came over me. If only she would say a definite thing in plain King’s English! If only I could find it in me to give utterance to what shouted so loud within me! If only—the same old cry—something would happen! For all this elliptic talk that dazed my mind left obscurity everywhere. Her atrocious meaning, none the less, flashed through me, though vanishing before it wholly divulged itself.

It brought a certain reaction with it. I found my tongue. Whether I actually believed what I said is more than I can swear to; that it seemed to me wise at the moment is all I remember. My mind was in a state of obscure perception less than that of normal consciousness.

“Yes, Frances, I believe that what you say is the truth, and that we are in it with her”—I meant to say it with loud, hostile emphasis, but instead I whispered it lest she should hear the trembling of my voice—“and for that reason, my dear sister, we leave tomorrow, you and I—today, rather, since it is long past midnight—we leave this house of the damned. We go back to London.”

Frances looked up, her face distraught almost beyond recognition. But it was not my words that caused the tumult in her heart. It was a sound—the sound she had been listening for—so faint I barely caught it myself, and had she not pointed I could never have known the direction whence it came. Small and terrible it rose again in the stillness of the night, the sound of gnashing teeth. And behind it came another—the tread of stealthy footsteps. Both were just outside the door.

The room swung round me for a second. My first instinct to prevent my sister going out—she had dashed past me frantically to the door—gave place to another when I saw the expression in her eyes. I followed her lead instead; it was surer than my own. The pistol in my pocket swung uselessly against my thigh. I was flustered beyond belief and ashamed that I was so.

“Keep close to me, Frances,” I said huskily, as the door swung wide and a shaft of light fell upon a figure moving rapidly. Mabel was going down the corridor. Beyond her, in the shadows on the staircase, a second figure stood beckoning, scarcely visible.

“Before they get her! Quick!” was screamed into my ears, and our arms were about her in the same moment. It was a horrible scene. Not that Mabel struggled in the least, but that she collapsed as we caught her and fell with her dead weight, as of a corpse, limp, against us. And her teeth began again. They continued, even beneath the hand that Frances clapped upon her lips. …

We carried her back into her own bedroom, where she lay down peacefully enough. It was so soon over. … The rapidity of the whole thing robbed it of reality almost. It had the swiftness of something remembered rather than of something witnessed. She slept again so quickly that it was almost as if we had caught her sleepwalking. I cannot say. I asked no questions at the time; I have asked none since; and my help was needed as little as the protection of my pistol. Frances was strangely competent and collected. … I lingered for some time uselessly by the door, till at length, looking up with a sigh, she made a sign for me to go.

“I shall wait in your room next door,” I whispered, “till you come.” But, though going out, I waited in the corridor instead, so as to hear the faintest call for help. In that dark corridor upstairs I waited, but not long. It may have been fifteen minutes when Frances reappeared, locking the door softly behind her. Leaning over the banisters, I saw her.

“I’ll go in again about six o’clock,” she whispered, “as soon as it gets light. She is sound asleep now. Please don’t wait. If anything happens I’ll call—you might leave your door ajar, perhaps.” And she came up, looking like a ghost.

But I saw her first safely into bed, and the rest of the night I spent in an armchair close to my opened door, listening for the slightest sound. Soon after five o’clock I heard Frances fumbling with the key, and, peering over the railing again, I waited till she reappeared and went back into her own room. She closed her door. Evidently she was satisfied that all was well.

Then, and then only, did I go to bed myself, but not to sleep. I could not get the scene out of my mind, especially that odious detail of it which I hoped and believed my sister had not seen—the still, dark figure of the housekeeper waiting on the stairs below—waiting, of course, for Mabel.

IX

It seems I became a mere spectator after that; my sister’s lead was so assured for one thing, and, for another, the responsibility of leaving Mabel alone—Frances laid it bodily upon my shoulders—was a little more than I cared about. Moreover, when we all three met later in the day, things went on so exactly as before, so absolutely without friction or distress, that to present a sudden, obvious excuse for cutting our visit short seemed ill-judged. And on the lowest grounds it would have been desertion. At any rate, it was beyond my powers, and Frances was quite firm that she must stay. We therefore did stay. Things that happen in the night always seem exaggerated and distorted when the sun shines brightly next morning; no one can reconstruct the terror of a nightmare afterwards, nor comprehend why it seemed so overwhelming at the time.

I slept till ten o’clock, and when I rang for breakfast, a note from my sister lay upon the tray, its message of counsel couched in a calm and comforting strain. Mabel, she assured me, was herself again and remembered nothing of what had happened; there was no need of any violent measures; I was to treat her exactly as if I knew nothing. “And, if you don’t mind, Bill, let us leave the matter unmentioned between ourselves as well. Discussion exaggerates; such things are best not talked about. I’m sorry I disturbed you so unnecessarily; I was stupidly excited. Please forget all the things I said at the moment.” She had written “nonsense” first instead of “things,” then scratched it out. She wished to convey that hysteria had been abroad in the night, and I readily gulped the explanation down, though it could not satisfy me in the smallest degree.

There was another week of our visit still, and we stayed it out to the end without disaster. My desire to leave at times became that frantic thing, desire to escape; but I controlled it, kept silent, watched and wondered. Nothing happened. As before, and everywhere, there was no sequence of development, no connection between cause and effect; and climax, none whatever. The thing swayed up and down, backwards and forwards like a great loose curtain in the wind, and I could only vaguely surmise what caused the draught or why there was a curtain at all. A novelist might mould the queer material into coherent sequence that would be interesting but could not be true. It remains, therefore, not a story but a history. Nothing happened.

Perhaps my intense dislike of the fall of darkness was due wholly to my stirred imagination, and perhaps my anger when I learned that Frances now occupied a bed in our hostess’s room was unreasonable. Nerves were unquestionably on edge. I was for ever on the lookout for some event that should make escape imperative, but yet that never presented itself. I slept lightly, left my door ajar to catch the slightest sound, even made stealthy tours of the house below-stairs while everybody dreamed in their beds. But I discovered nothing; the doors were always locked; I neither saw the housekeeper again in unreasonable times and places, nor heard a footstep in the passages and halls. The Noise was never once repeated. That horrible, ultimate thunder, my intensest dread of all, lay withdrawn into the abyss whence it had twice arisen. And though in my thoughts it was sternly denied existence, the great black reason for the fact afflicted me unbelievably. Since Mabel’s fruitless effort to escape, the Doors kept closed remorselessly. She had failed; they gave up hope. For this was the explanation that haunted the region of my mind where feelings stir and hint before they clothe themselves in actual language. Only I firmly kept it there; it never knew expression.

But, if my ears were open, my eyes were opened too, and it were idle to pretend that I did not notice a hundred details that were capable of sinister interpretation had I been weak enough to yield. Some protective barrier had fallen into ruins round me, so that Terror stalked behind the general collapse, feeling for me through all the gaping fissures. Much of this, I admit, must have been merely the elaboration of those sensations I had first vaguely felt, before subsequent events and my talks with Frances had dramatised them into living thoughts. I therefore leave them unmentioned in this history, just as my mind left them unmentioned in that interminable final week.

Our life went on precisely as before—Mabel unreal and outwardly so still; Frances, secretive, anxious, tactful to the point of slyness, and keen to save to the point of self-forgetfulness. There were the same stupid meals, the same wearisome long evenings, the stifling ugliness of house and grounds, the Shadow settling in so thickly that it seemed almost a visible, tangible thing. I came to feel the only friendly things in all this hostile, cruel place were the robins that hopped boldly over the monstrous terraces and even up to the windows of the unsightly house itself. The robins alone knew joy; they danced, believing no evil thing was possible in all God’s radiant world. They believed in everybody; their god’s plan of life had no room in it for hell, damnation and lakes of brimstone. I came to love the little birds. Had Samuel Franklyn known them, he might have preached a different sermon, bequeathing love in place of terror! …

Most of my time I spent writing; but it was a pretence at best, and rather a dangerous one besides. For it stirred the mind to production, with the result that other things came pouring in as well. With reading it was the same. In the end I found an aggressive, deliberate resistance to be the only way of feasible defence. To walk far afield was out of the question, for it meant leaving my sister too long alone, so that my exercise was confined to nearer home. My saunters in the grounds, however, never surprised the goblin garden again. It was close at hand, but I seemed unable to get wholly into it. Too many things assailed my mind for any one to hold exclusive possession, perhaps.

Indeed, all the interpretations, all the “layers,” to use my sister’s phrase, slipped in by turns and lodged there for a time. They came day and night, and though my reason denied them entrance they held their own as by a kind of squatters’ right. They stirred moods already in me, that is, and did not introduce entirely new ones; for every mind conceals ancestral deposits that have been cultivated in turn along the whole line of its descent. Any day a chance shower may cause this one or that to blossom. Thus it came to me, at any rate. After darkness the Inquisition paced the empty corridors and set up ghastly apparatus in the dismal halls; and once, in the library, there swept over me that easy and delicious conviction that by confessing my wickedness I could resume it later, since Confession is expression, and expression brings relief and leaves one ready to accumulate again. And in such mood I felt bitter and unforgiving towards all others who thought differently. Another time it was a Pagan thing that assaulted me—so trivial yet oh, so significant at the time—when I dreamed that a herd of centaurs rolled up with a great stamping of hoofs round the house to destroy it, and then woke to hear the horses tramping across the field below the lawns; they neighed ominously and their noisy panting was audible as if it were just outside my windows.

But the tree episode, I think, was the most curious of all—except, perhaps, the incident with the children which I shall mention in a moment—for its closeness to reality was so unforgettable. Outside the east window of my room stood a giant wellingtonia on the lawn, its head rising level with the upper sash. It grew some twenty feet away, planted on the highest terrace, and I often saw it when closing my curtains for the night, noticing how it drew its heavy skirts about it, and how the light from other windows threw glimmering streaks and patches that turned it into the semblance of a towering, solemn image. It stood there then so strikingly, somehow like a great old-world idol, that it claimed attention. Its appearance was curiously formidable. Its branches rustled without visibly moving and it had a certain portentous, forbidding air, so grand and dark and monstrous in the night that I was always glad when my curtains shut it out. Yet, once in bed, I had never thought about it one way or the other, and by day had certainly never sought it out.

One night, then, as I went to bed and closed this window against a cutting easterly wind, I saw—that there were two of these trees. A brother wellingtonia rose mysteriously beside it, equally huge, equally towering, equally monstrous. The menacing pair of them faced me there upon the lawn. But in this new arrival lay a strange suggestion that frightened me before I could argue it away. Exact counterpart of its giant companion, it revealed also that gross, odious quality that all my sister’s paintings held. I got the odd impression that the rest of these trees, stretching away dimly in a troop over the farther lawns, were similar, and that, led by this enormous pair, they had all moved boldly closer to my windows. At the same moment a blind was drawn down over an upper room; the second tree disappeared into the surrounding darkness. It was, of course, this chance light that had brought it into the field of vision, but when the black shutter dropped over it, hiding it from view, the manner of its vanishing produced the queer effect that it had slipped into its companion—almost that it had been an emanation of the one I so disliked, and not really a tree at all! In this way the garden turned vehicle for expressing what lay behind it all! …

The behaviour of the doors, the little, ordinary doors, seems scarcely worth mention at all, their queer way of opening and shutting of their own accord; for this was accountable in a hundred natural ways, and to tell the truth, I never caught one in the act of moving. Indeed, only after frequent repetitions did the detail force itself upon me, when, having noticed one, I noticed all. It produced, however, the unpleasant impression of a continual coming and going in the house, as though, screened cleverly and purposely from actual sight, some one in the building held constant invisible intercourse with—others.

Upon detailed descriptions of these uncertain incidents I do not venture, individually so trivial, but taken all together so impressive and so insolent. But the episode of the children, mentioned above, was different. And I give it because it showed how vividly the intuitive child-mind received the impression—one impression, at any rate—of what was in the air. It may be told in a very few words. I believe they were the coachman’s children, and that the man had been in Mr. Franklyn’s service; but of neither point am I quite positive. I heard screaming in the rose-garden that runs along the stable walls—it was one afternoon not far from the tea-hour—and on hurrying up I found a little girl of nine or ten fastened with ropes to a rustic seat, and two other children—boys, one about twelve and one much younger—gathering sticks beneath the climbing rose-trees. The girl was white and frightened, but the others were laughing and talking among themselves so busily while they picked that they did not notice my abrupt arrival. Some game, I understood, was in progress, but a game that had become too serious for the happiness of the prisoner, for there was a fear in the girl’s eyes that was a very genuine fear indeed. I unfastened her at once; the ropes were so loosely and clumsily knotted that they had not hurt her skin; it was not that which made her pale. She collapsed a moment upon the bench, then picked up her tiny skirts and dived away at full speed into the safety of the stable-yard. There was no response to my brief comforting, but she ran as though for her life, and I divined that some horrid boys’ cruelty had been afoot. It was probably mere thoughtlessness, as cruelty with children usually is, but something in me decided to discover exactly what it was.

And the boys, not one whit alarmed at my intervention, merely laughed shyly when I explained that their prisoner had escaped, and told me frankly what their “gime” had been. There was no vestige of shame in them, nor any idea, of course, that they aped a monstrous reality. That it was mere pretence was neither here nor there. To them, though make-believe, it was a make-believe of something that was right and natural and in no sense cruel. Grownups did it too. It was necessary for her good.

“We was going to burn her up, sir,” the older one informed me, answering my “Why?” with the explanation, “Because she wouldn’t believe what we wanted ’er to believe.”

And, game though it was, the feeling of reality about the little episode was so arresting, so terrific in some way, that only with difficulty did I confine my admonitions on this occasion to mere words. The boys slunk off, frightened in their turn, yet not, I felt, convinced that they had erred in principle. It was their inheritance. They had breathed it in with the atmosphere of their bringing-up. They would renew the salutary torture when they could—till she “believed” as they did.

I went back into the house, afflicted with a passion of mingled pity and distress impossible to describe, yet on my short way across the garden was attacked by other moods in turn, each more real and bitter than its predecessor. I received the whole series, as it were, at once. I felt like a diver rising to the surface through layers of water at different temperatures, though here the natural order was reversed, and the cooler strata were uppermost, the heated ones below. Thus, I was caught by the goblin touch of the willows that fringed the field; by the sensuous curving of the twisted ash that formed a gateway to the little grove of sapling oaks where fauns and satyrs lurked to play in the moonlight before Pagan altars; and by the cloaking darkness, next, of the copse of stunted pines, close gathered each to each, where hooded figures stalked behind an awful cross. The episode with the children seemed to have opened me like a knife. The whole Place rushed at me.

I suspect this synthesis of many moods produced in me that climax of loathing and disgust which made me feel the limit of bearable emotion had been reached, so that I made straight to find Frances in order to convince her that at any rate I must leave. For, although this was our last day in the house, and we had arranged to go next day, the dread was in me that she would still find some persuasive reason for staying on. And an unexpected incident then made my dread unnecessary. The front door was open and a cab stood in the drive; a tall, elderly man was gravely talking in the hall with the parlourmaid we called the Grenadier. He held a piece of paper in his hand. “I have called to see the house,” I heard him say, as I ran up the stairs to Frances, who was peering like an inquisitive child over the banisters. …

“Yes,” she told me with a sigh, I know not whether of resignation or relief, “the house is to be let or sold. Mabel has decided. Some Society or other, I believe—”

I was overjoyed: this made our leaving right and possible. “You never told me, Frances!”

“Mabel only heard of it a few days ago. She told me herself this morning. It is a chance, she says. Alone she cannot get it ‘straight.’ ”

“Defeat?” I asked, watching her closely.

“She thinks she has found a way out. It’s not a family, you see, it’s a Society, a sort of Community—they go in for thought—”

“A Community!” I gasped. “You mean religious?”

She shook her head. “Not exactly,” she said smiling, “but some kind of association of men and women who want a headquarters in the country—a place where they can write and meditate—think—mature their plans and all the rest—I don’t know exactly what.”

“Utopian dreamers?” I asked, yet feeling an immense relief come over me as I heard. But I asked in ignorance, not cynically. Frances would know. She knew all this kind of thing.

“No, not that exactly,” she smiled. “Their teachings are grand and simple—old as the world too, really—the basis of every religion before men’s mind perverted them with their manufactured creeds—”

Footsteps on the stairs, and the sound of voices, interrupted our odd impromptu conversation, as the Grenadier came up, followed by the tall, grave gentleman who was being shown over the house. My sister drew me along the corridor towards her room, where she went in and closed the door behind me, yet not before I had stolen a good look at the caller—long enough, at least, for his face and general appearance to have made a definite impression on me. For something strong and peaceful emanated from his presence; he moved with such quiet dignity; the glance of his eyes was so steady and reassuring, that my mind labelled him instantly as a type of man one would turn to in an emergency and not be disappointed. I had seen him but for a passing moment, but I had seen him twice, and the way he walked down the passage, looking competently about him, conveyed the same impression as when I saw him standing at the door—fearless, tolerant, wise. “A sincere and kindly character,” I judged instantly, “a man whom some big kind of love has trained in sweetness towards the world; no hate in him anywhere.” A great deal, no doubt, to read in so brief a glance! Yet his voice confirmed my intuition, a deep and very gentle voice, great firmness in it too.

“Have I become suddenly sensitive to people’s atmospheres in this extraordinary fashion?” I asked myself, smiling, as I stood in the room and heard the door close behind me. “Have I developed some clairvoyant faculty here?” At any other time I should have mocked.

And I sat down and faced my sister, feeling strangely comforted and at peace for the first time since I had stepped beneath The Towers’ roof a month ago. Frances, I then saw, was smiling a little as she watched me.

“You know him?” I asked.

“You felt it too?” was her question in reply. “No,” she added, “I don’t know him—beyond the fact that he is a leader in the Movement and has devoted years and money to its objects. Mabel felt the same thing in him that you have felt—and jumped at it.”

“But you’ve seen him before?” I urged, for the certainty was in me that he was no stranger to her.

She shook her head. “He called one day early this week, when you were out. Mabel saw him. I believe—” she hesitated a moment, as though expecting me to stop her with my usual impatience of such subjects—“I believe he has explained everything to her—the beliefs he embodies, she declares, are her salvation—might be, rather, if she could adopt them.”

“Conversion again!” For I remembered her riches, and how gladly a Society would gobble them.

“The layers I told you about,” she continued calmly, shrugging her shoulders slightly—“the deposits that are left behind by strong thinking and real belief—but especially by ugly, hateful belief, because, you see—there’s more vital passion in that sort—”

“Frances, I don’t understand a bit,” I said out loud, but said it a little humbly, for the impression the man had left was still strong upon me and I was grateful for the steady sense of peace and comfort he had somehow introduced. The horrors had been so dreadful. My nerves, doubtless, were more than a little overstrained. Absurd as it must sound, I classed him in my mind with the robins, the happy, confiding robins who believed in everybody and thought no evil! I laughed a moment at my ridiculous idea, and my sister, encouraged by this sign of patience in me, continued more fluently.

“Of course you don’t understand, Bill? Why should you? You’ve never thought about such things. Needing no creed yourself, you think all creeds are rubbish.”

“I’m open to conviction—I’m tolerant,” I interrupted.

“You’re as narrow as Sam Franklyn, and as crammed with prejudice,” she answered, knowing that she had me at her mercy.

“Then, pray, what may be his, or his Society’s beliefs?” I asked, feeling no desire to argue, “and how are they going to prove your Mabel’s salvation? Can they bring beauty into all this aggressive hate and ugliness?”

“Certain hope and peace,” she said, “that peace which is understanding, and that understanding which explains all creeds and therefore tolerates them.”

“Toleration! The one word a religious man loathes above all others! His pet word is damnation—”

“Tolerates them,” she repeated patiently, unperturbed by my explosion, “because it includes them all.”

“Fine, if true,” I admitted, “very fine. But how, pray, does it include them all?”

“Because the key-word, the motto, of their Society is, ‘There is no religion higher than Truth,’ and it has no single dogma of any kind. Above all,” she went on, “because it claims that no individual can be ‘lost.’ It teaches universal salvation. To damn outsiders is uncivilised, childish, impure. Some take longer than others—it’s according to the way they think and live—but all find peace, through development, in the end. What the creeds call a hopeless soul, it regards as a soul having further to go. There is no damnation—”

“Well, well,” I exclaimed, feeling that she rode her hobbyhorse too wildly, too roughly over me, “but what is the bearing of all this upon this dreadful place, and upon Mabel? I’ll admit that there is this atmosphere—this—er—inexplicable horror in the house and grounds, and that if not of damnation exactly, it is certainly damnable. I’m not too prejudiced to deny that, for I’ve felt it myself.”

To my relief she was brief. She made her statement, leaving me to take it or reject it as I would.

“The thought and belief its former occupants—have left behind. For there has been coincidence here, a coincidence that must be rare. The site on which this modern house now stands was Roman, before that Early Britain, with burial mounds, before that again, Druid—the Druid stones still lie in that copse below the field, the Tumuli among the ilexes behind the drive. The older building Sam Franklyn altered and practically pulled down was a monastery; he changed the chapel into a meeting hall, which is now the music room; but, before he came here, the house was occupied by Manetti, a violent Catholic without tolerance or vision; and in the interval between these two, Julius Weinbaum had it, Hebrew of most rigid orthodox type imaginable—so they all have left their—”

“Even so,” I repeated, yet interested to hear the rest, “what of it?”

“Simply this,” said Frances with conviction, “that each in turn has left his layer of concentrated thinking and belief behind him; because each believed intensely, absolutely, beyond the least weakening of any doubt—the kind of strong belief and thinking that is rare anywhere today, the kind that wills, impregnates objects, saturates the atmosphere, haunts, in a word. And each, believing he was utterly and finally right, damned with equally positive conviction the rest of the world. One and all preached that implicitly if not explicitly. It’s the root of every creed. Last of the bigoted, grim series came Samuel Franklyn.”

I listened in amazement that increased as she went on. Up to this point her explanation was so admirable. It was, indeed, a pretty study in psychology if it were true.

“Then why does nothing ever happen?” I enquired mildly. “A place so thickly haunted ought to produce a crop of no ordinary results!”

“There lies the proof,” she went on in a lowered voice, “the proof of the horror and the ugly reality. The thought and belief of each occupant in turn kept all the others under. They gave no sign of life at the time. But the results of thinking never die. They crop out again the moment there’s an opening. And, with the return of Mabel in her negative state, believing nothing positive herself, the place for the first time found itself free to reproduce its buried stores. Damnation, hellfire, and the rest—the most permanent and vital thought of all those creeds, since it was applied to the majority of the world—broke loose again, for there was no restraint to hold it back. Each sought to obtain its former supremacy. None conquered. There results a pandemonium of hate and fear, of striving to escape, of agonised, bitter warring to find safety, peace—salvation. The place is saturated by that appalling stream of thinking—the terror of the damned. It concentrated upon Mabel, whose negative attitude furnished the channel of deliverance. You and I, according to our sympathy with her, were similarly involved. Nothing happened, because no one layer could ever gain the supremacy.”

I was so interested—I dare not say amused—that I stared in silence while she paused a moment, afraid that she would draw rein and end the fairy tale too soon.

“The beliefs of this man, of his Society rather, vigorously thought and therefore vigorously given out here, will put the whole place straight. It will act as a solvent. These vitriolic layers actively denied, will fuse and disappear in the stream of gentle, tolerant sympathy which is love. For each member, worthy of the name, loves the world, and all creeds go into the melting-pot; Mabel, too, if she joins them out of real conviction, will find salvation—”

“Thinking, I know, is of the first importance,” I objected, “but don’t you, perhaps, exaggerate the power of feeling and emotion which in religion are au fond always hysterical?”

“What is the world,” she told me, “but thinking and feeling? An individual’s world is entirely what that individual thinks and believes—interpretation. There is no other. And unless he really thinks and really believes, he has no permanent world at all. I grant that few people think, and still fewer believe, and that most take ready-made suits and make them do. Only the strong make their own things; the lesser fry, Mabel among them, are merely swept up into what has been manufactured for them. They get along somehow. You and I have made for ourselves, Mabel has not. She is a nonentity, and when her belief is taken from her, she goes with it.”

It was not in me just then to criticise the evasion, or pick out the sophistry from the truth. I merely waited for her to continue.

“None of us have Truth, my dear Frances,” I ventured presently, seeing that she kept silent.

“Precisely,” she answered, “but most of us have beliefs. And what one believes and thinks affects the world at large. Consider the legacy of hatred and cruelty involved in the doctrines men have built into their creeds where the sine qua non of salvation is absolute acceptance of one particular set of views or else perishing everlastingly—for only by repudiating history can they disavow it—”

“You’re not quite accurate,” I put in. “Not all the creeds teach damnation, do they? Franklyn did, of course, but the others are a bit modernised now surely?”

“Trying to get out of it,” she admitted, “perhaps they are, but damnation of unbelievers—of most of the world, that is—is their rather favourite idea if you talk with them.”

“I never have.”

She smiled. “But I have,” she said significantly, “So, if you consider what the various occupants of this house have so strongly held and thought and believed, you need not be surprised that the influence they have left behind them should be a dark and dreadful legacy. For thought, you know, does leave—”

The opening of the door, to my great relief, interrupted her, as the Grenadier led in the visitor to see the room. He bowed to both of us with a brief word of apology, looked round him, and withdrew, and with his departure the conversation between us came naturally to an end. I followed him out. Neither of us in any case, I think, cared to argue further.

And, so far as I am aware, the curious history of The Towers ends here too. There was no climax in the story sense. Nothing ever really happened. We left next morning for London. I only know that the Society in question took the house and have since occupied it to their entire satisfaction, and that Mabel, who became a member shortly afterwards, now stays there frequently when in need of repose from the arduous and unselfish labours she took upon herself under its aegis. She dined with us only the other night, here in our tiny Chelsea flat, and a jollier, saner, more interesting and happy guest I could hardly wish for. She was vital—in the best sense; the lay-figure had come to life. I found it difficult to believe she was the same woman whose fearful effigy had floated down those dreary corridors and almost disappeared in the depths of that atrocious Shadow.

What her beliefs were now I was wise enough to leave unquestioned, and Frances, to my great relief, kept the conversation well away from such inappropriate topics. It was clear, however, that the woman had in herself some secret source of joy, that she was now an aggressive, positive force, sure of herself, and apparently afraid of nothing in heaven or hell. She radiated something very like hope and courage about her, and talked as though the world were a glorious place and everybody in it kind and beautiful. Her optimism was certainly infectious.

The Towers were mentioned only in passing. The name of Marsh came up—not the Marsh, it so happened, but a name in some book that was being discussed—and I was unable to restrain myself. Curiosity was too strong. I threw out a casual enquiry Mabel could leave unanswered if she wished. But there was no desire to avoid it. Her reply was frank and smiling.

“Would you believe it? She married,” Mabel told me, though obviously surprised that I remembered the housekeeper at all; “and is happy as the day is long. She’s found her right niche in life. A sergeant—”

“The army!” I ejaculated.

“Salvation Army,” she explained merrily.

Frances exchanged a glance with me. I laughed too, for the information took me by surprise. I cannot say why exactly, but I expected at least to hear that the woman had met some dreadful end, not impossibly by burning.

“And The Towers, now called the Rest House,” Mabel chattered on, “seems to me the most peaceful and delightful spot in England—”

“Really,” I said politely.

“When I lived there in the old days—while you were there, perhaps, though I won’t be sure,” Mabel went on, “the story got abroad that it was haunted. Wasn’t it odd? A less likely place for a ghost I’ve never seen. Why, it had no atmosphere at all.” She said this to Frances, glancing up at me with a smile that apparently had no hidden meaning. “Did you notice anything queer about it when you were there?”

This was plainly addressed to me.

“I found it—er—difficult to settle down to anything,” I said, after an instant’s hesitation. “I couldn’t work there—”

“But I thought you wrote that wonderful book on the Deaf and Blind while you stayed with me,” she asked innocently.

I stammered a little. “Oh no, not then. I only made a few notes—er—at The Towers. My mind, oddly enough, refused to produce at all down there. But—why do you ask? Did anything—was anything supposed to happen there?”

She looked searchingly into my eyes a moment before she answered:

“Not that I know of,” she said simply.

The Deferred Appointment

The little “Photographic Studio” in the side-street beyond Shepherd’s Bush had done no business all day, for the light had been uninviting to even the vainest sitter, and the murky sky that foreboded snow had hung over London without a break since dawn. Pedestrians went hurrying and shivering along the pavements, disappearing into the gloom of countless ugly little houses the moment they passed beyond the glare of the big electric standards that lit the thundering motor-buses in the main street. The first flakes of snow, indeed, were already falling slowly, as though they shrank from settling in the grime. The wind moaned and sang dismally, catching the ears and lifting the shabby coat-tails of Mr. Mor- timer Jenkyn, “Photographic Artist,” as he stood out- side and put the shutters up with his own cold hands in despair of further trade. It was five minutes to six.

With a lingering glance at the enlarged portrait of a fat man in masonic regalia who was the pride and glory of his window-front, he fixed the last hook of the shutter, and turned to go indoors. There was developing and framing to be done upstairs, not very remunerative work, but better, at any rate, than wait- ing in an empty studio for customers who did not come—wasting the heat of two oil-stoves into the bargain. And it was then, in the act of closing the street-door behind him, that he saw a man standing in the shadows of the narrow passage, staring fixedly into his face.

Mr. Jenkyn admits that he jumped. The man was so very close, yet he had not seen him come in; and in the eyes was such a curiously sad and appealing expression. He had already sent his assistant home, and there was no other occupant of the little two- storey house. The man must have slipped past him from the dark street while his back was turned. Who in the world could he be, and what could he want? Was he beggar, customer, or rogue?

“Good evening,” Mr. Jenkyn said, washing his hands, but using only half the oily politeness of tone with which he favoured sitters. He was just going to add “sir,” feeling it wiser to be on the safe side, when the stranger shifted his position so that the light fell directly upon his face, and Mr. Jenkyn was aware that he—recognised him. Unless he was greatly mistaken, it was the second-hand bookseller in the main street. “Ah, it’s you, Mr. Wilson!” he stammered, making half a question of it, as though not quite convinced. “Pardon me; I did not quite catch your face—er—I was just shutting up.” The other bowed his head in reply. “Won’t you come in? Do, please.”

Mr. Jenkyn led the way. He wondered what was the matter. The visitor was not among his customers; indeed, he could hardly claim to know him, having only seen him occasionally when calling at the shop for slight purchases of paper and what not. The man, he now realised, looked fearfully ill and wasted, his face pale and haggard. It upset him rather, this sud- den, abrupt call. He felt sorry, pained. He felt uneasy. Into the studio they passed, the visitor going first as though he knew the way, Mr. Jenkyn noticing through his flurry that he was in his “Sunday best.” Evidently he had come with a definite purpose. It was odd. Still without speaking, he moved straight across the room and posed himself in front of the dingy background of painted trees, facing the camera. The studio was brightly lit. He seated himself in the faded arm-chair, crossed his legs, drew up the little round table with the artificial roses upon it in a tall, thin vase, and struck an attitude. He meant to be pho- tographed. His eyes, staring straight into the lens, draped as it was with the black velvet curtain, seemed, however, to take no account of the Photo- graphic Artist. But Mr. Jenkyn, standing still beside the door, felt a cold air playing over his face that was not merely the winter cold from the street. He felt his hair rise. A slight shiver ran down his back. In that pale, drawn face, and in those staring eyes across the room that gazed so fixedly into the draped camera, he read the signature of illness that no longer knows hope. It was Death that he saw.

In a flash the impression came and went—less than a second. The whole business, indeed, had not occupied two minutes. Mr. Jenkyn pulled himself together with a strong effort, dismissed his foolish obsession, and came sharply to practical considera- tions. “Forgive me,” he said, a trifle thickly, confus- edly, “but I—er—did not quite realise. You desire to sit for your portrait, of course. I’ve had such a busy day, and—’ardly looked for a customer so late.” The clock, as he spoke, struck six. But he did not notice the sound. Through his mind ran another reflection: “A man shouldn’t ’ave his picture taken when he’s ill and next door to dying. Lord! He’ll want a lot of touching-up and finishin’, too!”

He began discussing the size, price, and length— the usual rigmarole of his “profession,” and the other, sitting there, still vouchsafed no comment or reply. He simply made the impression of a man in a great hurry, who wished to finish a disagreeable business without unnecessary talk. Many men, reflected the photographer, were the same; being photographed was worse to them than going to the dentist. Mr. Jenkyn filled the pauses with his professional running talk and patter, while the sitter, fixed and motionless, kept his first position and stared at the camera. The photographer rather prided himself upon his ability to make sitters look bright and pleasant; but this man was hopeless. It was only afterwards Mr. Jenkyn recalled the singular fact that he never once touched him—that, in fact, something connected possibly with his frail appearance of deadly illness had pre- vented his going close to arrange the details of the hastily assumed pose.

“It must be a flashlight, of course, Mr. Wilson,” he said, fidgeting at length with the camera-stand, shift- ing it slightly nearer; while the other moved his head gently yet impatiently in agreement. Mr. Jenkyn longed to suggest his coming another time when he looked better, to speak with sympathy of his illness; to say something, in fact, that might establish a per- sonal relation. But his tongue in this respect seemed utterly tied. It was just this personal relation which seemed impossible of approach—absolutely and peremptorily impossible. There seemed a barrier between the two. He could only chatter the usual professional commonplaces. To tell the truth, Mr. Jenkyn thinks he felt a little dazed the whole time— not quite his usual self. And, meanwhile, his uneasi- ness oddly increased. He hurried. He, too, wanted the matter done with and his visitor gone.

At length everything was ready, only the flash- light waiting to be turned on, when, stooping, he cov- ered his head with the velvet cloth and peered through the lens— at no one! When he says “at no one,” however, he qualifies it thus: “There was a quick flash of brilliant white light and a face in the middle of it—my gracious Heaven! But such a face— ’im, yet not ’im—like a sudden rushing glory of a face! It shot off like lightning out of the camera’s field of vision. It left me blinded, I assure you, ’alf blinded, and that’s a fac’. It was sheer dazzling!”

It seems Mr. Jenkyn remained entangled a moment in the cloth, eyes closed, breath coming in gasps, for when he got clear and straightened up again, staring once more at his customer over the top of the camera, he stared for the second time at—no one. And the cap that he held in his left hand he clapped feverishly over the uncovered lens. Mr. Jenkyn staggered... looked hurriedly round the empty studio, then ran, knocking a chair over as he went, into the passage. The hall was deserted, the front door closed. His visitor had disappeared “almost as though he hadn’t never been there at all”—thus he described it to himself in a terrified whisper. And again he felt the hair rise on his scalp; his skin crawled a little, and something put back the ice against his spine.

After a moment he returned to the studio and somewhat feverishly examined it. There stood the chair against the dingy background of trees; and there, close beside it, was the round table with the flower vase. Less than a minute ago Mr. Thomas Wilson, looking like death, had been sitting in that very chair. “It wasn’t all a sort of dreamin’, then,” ran through his disordered and frightened mind. “I did see something...!” He remembered vaguely stories he had read in the newspapers, stories of queer warnings that saved people from disasters, apparitions, faces seen in dream, and so forth. “Maybe,” he thought with confusion, “something’s going to ’appen to me! “Further than that he could not get for some little time, as he stood there staring about him, almost expecting that Mr. Wilson might reappear as strangely as he had disappeared. He went over the whole scene again and again, reconstructing it in minutest detail. And only then, for the first time, did he plainly realise two things which somehow or other he had not thought strange before, but now thought very strange. For his visitor, he remembered, had not uttered a single word, nor had he, Mr. Jenkyn, once touched his person... And, thereupon, without more ado, he put on his hat and coat and went round to the little shop in the main street to buy some ink and stationery which he did not in the least require. The shop seemed all as usual, though Mr. Wilson himself was not visible behind the littered desk. A tall gentleman was talking in low tones to the partner. Mr. Jenkyn bowed as he went in, then stood examin- ing a case of cheap stylographic pens, waiting for the others to finish. It was impossible to avoid overhear- ing. Besides, the little shop had distinguished cus- tomers sometimes, he had heard, and this evidently was one of them. He only understood part of the conversation, but he remembers all of it. “Singular, yes, these last words of dying men,” the tall man was saying, “very singular. You remember Newman’s: ‘More light,’ wasn’t it?” The bookseller nodded. “Fine,” he said, “fine, that!” There was a pause. Mr, Jenkyn stooped lower over the pens. “This, too, was fine in its way,” the gentleman added, straightening up to go; “the old promise, you see, unfulfilled but not forgotten. Cropped up suddenly out of the delir- ium. Curious, very curious! A good, conscientious man to the last. In all the twenty years I’ve known him he never broke his word...”

A motor-bus drowned a sentence, and then was heard in the bookseller’s voice, as he moved towards the door. “...You see, he was half-way down the stairs before they found him, always repeating the same thing, ‘I promised the wife, I promised the wife.’ And it was a job, I’m told, getting him back again... he struggled so. That’s what finished him so quick, I suppose. Fifteen minutes later he was gone, and his last words were always the same, ‘I promised the wife’...”

The tall man was gone, and Mr. Jenkyn forgot about his purchases. “When did it ’appen?” he heard himself asking in a voice he hardly recognised as his own. And the reply roared and thundered in his ears as he went down the street a minute later to his house: “Close on six o’clock—a few minutes before the hour. Been ill for weeks, yes. Caught him out of bed with high fever on his way to your place, Mr. Jenkyn, calling at the top of his voice that he’d forgot- ten to see you about his picture being taken. Yes, very sad, very sad indeed.”

But Mr. Jenkyn did not return to his studio. He left the light burning there all night. He went to the little room where he slept out, and next day gave the plate to be developed by his assistant. “Defective plate, sir,” was the report in due course; “shows noth- ing but a flash of light—uncommonly brilliant.” “Make a print of it all the same,” was the reply. Six months later, when he examined the plate and print, Mr. Jenkyn found that the singular streaks of light had disappeared from both. The uncommon brilliance had faded out completely as though it had never been there.

The Destruction of Smith

Ten years ago, in the western States of America, I once met Smith. But he was no ordinary member of the clan: he was Ezekiel B. Smith of Smithville. He was Smithville, for he founded it and made it live.

It was in the oil region, where towns spring up on the map in a few days like mushrooms, and may be destroyed again in a single night by fire and earth- quake. On a hunting expedition Smith stumbled upon a natural oil well, and instantly staked his claim; a few months later he was rich, grown into affluence as rapidly as that patch of wilderness grew into streets and houses where you could buy anything from an evening’s gambling to a tin of Boston baked pork -and- beans. Smith was really a tremendous fellow, a sort of human dynamo of energy and pluck, with rare judgment in his great square head—the kind of judgment that in higher walks of life makes statesmen. His personality cut through the difficulties of life with the clean easy force of putting his whole life into anything he touched. “God’s own luck,” his comrades called it; but really it was sheer ability and character and personality. The man had power.

From the moment of that “oil find” his rise was very rapid, but while his brains went into a dozen other big enterprises, his heart remained in little Smithville, the flimsy mushroom town he had created. His own life was in it. It was his baby. He spoke tenderly of its hideousness. Smithville was an intimate expression of his very self.

Ezekiel B. Smith I saw once only, for a few minutes; but I have never forgotten him. It was the moment of his death. And we came across him on a shooting trip where the forests melt away towards the vast plains of the Arizona desert. The personality of the man was singularly impressive. I caught myself thinking of a mountain, or of some elemental force of Nature so sure of itself that hurry is never necessary. And his gentleness was like the gentleness of women. Great strength often—the greatest always—has tenderness in it, a depth of tenderness unknown to pettier life.

Our meeting was coincidence, for we were hunting in a region where distances are measured by hours and the chance of running across white men very rare. For many days our nightly camps were pitched in spots of beauty where the loneliness is akin to the loneliness of the Egyptian Desert. On one side the mountain slopes were smothered with dense forest, hiding wee meadows of sweet grass like English lawns; and on the other side, stretching for more miles than a man can count, ran the desolate alkali plains of Arizona where tufts of sagebrush are the only vegetation till you reach the lips of the Colorado Canyons. Our horses were tethered for the night beneath the stars. Two backwoodsmen were cooking dinner. The smell of bacon over a wood fire mingled with the keen and fragrant air—when, suddenly, the horses neighed, signalling the approach of one of their own kind. Indians, white men—probably another hunting party—were within scenting distance, though it was long before my city ears caught any sound, and still longer before the cause itself entered the circle of our firelight.

I saw a square-faced man, tanned like a redskin, in a hunting shirt and a big sombrero, climb down slowly from his horse and move towards us, keenly searching with his eyes; and at the same moment Hank, looking up from the frying-pan where the bacon and venison spluttered in a pool of pork-fat, exclaimed, “ Why, it’s Ezekiel B.!” The next words, addressed to Jake, who held the kettle, were below his breath: “ And if he ain’t all broke up! Jest look at the eyes on him!” I saw what he meant—the face of a human being distraught by some extraordinary emotion, a soul in violent distress, yet betrayal well kept under. Once, as a newspaper man, I had seen a murderer walk to the electric chair. The expression was similar. Death was behind the. eyes, not in them. Smith brought in with him—terror.

In a dozen words we learned he had been hunting for some weeks, but was now heading for Tranter, a “stop-off” station where you could flag the daily train 140 miles southwest. He was making for Smithville, the little town that was the apple of his eye. Something “was wrong” with Smithville. No one asked him what—it is the custom to wait till information is volunteered. But Hank, helping him presently to venison (which he hardly touched), said casually, “Good hunting, Boss, your way?”; and the brief reply told much, and proved how eager he was to relieve his mind by speech. “I’m glad to locate your camp, boys,” he said. “That’s luck. There’s something going wrong “—and a catch came into his voice—“with Smithville.” Behind the laconic statement emerged somehow the terror the man experienced. For Smith to confess cowardice and in the same breath admit mere “luck,” was equivalent to the hysteria that makes city people laugh or cry. It was genuinely dramatic. I have seen nothing more impressive by way of human tragedy—though hard to explain why—than this square-jawed, daunt- less man, sitting there with the firelight on his rugged features, and saying this simple thing. For how in the world could he know it—?

In the pause that followed, his Indians came gliding in, tethered the horses, and sat down without a word to eat what Hank distributed. But nothing was to be read on their impassive faces. Redskins, whatever they may feel, show little. Then Smith gave us another pregnant sentence. “They heard it too,” he said, in a lower voice, indicating his three men; “they saw it jest as I did.” He looked up into the starry sky a second. “It’s hard upon our trail right now,” he added, as though he expected something to drop upon us from the heavens. And from that moment I swear we all felt creepy. The darkness round our lonely camp hid terror in its folds; the wind that whispered through the dry sagebrush brought whispers and the shuffle of watching figures; and when the Indians went softly out to pitch the tents and get more wood for the fire, I remember feeling glad the duty was not mine. Yet this feeling of uneasiness is something one rarely experiences in the open. It belongs to houses, overwrought imaginations, and the presence of evil men. Nature gives peace and security. That we all felt it proves how real it was. And Smith, who felt it most, of course, had brought it.

“There’s something gone wrong with Smithville” was an ominous statement of disaster. He said it just as a man in civilised lands might say, “My wife is dying; a telegram’s just come. I must take the train.” But how he felt so sure of it, a thousand miles away in this uninhabited corner of the wilder- ness, made us feel curiously uneasy. For it was an incredible thing—yet true. We all felt that. Smith did not imagine things. A sense of gloomy apprehension settled over our lonely camp, as though things were about to happen. Already they stalked across the great black night, watching us with many eyes. The wind had risen, and there were sounds among the trees. I, for one, felt no desire to go to bed. The way Smith sat there, watching the sky and peering into the sheet of darkness that veiled the Desert, set my nerves all jangling. He expected something—but what? It was following him. Across this tractless wilder- ness, apparently above him against the brilliant stars, Something was “hard upon his trail.”

Then, in the middle of painful silences, Smith suddenly turned loquacious—further sign with him of deep mental disturbance. He asked questions like a schoolboy—asked them of me too, as being “ an edicated man.” But there were such queer things to talk about round an Arizona campfire that Hank clearly wondered for his sanity. He knew about the “wilderness madness’ that attacks some folks. He let his green cigar go out and flashed me signals to be cautious. He listened intently, with the eyes of a puzzled child, half cynical, half touched with superstitious dread. For, briefly, Smith asked me what I knew about stories of dying men appearing at a distance to those who loved them much. He had read such tales, “heard tell of ’em,” but “are they dead true, or are they jest little feery tales?” I satisfied him as best I could with one or two authentic stories. Whether he believed or not I cannot say; but his swift mind jumped in a flash to the point. “ Then, if that kind o” stuff is true,” he asked, simply, ’ it looks as though a feller had a dooplicate of him- self—sperrit maybe—that gits loose and active at the time of death, and heads straight for the party it loves best. Ain’t that so, Boss?” I admitted the theory was correct. And then he startled us with a final question that made Hank drop an oath below his breath—sure evidence of uneasy excitement in the old backwoodsman. Smith whispered it, looking over his shoulder into the night: “Ain’t it jest possible then,” he asked, “seeing that men an” Nature is all made of a piece like, that places too have this dooplicate appearance of theirselves that gits loose when they go under?”

It was difficult, under the circumstances, to ex- plain that such a theory had been held to account for visions of scenery people sometimes have, and that a city may have a definite personality made up of all its inhabitants—moods, thoughts, feelings, and passions of the multitude who go to compose its life and atmosphere, and that hence is due the odd changes in a man’s individuality when he goes from one city to another. Nor was there any time to do so, for hardly had he asked his singular question when the horses whinnied, the Indians leaped to their feet as if ready for an attack, and Smith himself turned the colour of the ashes that lay in a circle of whitish-grey about the burning wood. There was an expression in his face of death, or, as the Irish peasants say, “destroyed.”

“ That’s Smithville,” he cried, springing to his feet, then tottering so that I thought he must fall into the flame; “that’s my baby town—got loose and huntin” for me, who made it, and love it better’n anything on Gawd’s green earth!” And then he added with a kind of gulp in his throat as of a man who wanted to cry but couldn’t: “And it’s going to bits—it’s dying—and I’m not thar to save it!”

He staggered and I caught his arm. The sound of his frightened, anguished voice, and the shuffling of our many feet among the stones, died away into the night. We all stood, staring. The darkness came up closer. The horses ceased their whinnying. For a moment nothing happened. Then Smith turned slowly round and raised his head towards the stars as though he saw something. “Hear that?” he whispered. “It’s coming up close. That’s what I’ve bin hearing now, on and off, two days and nights. Listen!” His whispering voice broke horribly; the man was suffering atrociously. For a moment he became vastly, horribly animated—then stood still as death.

But in the hollow silence, broken only by the sighing of the wind among the spruces, we at first heard nothing. Then, most curiously, something like rapid driven mist came trooping down the sky, and veiled a group of stars. With it, as from an enormous distance, but growing swiftly nearer, came noises that were beyond all question the noises of a city rushing through the heavens. From all sides they came; and with them there shot a reddish, streaked appearance across the misty veil that swung so rapidly and softly between the stars and our eyes. Lurid it was, and in some way terrible. A sense of helpless bewilderment came over me, scattering my faculties as in scenes of fire, when the mind struggles violently to possess itself and act for the best. Hank, holding his rifle ready to shoot, moved stupidly round the group, equally at a loss, and swearing in- cessantly below his breath. For this overwhelming certainty that Something living had come upon us from the sky possessed us all, and I, personally, felt as if a gigantic Being swept against me through the night, destructive and enveloping, and yet that it was not one, but many. Power of action left me. I could not even observe with accuracy what was going on. I stared, dizzy and bewildered, in all directions; but my power of movement was gone, and my feet refused to stir. Only I remember that the Redskins stood like figures of stone, unmoved.

And the sounds about us grew into a roar. The distant murmur came past us like a sea. There was a babel of shouting. Here, in the deep old wilder- ness that knew no living human beings for hundreds of leagues, there was a tempest of voices calling, crying, shrieking; men’s hoarse clamouring, and the high screaming of women and children. Behind it ran a booming sound like thunder. Yet all of it, while apparently so close above our heads, seemed in some inexplicable way far off in the distance—muted, faint, thinning out among the quiet stars. More like a memory of turmoil and tumult it seemed than the actual uproar heard at first hand. And through it ran the crash of big things tumbling, breaking, falling in destruction with an awful detonating thunder of collapse. I thought the hills were toppling down upon us. A shrieking city, it seemed, fled past us through the sky.

How long it lasted it is impossible to say, for my power of measuring time had utterly vanished. A dreadful wild anguish summed up all the feelings I can remember. It seemed I watched, or read, or dreamed some desolating scene of disaster in which human life went overboard wholesale, as though one threw a hatful of insects into a blazing fire. This idea of burning, of thick suffocating smoke and savage flame, coloured the entire experience. And the next thing I knew was that it had passed away as completely as though it had never been at all; the stars shone down from an air of limpid clearness, and—there was a smell of burning leather in my nostrils. I just stepped back in time to save my feet. I had moved in my excitement against the circle of hot ashes. Hank pushed me back roughly with the barrel of his rifle.

But, strangest of all, I understood, as by some flash of divine intuition, the reason of this abrupt cessation of the horrible tumult. The Personality of the town, set free and loosened in the moment of death, had returned to him who gave it birth, who loved it, and of whose life it was actually an expression. The Being of Smithville was literally a projection, an emanation of the dynamic, vital personality of its puissant creator. And, in death, it had returned on him with the shock of an accu- mulated power impossible for a human being to resist. For years he had provided it with life—but gradually. It now rushed back to its source, thus concentrated, in a single terrific moment.

“ That’s him,” I heard a voice saying from a great distance as it seemed. “He’s fired his last shot—!” and saw Hank turning the body over with his rifle- butt. And, though the face itself was calm beneath the stars, there was an attitude of limbs and body that suggested the bursting of an enormous shell that had twisted every fibre by its awful force yet somehow left the body as a whole intact.

We carried “it” to Tranter, and at the first real station along the line we got the news by telegraph: “ Smithville wiped out by fire. Burned two days and nights. Loss of life, 3000.” And all the way in my dreams I seemed still to hear that curious, dread- ful cry of Smithville, the shrieking city rushing headlong through the sky.